<body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<pb n='73110001' facs='1773-054.pbm'/>
 <div><head>CATH-LODA: A POEM, DUAN FIRST.</head><p> </p></div> <!--  -->
<!-- Vol. 1. B -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110002' facs='1773-057.pbm'/>
 <div><head>ARGUMENT.</head><p> <sc>Fingal</sc>, when very young, making a voyage to the Orkney Iſlands, was driven, by ſtreſs of weather, into a bay of Scandinavia, near the reſidence of Starno, king of Lochlins. Starno invites Fingal to a feaſt, Fingal, doubting the faith of the king, and mindful of a former breach of hoſpitality, refuſes to go.—Starno gathers together his tribes: Fingal reſolves to defend himſelf. — Night coming on, Duth-maruno Propoſes to Fingal, to obſerve the motions of the enemy.— The king himſelf undertakes the watch. Advancing towards the enemy, he, accidentally, comes to the cave of Turthor, where Starno had confined Conban-carglas, the captive daughter of a neighbouring chief. — Her ſtory is imperfect, a part of the original being loſt.— Fingal comes to a place of worſhip, where Starno and his ſon, Swaran, conſulted the ſpirit of Loda, concerning the iſſue of the war.— The rencounter of Fingal and Swaran.— <sc>Duän</sc> firſt concludes with a deſcription of the airy hall of Cruth-loda ſuppoſed to be the Odin of Scandinavia. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110003' facs='1773-060.pbm'/>
<!-- [3] -->
 <div><head>CATH-LODA. DUAN<ptr target='#N_1'/> FIRST.</head><p> A <sc>Tale</sc> of the times of old!</p><p><sc>Why</sc>, thou wanderer unſeen! Thou bender of the thiſtle of Lora ; why, thou breeze of the valley, haſt thou left mine ear ? I hear <!--  -->
<!-- B2 fearing -->
<pb n='73110004' facs='1773-063.pbm'/>
<!-- 4 CATH-LODA: -->
no diſtant roar of ſtreams! No ſound of the harp, from the rock ! Come, thou huntreſs of Lutha, Malvina, call back his ſoul to the bard. I look forward to Lochlin of lakes, to the dark, billowy bay of U-thorno, where Fingal deſcends from Ocean, from the roar of winds. Few are the heroes of Morven, in a land unknown !</p><p><sc>Starno</sc> ſent a dweller of Loda, to bid Fingal to the feaſt; but the King remembered the paſt, and all his rage aroſe, “Nor Gormal's moſſy towers, nor Starno ſhall Fingal behold. Deaths wander, like ſhadows, over his fiery ſoul! Do I ſorget that beam of light, the whitehanded daughter<ptr target='#N_2'/> of kings? Go, ſon of Loda; his words are wind to Fingal : wind, that, to and fro, drives the thiſtle, in autumn's duſky <!--  -->
<!-- Duth- -->
<pb n='73110005' facs='1773-066.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN FIRST. 5 -->
 vale. Duth-maruno<ptr target='#N_3'/>, arm of death ! Crommaglas, of iron ſhields! Struthmor, dweller of battle's wing ! Cormar, whoſe ſhips bound on ſeas, careleſs as the courſe of a meteor, on darkrolling clouds! Ariſe, around me, children of heroes, in a land unknown! Let each look on his ſhield, like Trenmor, the ruler of wars. “Come down, thus Trenmor ſaid, thou dweller between the harps. Thou ſhalt roll this ſtream away, or waſte with me in earth.”</p><p><sc>Around</sc> the king they riſe in wrath. No words come forth : they ſeize their ſpears. Each ſoul is rolled into itſelf. At length the ſudden clang is waked, on all their echoing ſhields. Each takes his hill, by night; at intervals, they darkly ſtand. Unequal burſts the hum of ſongs, between the roaring wind ! <!--  -->
<!-- B 3 Broad -->
<pb n='73110006' facs='1773-069.pbm'/>
<!-- 6 CATH-LODA: -->
 <sc>Broad</sc> over them roſe the moon !</p><p><sc>In</sc> his arms, came tall Duth-maruno; he from Croma of rocks, ſtern hunter of the boar ! In his dark boat he roſe on waves, when Crumthormo<ptr target='#N_4'/> awaked its woods. In the chace he ſhone, among foes: No fear was thine, Duthmaruno !</p><p>“<sc>Son</sc> of daring Comhal, ſhall my ſteps be forward through night? From this ſhield ſhall I view them, over their gleaming tribes? Starno king of lakes, is before me, and Swaran, the foe of ſtrangers. Their words are not in vain, by Loda's ſtone of power. — Should Duthmaruno not return, his ſpouſe is lonely, at home, where meet two roaring ſtreams, on Crathmo-craulo's plain. Around are hills, with echoing woods, the ocean is rolling near. My ſon looks on ſcreaming ſea-fowl, a young wanderer on the field. Give the head of a boar to Can-dona<ptr target='#N_5'/>, tell him of his father's joy, when the <!--  -->
<!-- this -->
<pb n='73110007' facs='1773-072.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN FIRST. 7 -->
 briſtly ſtrength of I-thorno rolled on his lifted ſpear. Tell him of my deeds in war ! Tell where his father fell!'' <!--  -->
<!-- B4 “Not -->
<pb n='73110008' facs='1773-075.pbm'/>
<!-- 8 CATH-LODA: -->
</p><p>“Nor forgetful of my fathers,” ſaid Fingal, “I have bounded over the ſeas. Theirs were the times of danger, in the days of old. Nor ſettles darkneſs on me, before foes, tho' youthful in my locks. Chief of Crathmo-craulo, the field of night is mine.”</p><p>Fingal ruſhed, in all his arms, wide-bounding over Turthor's ſtream, that ſent its ſullen roar, by night, through Gormal's miſty vale. A moon-beam glittered on a rock; in the midſt, ſtood a ſtately form; a form with floating locks, like Lochlin's white-boſomed maids. Unequal are her ſteps, and ſhort. She throws a broken ſong on wind. At times ſhe toſſes her white arms : for grief is dwelling in her ſoul.</p><p>“<sc>Torcul-Torno</sc><ptr target='#N_6'/>, of aged locks !” ſhe ſaid, “where now are thy ſteps, by Lulan? Thou <!--  -->
<!-- chace.</sc> -->
<pb n='73110009' facs='1773-078.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN FIRST. 9 -->
 haſt failed, at thine own dark ſtreams, father of Conban-cârgla ! But I behold thee, chief of Lulan, ſporting by Loda's hall, when the darkſkirted night is rolled along the ſky.—Thou, ſometimes, hideſt the moon, with thy ſhield. I have ſeen her dim, in heaven. Thou kindleſt thy hair into meteors, and faileſt along the night. Why am I forgot, in my cave, king of ſhaggy boars? Look, from the hall of Loda, on thy lonely daughter.”</p><p>“<sc>Who</sc> art thou,” ſaid Fingal, “voice of night ?” </p><p> <sc>She</sc>, trembling, turned away.</p><p>“<sc>Who</sc> art thou, in thy darkneſs ?”</p><p><sc>She</sc> ſhrunk into the cave.</p><p><sc>The</sc> king looſed the thong from her hands. He aſked about her fathers. <!--  -->
<!-- “TORCUL- -->
<pb n='73110010' facs='1773-081.pbm'/>
<!-- 19 CATH-LODA. -->
 “<sc>Torcul-Torno</sc>,” ſhe ſaid, “once dwelt at Lulan's foamy ſtream : he dwelt—but, now, in Loda's hall, he ſhakes the ſounding ſhell. He met Starno of Lochlin, in war ; long fought the dark-eyed kings. My father fell, in his blood, blue-ſhielded Torcul-torno! By a rock, at Lulan's ſtream, I had pierced the bounding roe. My white hand gathered my hair, from off the ruſhing winds. I heard a noiſe. Mine eyes were up. My ſoft breaſt roſe on high. My ſtep was forward, at Lulan, to meet thee, Torcul-torno ! It was Starno, dreadful king ! His red eyes rolled on me in love. Dark waved his ſhaggy brow, above his gathered ſmile. Where is my father; I ſaid, he that was mighty in war? Thou art left alone among foes, O daughter of Torcul-torno! He took my hand. He raiſed the ſail. In this cave he placed me dark. At times, he comes, a gathered miſt. He lifts, before me, my father's ſhield. But often paſſes a beam<ptr target='#N_7'/> of youth, far-diſtant from my cave. The ſon of Starno moves, in my ſight. He dwells lonely in my ſoul.”</p><p>“<sc>Maid</sc> of Lulan,” ſaid Fingal, “white<!--  -->
<!-- handed -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110011' facs='1773-084.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN FIRST. 11 -->
 handed daughter of grief! a cloud, marked with ſtreaks of fire, is rolled along thy ſoul. Look not to that dark-robed moon ; look not to thoſe meteors of heaven. My gleaming ſteel is around thee, the terror of thy foes! It is not the ſteel of the feeble, nor of the dark in ſoul! The maids are not ſhut in our<ptr target='#N_8'/> caves of ſtreams. They toſs not their white arms alone. They bend, fair within their locks, above the harps of Selma. Their voice is not in the deſart wild. We melt along the pleaſing ſound !”</p><p> * * * * * *</p><p><sc>Fingal</sc>, again, advanced his ſteps, wide thro' the boſom of night, to where the trees of Loda ſhook amid ſqually winds. Three ſtones, with heads of moſs, are there; a ſtream, with foaming courſe: and dreadful, rolled around them, is the dark-red cloud of Loda. High from its top looked forward a ghoſt, half-formed of the ſhadowy ſmoak. He poured his voice, at limes, amidſt the roaring ſtream. Near, bend<!--  -->
<!-- ing -->
<!-- 3 -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110012' facs='1773-087.pbm'/>
<!-- 12 CATH-LODA: -->
 ing beneath a blaſted tree, two heroes received his words : Swaran of lakes, and Starno foe of ſtrangers. On their dun ſhields, they darkly leaned : their ſpears are forward through night. Shrill ſounds the blaſt of darkneſs, in Starno's floating beard.</p><p><sc>They</sc> heard the tread of Fingal. The warriors roſe in arms. “Swaran, lay that wanderer low,” ſaid Starno, in his pride. “Take the ſhield of thy father. It is a rock in war.”— Swaran threw his gleaming ſpear. It ſtood fixed in Loda's tree. Then came the foes forward, with ſwords. They mixed their rattling ſteel. Through the thongs of Swaran's thield ruſhed the blade<ptr target='#N_9'/> of Luno. The ſhield fell rolling on earth. Cleft the helmet<ptr target='#N_10'/> fell down. Fingal ſtopt the lifted ſteel. Wrathful ſtood Swaran, unarmed. He rolled his ſilent eyes; he threw his ſword on earth. Then, ſlowly ſtalking over the ſtream, he whiſtled as he went.</p><p><sc>Nor</sc> unſeen of his father is Swaran. Starno turns away in wrath. His ſhaggy brows wave dark, above his gathered rage. He ſtrikes Loda's <!--  -->
<!-- tree, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110013' facs='1773-090.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN FIRST. 13 -->
 tree, with his ſpear. He raiſes the hum of ſongs. They come to the hoſt of Lochlin, each in his own dark path; like two foam-covered ſtreams, from two rainy vales !</p><p>To Turthor's plain Fingal returned. Fair roſe the beam of the eaſt. It ſhone on the ſpoils of Lochlin in the hand of the king. From her cave came forth, in her beauty, the daughter of Torcul-torno. She gathered her hair from wind. She wildly raiſed her ſong. The ſong of Lulan of ſhells, where once her father dwelt. She ſaw Starno's bloody ſhield. Gladneſs roſe, a light, on her face. She ſaw the cleft helmet of Swaran<ptr target='#N_11'/>. She ſhrunk, darkened, from Fingal.—“Art thou fallen, by thy hundred ſtreams, O love of the mournful maid.”</p><p><sc>U-Thorno</sc>, that riſeſt in waters! on whoſe ſide are the meteors of night! I behold the dark moon deſcending, behind thy reſounding woods. On thy top dwells the miſty Loda: the houſe of <!--  -->
<!-- the -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110014' facs='1773-093.pbm'/>
<!-- 14 CATH-LODA: -->
 the ſpirits of men! In the end of his cloudy hall, bends forward Cruth-loda of ſwords. His form is dimly ſeen, amid his wavy miſt. His right-hand is on his ſhield. In his left is the half-viewleſs ſhell. The roof of his dreadful hall is marked, with nightly fires!</p><p><sc>The</sc> race of Cruth-loda advance, a ridge of formleſs ſhades. He reaches the ſounding ſhell, to thoſe who ſhone in war. But, between him and the feeble, his ſhield riſes, a darkened orb. He is a ſetting meteor to the weak in arms. Bright, as a rainbow on ſtreams, came Lulan's white-boſomed maid. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!-- CATH- -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110015' facs='1773-096.pbm'/>
 <div><head>CATH-LODA: A POEM. DUAN SECOND</head><p> </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110016' facs='1773-099.pbm'/>
 <div><head>ARGUMENT.</head><p> FINGAL returning, with day, devolves the command on Duthmaruno, who engages the enemy, and drives them over the ſtream of Turthor. Having recalled his people, he congratulates Duth-maruno on his ſucceſs, but diſcovers, that that hero had been mortally wounded in the action. —Duthmaruno dies. Ulin, the bard, in honour of the dead, introduces the epiſode of Colgorm and Strina-dona, which concludes this <hi>duan</hi>. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110017' facs='1773-102.pbm'/>
<!-- [17] -->
 <div><head>CATH-LODA: DUAN SECOND. </head><p> “<sc>Where</sc> art thou, ſon of the king,” ſaid dark-haired Duth-maruno ? “Where haſt thou failed, young beam of Selma? He returns not, from the boſom of night ! Morning is ſpread on U-thorno. In his miſt is the ſun, on his hill. Warriors, lift the ſhields, in my preſence. He muſt not fall, like a fire from heaven, whoſe place is not marked on the ground. He comes, like an eagle, from the ſkirt of his ſqually wind ! In his hand are the ſpoils of foes. King of Selma, our ſouls were ſad !”</p><p>“<sc>Near</sc> us are the foes, Duth-maruno. They come forward, like waves in miſt, when their foamy tops are ſeen, at times, above the lowſailing vapour. The traveller ſhrinks on his journey ; he knows not whither to fly. No trembling travellers are we ! Sons of heroes call forth the ſteel. Shall the ſword of Fingal ariſe, or ſhall a warrior lead ?” <!--  -->
<!-- Vol.1, C THE -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110018' facs='1773-105.pbm'/>
<!-- 18 CATH-LODA: --><ptr target='#N_010'/> <sc>The</sc> deeds of old, ſaid Duth-maruno, are like paths to our eyes, O Fingal. Broad-ſhielded Trenmor, is ſtill ſeen, amidſt his own dim years. Nor feeble was the ſoul of the king. There, no dark deed wandered in ſecret. From their hundred ſtreams came the tribes, to graſſy Colglancrona. Their chiefs were before them. Each ſtrove to lead the war. Their ſwords were often half-unſheathed. Red rolled their eyes of rage. <!--  -->
<!-- I Separate -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110019' facs='1773-108.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN SECOND. 19 -->
 Separate they ſtood, and hummed their ſurly ſongs. “Why ſhould they yield to each other ? their fathers were equal in war.” Trenmor was there, with his people, ſtately in youthful locks. He ſaw the advancing foe. The grief of his ſoul aroſe. He bade the chiefs to lead, by turns : they led, but they were rolled away. From his own moſſy hill, blue-ſhielded Trenmor came down. He led wide-ſkirted battle, and the ſtrangers failed. Around him the dark-browed warriors came : they ſtruck the ſhield of joy. Like a pleaſant gale, the words of power ruſhed forth from Selma of kings. But the chiefs led, by turns, in war, till mighty danger roſe : then was the hour of the king to conquer in the field.</p><p>“<sc>Not</sc> unknown, ſaid Cromma-glaſs<ptr target='#N_011'/> of <!--  -->
<!-- ſhields, -->
<!--  -->
<!-- C2 country, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110020' facs='1773-111.pbm'/>
<!-- 20 CATH-LODA: -->
 ſhields, are the deeds of our fathers. But who ſhall now lead the war, before the race of kings? Miſt ſettles on theſe four dark hills : within it let each warrior ſtrike his ſhield. Spirits may deſcend in darkneſs, and mark us for the war.”</p><p><sc>They</sc> went, each to his hill of miſt. Bards marked the ſounds of the ſhields. Loudeſt rung thy boſs, Duth-maruno. Thou muſt lead in war!</p><p><sc>Like</sc> the murmur of waters, the race of Uthorno came down. Starno led the battle, and Swaran of ſtormy iſles. They looked forward from iron ſhields, like Cruth-loda fiery-eyed, when he looks from behind the darkened moon, and ſtrews his ſigns on night. The foes met by Turthor's ſtream. They heaved like ridgy waves. Their echoing ſtrokes are mixed. Shadowy death flies over the hoſts. They were clouds of hail, with ſqually winds in their ſkirts. Their <!--  -->
<!-- 8 ſhowers, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110021' facs='1773-114.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN SECOND. 21 -->
 ſhowers are roaring together. Below them ſwells the dark-rolling deep.</p><p><sc>Strife</sc> of gloomy U-thorno, why ſhould I mark thy wounds ! Thou art with the years that are gone ! thou fadeſt on my ſoul !</p><p><sc>Starno</sc> brought forward his ſkirt of war, and Swaran his own dark wing. Nor a harmleſs fire is Duth-maruno's ſword. Lochlin is rolled over her ſtreams. The wrathful kings are loſt in thought. They roll their ſilent eyes, over the flight of their land. The horn of Fingal was heard; the ſons of woody Albion returned. But many lay, by Turthor's ſtream, ſilent in their blood.</p><p><sc>Chief</sc> of Crathmo, ſaid the king, Duthmaruno, hunter of boars ! not harmleſs returns my eagle, from the field of foes! For this whiteboſomed Lanul ſhall brighten, at her ſtreams; Candona ſhall rejoice, as he wanders in Crathmo's fields.</p><p><sc>Colgorm</sc><ptr target='#N_12'/>, replied the chief, was the firſt <!--  -->
<!-- of -->
<!--  -->
<!-- C 3 the -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110022' facs='1773-117.pbm'/>
<!-- 22 CATH-LODA: -->
 of my race in Albion; Colgorm, the rider of ocean, thro' its watry vales. He flew his brother in I-thorno<ptr target='#N_13'/>: he left the land of his fathers. He choſe his place, in ſilence, by rocky Crathmo-craulo. His race came forth, in their years; they came forth to war, but they always fell. The wound of my fathers is mine, king of echoing iſles !</p><p><sc>He</sc> drew an arrow from his ſide! He fell pale, in a land unknown. His ſoul came forth to his fathers, to their ſtormy iſle. There they purſued boars of miſt, along the ſkirts of winds. The chiefs ſtood ſilent around, as the ſtones of Loda, on their hill. The traveller ſees them, through the twilight, from his lonely path. He thinks them the ghoſts of the aged, forming future wars,</p><p><sc>Night</sc> came down, on U-thorno. Still ſtood the chiefs in their grief. The blaſt whiſtled by turns, thro' every warrior's hair. Fingal, at length, broke forth from the thoughts of his ſoul. He called Ullin of harps, and bade the ſong to riſe. “No falling fire, that is only ſeen, and then retires in night ; no <!--  -->
<!-- departing -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110023' facs='1773-120.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN SECOND. 23 -->
 departing meteor was he that is laid ſo low. He was like the ſtrong-beaming ſun, long rejoicing on his hill. Call the names of his fathers, from their dwellings old !”</p><p><sc>I-thorno</sc><ptr target='#N_14'/>, ſaid the bard, that riſeſt midſt ridgy ſeas! Why is thy head ſo gloomy, in the ocean's miſt ? From thy vales came forth a race, fearleſs as thy ſtrong-winged eagles; the race of Colgorm of iron ſhields, dwellers of Loda's hall.</p><p><sc>In</sc> Tormoth's reſounding iſle, aroſe Lurthan, ſtreamy hill. It bent its woody head over a ſilent vale. There, at foamy Cruruth's ſource, dwelt Rurmar, hunter of boars! His daughter was fair as a ſun-beam, white-boſomed Strinadona !</p><p><sc>Many</sc> a king of heroes, and hero of iron ſhields; many a youth of heavy locks came to Rurmar's echoing hall. They came to woo the <!--  -->
<!-- C 4 maid, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110024' facs='1773-123.pbm'/>
<!-- 24 CATH-LODA: -->
 maid, the ſtately huntreſs of Tormoth wild. But thou lookeſt careleſs from thy ſteps, highboſomed Strina-dona !</p><p><sc>If</sc> on the heath ſhe moved, her breaſt was whiter than the down of Cana<ptr target='#N_15'/> ; if on the ſeabeat ſhore, than the foam of the rolling ocean. Her eyes were two ſtars of light. Her face was heaven's bow in ſhowers. Her dark hair flowed round it, like the ſtreaming clouds. Thou wert the dweller of ſouls, white-handed Strina-dona !</p><p><sc>Colgorm</sc> came, in his ſhip, and CorculSuran, king of ſhells. The brothers came, from I-thorno, to woo the ſun-beam of Tormoth wild. She ſaw them in their echoing ſteel. Her ſoul was fixed on þlue-eyed Colgorm. Ul-lochlin's<ptr target='#N_16'/> nightly eye looked in, and ſaw the toſſing arms of Strina-dona.</p><p><sc>Wrathful</sc> the brothers frowned. Their flaming eyes, in ſilence, met. They turned away. They ſtruck their ſhields. Their hands were trembling on their ſwords. They ruſhed into the ſtrife of heroes, for long-haired Strinadona. <!--  -->
<!-- CORCUL- -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110025' facs='1773-126.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN SECOND. 25 -->
 <sc>Corcul-suran</sc> fell in blood. On his iſle, raged the ſtrength of his father. He turned Colgorm, from I-thorno, to wander on all the winds. In Crathmo-craulo's rocky field, he dwelt by a foreign ſtream. Nor darkened the king alone, that beam of light was near, the daughter of echoing Tormoth, white-armed Strina-dona<ptr target='#N_17'/>. <!--  -->
<!-- CATH- -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110026' facs='1773-130.pbm'/>
 </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110027' facs='1773-132.pbm'/>
 <div><head>CATH-LODA: A POEM. DUAN THIRD</head><p> </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110028' facs='1773-133.pbm'/>
 <div><head>ARGUMENT.</head><p> <sc>Oſſian</sc>, after ſome general reflections, deſcribes the ſituation of Fingal, and the poſition of the army of Lochlin.—The converſation of Starno and Swaran.—The epiſode of Corman-trunar and Foinar-bragal.—Starno, from his own example, recommends to Swaran, to ſurprize Fingal, who had retired alone to a neighbouring hill. Upon Swaran's refuſal, Starno undertakes the enterprize himſelf, is overcome, and taken priſoner, by Fingal.—He is diſmiſſed, after a ſevere reprimand for his cruelty. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110029' facs='1773-136.pbm'/>
<!-- [ 29 ] -->
 <div><head>CATH-LODA: DUAN THIRD.</head><p> <sc>Whence</sc> is the ſtream of years? Whither do they roll along? Where have they hid, in miſt, their many-coloured ſides ?</p><p>I look into the times of old, but they ſeem dim to Oſſian's eyes, like reflected moon-beams, on a diſtant lake. Here riſe the red beams of war! There, ſilent, dwells a feeble race ! They mark no years with their deeds, as ſlow they paſs along. Dweller between the ſhields ! thou that awakeſt the failing ſoul! deſcend from thy wall, harp of Cona, with thy voices three ! Come with that which kindles the paſt : rear the forms of old, on their own dark-brown years !<ptr target='#N_30'/> UTHORNO, hill of ſtorms, I behold my race on thy ſide. Fingal is bending, in night, over <!--  -->
<!-- Duth- -->
<!--  -->
<!-- genuine -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110030' facs='1773-139.pbm'/>
<!-- 30 CATH-LODA: -->
 Duth-maruno's tomb. Near him are the ſteps of his heroes, hunters of the boar. By Turthor's ſtream the hoſt of Lochlin is deep in ſhades. The wrathful kings ſtood on two hills ; they looked forward from their boſſy ſhields. They looked forward to the ſtars of night, redwandering in the weſt. Cruth-loda bends from high, like a formleſs meteor in clouds, He ſends <!--  -->
<!-- abroad -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110031' facs='1773-142.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN THIRD. 31 -->
 abroad the winds, and marks them, with his ſigns. Starno foreſaw, that Morven's king was not to yield in war.</p><p><sc>He</sc> twice ſtruck the tree in wrath. He ruſhed before his ſon. He hummed a ſurly ſong ; and heard his hair in wind. Turned<ptr target='#N_31'/> from one another, they ſtood, like two oaks, which different winds had bent; each hangs over its own loud rill, and ſhakes its boughs in the courſe of blaſts.</p><p>“<sc>Annir</sc>,” ſaid Starno of lakes, “was a fire that conſumed of old. He poured death from his eyes, along the ſtriving fields. His joy was in the fall of men. Blood, to him, was a ſummer ſtream, that brings joy to withered vales, from its own moſſy rock. He came forth to the lake Luth-cormo, to meet the tall Colman-trunar, he from Urlor of ſtreams, dweller of battle's wing.” <!--  -->
<!-- “The -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110032' facs='1773-145.pbm'/>
<!-- 32 CATH-LODA: -->
 “<sc>The</sc> chief of Urlor had come to Gormal, with his dark-boſomed ſhips. He ſaw the daughter of Annir, white-armed Foina-brâgal. He ſaw her ! Nor careleſs rolled her eyes, on the rider of ſtormy waves. She fled to his ſhip in darkneſs, like a moon-beam thro' a nightly vale. Annir purſued along the deep; he called the winds of heaven. Nor alone was the king ! Starno was by his ſide. Like U-thorno's young eagle, I turned my eyes on my father.</p><p>We ruſhed into roaring Urlor. With his people came tall Corman-trunar. We fought ; but the foe prevailed. In his wrath my father ſtood. He lopped the young trees, with his ſword. His eyes rolled red in his rage. I marked the ſoul of the king, and I retired in night. From the field  I took a broken helmet : a ſhield that was pierced with ſteel : pointleſs was the ſpear in my hand. I went to find the foe.</p><p><sc>On</sc> a rock ſat tall Corman-trunar, beſide his burning oak ; and near him, beneath a tree, ſat deep-boſomed Foina-brâgal. I threw my broken ſhield before her. I ſpoke the words of peace. “Beſide his rolling ſea, lies Annir of many lakes. The king was pierced in battle ; and Starno is to raiſe his tomb. Me, a fon of Loda, he ſends <!--  -->
<!-- to -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110033' facs='1773-148.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN THIRD. 23 -->
 to white-handed Foina, to bid her ſend a lock from her hair, to reſt with her father, in earth. And thou king of roaring Urlor, let the battle ceaſe, till Annir receive the ſhell, from fiery-eyed Cruth-loda.<ptr target='#N_32'/> <sc>Bursting</sc> into tears, ſhe roſe, and tore a lock from her hair; a lock, which wandered, in the blaſt, along her heaving breaſt. Corman-trunar gave the ſhell; and bade me to rejoice before him, I reſted in the ſhade of night; and hid my face in my helmet deep. Sleep deſcended on the foe. I roſe, like a ſtalking ghoſt. I pierced the ſide of Cormantrunar. Nor did Foina-bragal eſcape. She rolled her white boſom in blood,</p><p><sc>Why</sc> then, daughter of heroes, didſt thou wake my rage ?</p><p><sc>Morning</sc> roſe. The foe were fled, like the departure of miſt. Annir ſtruck his boſſy ſhield. He called his dark-haired ſon. I came, ſtreaked with wandering blood; thrice roſe the <!--  -->
<!-- Vol. I. D ſhout -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110034' facs='1773-151.pbm'/>
<!-- 34 CATH-LODA: -->
 ſhout of the king, like the burſting forth of a ſquall of wind, from a cloud, by night. We rejoiced, three days, above the dead, and called the hawks of heaven. They came, from all their winds, to feaſt on Annir's foes. Swaran! Fingal is alone<ptr target='#N_33'/>, on his hill of night. Let thy ſpear pierce the king in ſecret; like Annir, my ſoul ſhall rejoice.</p><p>“<sc>Son</sc> of Annir,” ſaid Swaran, “I ſhall not ſlay in ſhades. I move forth in light : the hawks ruſh from all their winds. They are wont to trace my courſe : it is not harmleſs thro' war.”</p><p><sc>Burning</sc> roſe the rage of the king. He thrice raiſed his gleaming ſpear. But, ſtarting, he ſpared his ſon; and ruſhed into the night. By Turthor's ſtream a cave is dark, the dwelling of Conban-carglas. There he laid the helmet of kings, and called the maid of Lulan, but ſhe was diſtant far, in Loda's reſounding hall.</p><p><sc>Swelling</sc> in his rage, he ſtrode, to where Fingal lay alone. The King was laid on his ſhield, on his own ſecret hill. <!--  -->
<!-- STERN -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110035' facs='1773-154.pbm'/>
<!-- DUAN THIRD. 35 -->
 <sc>Stern</sc> hunter of ſhaggy boars! no feeble maid is laid before thee. No boy, on his ferny bed, by Turthor's murmuring ſtream. Here is ſpread the couch of the mighty, from which they riſe to deeds of death ! Hunter of ſhaggy boars awaken not the terrible !</p><p><sc>Starno</sc> came murmuring on. Fingal aroſe in arms. “Who art thou, ſon of night?” Silent he threw the ſpear. They mixed their gloomy ſtrife. The ſhield of Starno fell, cleft in twain. He is bound to an oak. The early beam aroſe, It was then Fingal beheld the king. He rolled a while his ſilent eyes. He thought of other days, when white-boſomed Agandecca moved like the muſic of ſongs. He looſed the thong from his hands. Son of Annir, he ſaid, retire. Retire to Gormal of ſhells; a beam that was ſet returns. I remember thy white-boſomed daughter; dreadful king away ! Go to thy troubled dwelling, cloudy foe of the lovely ! Let the ſtranger ſhun thee, thou gloomy in the hall!</p><p>A <sc>TALE</sc> of the times of old! <!--  -->
<!-- D2 -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110036' facs='1773-158.pbm'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
</p></div>
<div type='notes'> <note xml:id='N_1'><p>The bards diſtinguiſhed thoſe compoſitions, in which the narration is often interrupted, by epiſodes and apoſtrophes, by the name of <hi>Duan</hi>. Since the extinction of the order of the bards, it has been a general name for all ancient compoſitions in verſe. The abrupt manner in which the ſtory of this poem begins, may render it obſcure to ſome readers ; it may not therefore be improper, to give here the traditional preface, which is generally prefixed to it. Two years after he took to wife Ros-crana, the daughter of Cormac, king of Ireland, Fingal undertook an expedition into Orkney, to viſit his friend Cathulla, king of Iniſtore. After ſtaying a few days at Caric-thura, the reſidence of Cathulla, the king ſet ſail, to return to Scotland ; but, a violent ſtorm ariſing, his ſhips were driven into a bay of Scandinavia, near Gormal, the ſeat of Starno, king of Lochlin, his avowed enemy. Starno, upon the appearance of ſtrangers on his coaſt, ſummoned together the neighbouring tribes, and advanced, in a hoſtile manner, towards the bay of U-thorno, where Fingal had taken ſhelter. Upon diſcovering who the ſtrangers were, and fearing the valour of Fingal, which he had, more than once, experienced before, he reſolved to accompliſh by treachery what he was afraid he ſhould fail in by open force. He invited, therefore, Fingal to a feaſt, at which he intended to aſſaſſinate him, The king prudently declined to go, and Starno betook himſelf to arms. The ſequel of the ſtory may be learned from the poem itſelf. </p></note><note xml:id='N_2'><p>Agandecca, the daughter of Starno, whom her father killed, on account of her diſcovering to Fingal, a plot laid againſt his life, Her ſtory is related at large, in the third book of Fingal. </p></note><note xml:id='N_3'><p>Duth-maruno is a name very famous in tradition. Many of his great actions are handed down, but the poems, which contained the detail of them, are long ſince loſt. He lived, it is ſuppoſed, in that part of the north of Scotland, which is over againſt Orkney. Duth-maruno, Cromma-glas, Struthmor, and Cormar, are mentioned, as attending Comhal, in his laſt battle againſt the tribe of Morni, in a poem, which is ſtill preſerved. It is not the work of Oſſian ; the phraſeology betrays it to be a modern compoſition. It is ſomething like thoſe trivial compoſitions, which the Iriſh bards forged, under the name of Oſſian, in the fifteenth and ſixteenth centuries. Duth-maruno ſignifies, <hi>black and ſteady</hi>; Cromma-glas, <hi>bending and ſwarthy</hi>; Struthmor, <hi>roaring ſtream</hi> ; Cormar, expert at ſea. </p></note><note xml:id='N_4'><p>Crumthormoth, one of the Orkney or Shetland iſlands, The name is not of Galic original. It was ſubject to its own petty king, who is mentioned in one of Oſſian's poems. </p></note><note xml:id='N_5'><p>Cean-daona, <hi>head of the people</hi>, the ſon of Duth-maruno. He became afterwards famous, in the expeditions of Oſſian, after the death of Fingal. The traditional tales concerning him are very numerous, and, from the epithet, in them, beſtowed on him <hi>(Candona of boars)</hi> it would appear, that he applied himſelf to that kind of hunting, which his father, in this paragraph, is ſo anxious to recommend to him. As I have mentioned the traditional tales of the Highlands, it may not be improper here, to give ſome account of them. After the expulſion of the bards, from the houſes of the chiefs, they, being an indolent race of men, owed all their ſubſiſtence to the generoſity of the vulgar, whom they diverted with repeating tne compoſitions of their predeceſſors, and running up the genealogies of their entertainers to the family of their chiefs. As this ſubject was, however, ſoon exhauſted, they were obliged to have recourſe to invention, and form ſtories having no ſoundation in fact which were ſwallowed, with great credulity, by an ignorant multitude. By frequent repeating, the fable grew upon their hands, and, as each threw in whatever circumſtance he thought conducive to raiſe the admiration of his hearers, the ſtory became, at laſt, ſo devoid of all probability, that even the vulgar themſelves did nor believe it. They, however, liked the tales ſo well, that the bards ſound their advantage in turning profeſſed tale makers. They then launched out into the wildeſt regions of fiction and romance. I firmly believe, there are more ſtories of giants, enchanted caſtles, dwarfs, and palfreys, in the Highlands, than in any country in Europe. Theſe tales, it is certain, like other romantic compoſitions, have many things in them unnatural, and, conſequently, diſguſtful to true taſte, but, I know not how it happens, they command attention more than any other fictions I ever met with. The extreme length of theſe pieces is very ſurpriſing, ſome of them requiring many days to repeat them, but ſuch hold they take of the memory, that few circumſtances are ever omitted by thoſe who have received them only from oral tradition : What is ſtill more amazing, the very language of the bards is ſtill preſerved. It is curious to ſee, that the deſcriptions of magnificence, introduced in theſe tales, is even ſuperior to all the pompous oriental fictions of the kind. </p></note><note xml:id='N_6'><p>Torcul-torno, according to tradition, was king of CrathJun, a diſtrict in Sweden. The river Lulan ran near the reſidence of Torcul-torno. There is a river in Sweden, ſtill called Lula, which is probably the ſame with Lulan. The war between Starno and Torcul-torno, which terminated in the death of the latter, had its riſe at a hunting party. Starno being invited, in a friendly manner, by Torcul-rorno, both Kings, with their followers, went to the mountains of Stivamore, to hunt. A boar ruſhed from the wood before the kings, and Torcul-torno killed it. Starno thought this behaviour a breach upon the privilege of gueſts, who were always, <hi>honoured</hi>, as tradition expreſſes it, <hi>with the danger of the</hi> <sc>chace</sc>, A quarrel aroſe, the kings came to battle, with all their attendants, and the party of Torcul-torno were totally defeated, and he himſelf ſlain. Starno purſued his viſtory, laid waſte the diſtrict of Crathlun, and, coming to the reſidence of Torcul torno, carried off, by force, Conban-carglas, the beautiful daughter of his enemy. Her he confined in a cave, near the palace of Gormal, where, on account of her cruel treatment, ſhe became diſtracted.</p><p>The paragraph, juſt now before us, is the ſong of Conbancarglas, at the time ſhe was diſcovered by Fingal. It is in Lyric meaſure, and ſet to muſic, which is wild and ſimple, and ſo inimitably ſuited to the ſituation of the unhappy lady, that few can hear it without tears. </p></note><note xml:id='N_7'><p>By the <hi>beam of youth</hi>, it afterwards appears, that Conbancarglas means Swaran, the ſon of Starno, with whom, during her confinement, ſhe had fallen in love. </p></note><note xml:id='N_8'><p>From this contraſt, which Fingal draws, between his own nation, and the inhabitants of Scandinavia, we may learn, that the former were much leſs barbarous than the latter, This distinction is ſo much obſerved throughout the poems of Oſſian, that there can be no doubt, that he followed the real manners of both nations in his own time. At the cloſe of the ſpeech of Fingal, there is a great part of the original loſt. </p></note><note xml:id='N_9'><p>The ſword of Fingal, ſo called from its maker, Luno of Lochlin. </p></note><note xml:id='N_10'><p>The helmet of Swaran. The behaviour of Fingal is always conſiſtent with that generoſity of ſpirit which belongs to a hero. He takes no advantage of a foe diſarmed. </p></note><note xml:id='N_11'><p>Conban-carglas, from ſeeing the helmet of Swaran bloody in the hands of Fingal conjectured, that that hero was killed. A part of the original is loſt, It appears, however, from the ſequel of the poem, that the daughter of Torcultorno did not long ſurvive her ſurprize, occaſioned by the ſuppoſed death of her lover. The deſcription of the airy hall of Loda (which is ſuppoſed to be the ſame with that of Odin, the deity of Scandinavia) is more pictureſque and deſcriptive, than any in the Edda, or other works of the northern Scalders. </p></note><note xml:id='N_010'><p> In this ſhort epiſode we have a very probable account given us, of the origin of monarchy in Caledonia. The <sc>Caël</sc> or Gauls, who poſeſſed the countries to the north of the Firth of Edinburgh, were, originally, a number of diſtinct tribes, or clans, each ſubject to its own chief, who was free and independent of any other power. When the Romans invaded them, the common danger might, perhaps, have induced thoſe <sc>reguli</sc> to join together, but, as they were unwilling to yield to the command of one of their own number, their battles were ill-conducted, and, conſequently, unſucceſsful. Trenmor was the firſt who repreſented to the chiefs, the bad conſequences of carrying on their wars in this irregular manner, and adviſed, that they themſelves ſhould alternately lead in battle. They did ſo, but they were unſucceſsful. When it came to Trenmor's turn, he totally defeated the enemy, by his ſuperior valour and conduct, which gained him ſuch an intereſt among the tribes, that he, and his family after him, were regarded as kings; or to uſe the poet's expreſſion, <sc>the words of power ruſhed forth from Selma of kings</sc>. The regal authority, however, except in time of war, was but inconſiderable; for every chief, within his own diſtrict, was abſolute and independent. From the ſcene of the battle in this epiſode, (which was in the valley of Crona, a little to the north of Agricola's wall) I ſhould ſuppoſe, that the enemies of the Caledonians were the Romans, or provincial Britons. </p></note><note xml:id='N_011'><p> In tradition, this Cromma glas makes a great figure in that battle which Comhal loſt, together with his life, to the tribe of Morni, I have juſt now, in my hands, an Iriſh compoſition, of a very modern date, as appears from the language, in which all the traditions, concerning that deciſive engagement, are jumbled together. In juſtice to the merit of the poem, I ſhould have here preſented to the reader a tranſlation of it, did not the bard mention ſome circumſtances very ridiculous, and others altogether indecent. Morna, the wife of Comhal, had a principal hand in all the tranſactions previous to the defeat and death of her huſband ; ſhe, to uſe the words of the bard, <sc>who was the guiding ſtar of the women of Erin</sc>. The bard, it is to be hoped, miſrepreſented the ladies of his</p><p>country, for Morna's behaviour was, according to him, ſo void of all decency and virtue, that it cannot be ſuppoſed, they had choſen her for their <hi>guiding ſtar</hi>, The poem conſiſts of many ſtanzas. The language is figurative, and the numbers harmonious ; but the piece is ſo full of anachroniſms, and ſo unequal in its compoſition, that the author, moſt undoubtedly, was either mad, or drunk, when he wrote it. It is worthy of being remarked, that Comhal is, in this poem, very often called, <hi>Comhal na h'Albin</hi>, or <hi>Comhal of Albion</hi>, which ſufficiently demonſtrates, that the allegations of Keating and O'Flaherty, concerning <hi>Fion Mac-Comnal</hi>, are but of late invention. </p></note><note xml:id='N_12'><p> The family of Duth-maruno, it appears, came originally from Scandinavia, or, at leaſt, from ſome of the northern Iles, ſubject, in chief, to the kings of Lochlin. The Highland ſenachies, who never miſſed to make their comments on, and additions to, the works of Oſſian, have given us a long liſt of the anceſtors of Duth maruno, and a particular account of their actions, many of which are of the marvellous kind. One of the tale-makers of the north has choſen for his hero, Starnmor,</p><p>the father of Duth-maruno, and, conſidering the adventures thro' which he has led him, the piece is neither diſagreeable, nor abounding with that kind of fiction, which ſhocks credibility. </p></note><note xml:id='N_13'><p> An iſland of Scandinavia, </p></note><note xml:id='N_14'><p> This epiſode is, in the original, extremely beautiful. It is ſet to that wild kind of muſic, which ſome of the Highlanders diſtinguith, by the title of <hi>Fón Oimarra</hi>, or, the <hi>Song of mermaids</hi>. Some part of the air is abſolutely infernal, but there are many returns in the meaſure, which are inexpreſſibly wild and beautiful. From the genius of the muſic, I ſhould think it came originally from Scandinavia, for the fictions delivered down concerning the <hi>Oi-marra</hi>, (who are reputed the authors of the muſic) exactly correſpond with the notions of the northern nations, concerning their <hi>diræ</hi>, or <hi>goddeſſes of death</hi>, —Of all the names in this epiſode, there is none of a Galic original, except Strina-dona, which signifies, the <hi>ſtrife of heroes</hi>. </p></note><note xml:id='N_15'><p> The <sc>Cana</sc> is a certain kind of graſs, which grows plentiful in the heathy moraſſes of the north. Its ſtalk is of the reedy kind, and it carries a tuft of down, very much reſembling cotton. It is exceſſively white, and, conſequently often introduced by the bards, in their ſimiles concerning the beauty of women. </p></note><note xml:id='N_16'><p> Ul-locklin, <hi>the guide to Lochlin</hi> ; the name of a ſtar. </p></note><note xml:id='N_17'><p> The continuation of this epiſode is juſt now in my hands ; but the language is ſo different from, and the ideas ſo unworthy of, Oſſian, that I have rejected it, as an interpolation by a modern bard. </p></note><note xml:id='N_30'><p> The bards, who were always ready to ſupply what they thought deficient in the poems of Oſſian, have inſerted a great many incidents between the ſecond and third <hi>duän</hi> of Cathloda. Their interpolations are ſo eaſily diſtinguiſhed from the</p><p>genuine remains of Oſſian, that it took me very little time to mark them out, and totally to reject them. If the modern Scotch and Iriſh bards have ſhewn any judgment, it is in aſcribing their own compoſitions to names of antiquity, for, by that means, they themſelves have eſcaped that contempt, which the authors of ſuch futile performances muſt, neceſſarily, have met with, from people of true taſte. I was led into this obſervation, by an Iriſh poem, juſt now before me. It concerns a deſcent made by Swaran, king of Lochlin, on Ireland, and is the work, ſays the traditional preface prefixed to it, of <hi>Oſſian Mac-Fion</hi>. It however appears, from ſeveral pious ejaculations, that it was rather the compoſition of ſome good prieſt, in the fifteenth or ſixteenth century, for he ſpeaks; with great devotion, of pilgrimage, and more particularly, of the <hi>blue-eyed daughters of the convent</hi>. Religious, however, as this poet was, he was not altogether decent, in the ſcenes he introduces between Swaran and the wife of <hi>Congcullion</hi>, both of whom he repreſents as giants. It happening unfortunately, that <hi>Congcullion</hi> was only of a moderate ſtature, his wife without heſitation, preferred Swaran, as a more adequate match for her own gigantic ſize. From this fatal preference proceeded ſo much miſchief, that the good poet altogether loſt ſight of his principal action, and he ends the piece, with an advice to men, in the choice of their wives, which, however good it may be, I ſhall leave concealed in the obſcurity of the original. </p></note><note xml:id='N_31'><p> The ſurly attitude of Starno and Swaran is well adapted to their fierce and uncomplying diſpoſitions. Their characters, at firſt ſight, ſeem little different ; but, upon examination, we find that the poet has dexterouſly diſtinguiſhed between them. They were both dark, ſtubborn, haughty and reſerved ; but Starno was cunning, revengeful, and cruel, to the higheſt degree; the diſpoſition of Swaran, though ſavage, was leſs bloody, and ſomewhat tinctured with generoſity. It is doing injuſtice to Oſſian, to ſay, that he has not a great variety of characters. </p></note><note xml:id='N_32'><p> Oſſian is very partial to the fair ſex. Even the daughter of the cruel Annir, the ſiſter of the revengeful and bloody Starno, partakes not of thoſe diſagreeable characters ſo peculiar to her family. She is altogether tender and delicate. Homer, of all ancient poets, uſes the ſex with leaſt ceremony. His cold contempt is even worſe, than the downright abuſe of the moderns ; for to draw abuſe implies the poſſeſſion of ſome merit. </p></note><note xml:id='N_33'><p> Fingal, according to the cuſtom of the Caledonian kings, had retired to a hill alone, as he himſelf was to reſume the command of the army the next day. Starno might have ſome intelligence of the king's retiring, which occaſions his requeſt to Sweran, to ſtab him ; as he foreſaw, by his art of divination, that he could not overcome him in open battle. </p></note></div></body>
