<body>
<pb n='73110126' facs='1773-419.pbm'/>
 <div><head>ARGUMENT.</head><p> Malvina the daughter of Toſcar is overheard by Oſſian lamenting the death of Oſcar her lover. Oſſian, to divert her grief, relates his own actions in an expedition which he undertook, at Fingal's command, to aid Crothar the petty king of Croma, a country in Ireland, againſt Rothmar who invaded his dominions. The ſtory is delivered down thus in tradition. Crothar king of Croma being blind with age, and his fon too young for the field, Rothmar the chief of Tromlo reſolved to avail himſelf of the opportunity offered of annexing the dominions of Crothar to his own. He accordingly marched into the country ſubject to Crothar, but which he held of Arth or Artho, who was, at the time, ſupreme king of Ireland.</p><p>Crothar being, on account of his age and blindneſs, unfit for action, ſent for aid to Fingal king of Scotland; who ordered his ſon Oſſian to the relief of Crothar. But before his arrival Fovargormo, the ſon of Crothar, attacking Rothmar, was ſlain himſelf, and his forces totally defeated. Oſſian renewed the war; came to battle, killed Rothmar, and routed his army, Croma being thus delivered of its enemies, Oſſian returned to Scotland. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110127' facs='1773-422.pbm'/>
<!-- [227 ] -->
 <div><head>CROMA: A POEM.</head><p> “<sc>It</sc> was the voice of my love! ſeldom art thou, in the dreams of Malvina! Open your airy halls, O fathers of Toſcar of ſhields ! Unfold the gates of your clouds : the ſteps of Malvina are near. I have heard a voice in my dream. I feel the fluttering of my ſoul. Why didſt thou come, O blaſt, from the dark-rolling face of the lake? Thy ruſtling wing was in the tree; the dream of Malvina fled. But ſhe beheld her love, when his robe of miſt flew on the wind. A ſun-beam was on his ſkirts, they glittered like the gold of the ſtranger. It was the voice of my love! ſeldom comes he to my dreams!”</p><p>“<sc>But</sc> thou dwelleſt in the ſoul of Malvina, ſon of mighty Oſſian! My ſighs ariſe with the beam of the eaſt; my tears deſcend with the drops of night. I was a lovely tree, in thy <!--  -->
<!-- preſence, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110128' facs='1773-425.pbm'/>
<!-- 128 CR O M A: -->
 preſence, Oſcar, with all my branches round me; but thy death came like a blaſt from the deſart, and laid my green head low. The ſpring returned with its ſhowers; no leaf of mine aroſe ! The virgins ſaw me ſilent in the hall; they touched the harp of joy. The tear was on the cheek of Malvina : the virgins beheld me in my grief. Why art thou ſad, they ſaid ; thou firſt of the maids of Lutha? Was he lovely as the beam of the morning, and ſtately in thy ſight?”</p><p><sc>Pleasant</sc> is thy ſong in Oſſian's ear, daughter of ſtreamy Lutha! Thou haſt heard the muſic of departed bards, in the dream of thy reſt, when ſleep fell on thine eyes, at the murmur of Moruth<ptr target='#N_1'/>. When thou didſt return from the chace, in the day of the ſun, thou haſt heard the muſic of bards, and thy ſong is lovely ! It is lovely, O Malvina, but it melts the ſoul. There is a joy in grief when peace dwells in the breaſt of the ſad. But ſorrow waſtes the mournful, O daughter of Toſcar, and their days are few! They fall away, like the flower on which the ſun hath looked in his ſtrength after the mildew has paſſed over it, when its head is heavy with the drops of night. Attend to the tale of Oſſian, O maid. He remembers the days of his youth !</p><p><!--  -->
<!-- THrHs -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110129' facs='1773-428.pbm'/>
<!-- A P OE M. 129 -->
</p><p><sc>The</sc> king commanded; I raiſed my ſails, and ruſhed into the bay of Croma; into Croma's ſounding bay in lovely Inisfail<ptr target='#N_2'/>. High on the coaſt aroſe the towers of Crothar king of ſpears; Crothar renowned in the battles of his youth ; but age dwelt then around the chief. Rothmar had raiſed the ſword againſt the hero; and the wrath of Fingal burned. He ſent Oſſian to meet Rothmar in war, for the chief of Croma was the friend of his youth. I ſent the bard before me with ſongs. I came into the hall of Crothar. There ſat the chief amidſt the arms of his fathers, but his eyes had failed. His grey locks waved around a ſtaff, on which the warrior leaned. He hummed the ſong of other times, when the ſound of our arms reached his ears. Crothar roſe, ſtretched his aged hand and bleſſed the ſon of Fingal.</p><p>“<sc>Ossian</sc>!” ſaid the hero, “the ſtrength of Crothar's arm has failed, O could I lift the ſword, as on the day that Fingal fought at Strutha ! He was the firſt of men ! but Crothar had alſo his fame. The king of Morven praiſed me ; he placed on my arm the boſſy ſhield of Calthar, whom the king had flain in his wars. Doſt thou not behold it on the wall, for Cro<!--  -->
<!-- Vol. 1. K that's -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110130' facs='1773-431.pbm'/>
<!-- 1309 C R O MM A . -->
 thar's eyes have failed ? Is thy ſtrength, like thy fathers, Oſſian ? let the aged feel thine arm !”</p><p><sc>I gave</sc> my arm to the king; he felt it with his aged hands. The ſigh roſe in his breaſt, and his tears came down. “Thou art ſtrong, my ſon, he ſaid, but not like the king of Morven! But who is like the hero among the mighty in war! Let the feaſt of my hall be ſpread; and let my bards exalt the ſong. Great is he that is within my walls, ye ſons of eechoing Croma !” The feaſt is ſpread. The harp is heard; and joy is in the hall. But it was joy covering a ſigh, that darkly dwelt in every breaſt. It was like the faint beam of the moon ſpread on a cloud in heaven. At length the muſic ceaſed, and the aged king of Croma ſpoke; he ſpoke without a tear, but ſorrow ſwelled in the midſt of his voice.</p><p>“<sc>Son</sc> of Fingal! behold'ſt thou not the darkneſs of Crothar's joy? My ſoul was not ſad at the feaſt, when my people lived before me. I rejoiced in the preſence of ſtrangers, when my ſon ſhone in the hall, But, Oſſian, he is a beam that is departed. He left no ſtreak of light behind. He is fallen, ſon of Fingal, in the wars of his father. Rothmar the chief of graſſy Tromlo heard that theſe eyes had failed; he heard that my arms were fixed in the hall, <!--  -->
<!-- and -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110131' facs='1773-434.pbm'/>
<!-- A PO E M. 131 -->
 and the pride of his ſoul aroſe! He came towards Croma ; my people fell before him. I took my arms in my wrath, but what could ſightleſs Crothar do? My ſteps were unequal; my grief was great. I wiſhed for the days that were paſt. Days! wherein I fought; and won in the field of blood. My ſon returned from the chace ; the fair-haired Fovar-gormo<ptr target='#N_3'/>. He had not lifted his ſword in battle, for his arm was young. But the ſoul of the youth was great ; the fire of valour burnt in his eyes. He ſaw the diſordered ſteps of his father, and his ſigh aroſe. “King of Croma,” he ſaid, “is it becauſe thou haſt no ſon; is it for the weakneſs of Forar-gormo's arm that thy ſighs ariſe ? I begin, my father, to feel my ſtrength ; I have drawn the ſword of my youth; and I have bent the bow. Let me meet this Rothmar, with the ſons of Croma : let me meet him, O my father; I feel my burning ſoul!” And thou ſhalt meet him, I ſaid, ſon of the ſightleſs Crothar ! But let others advance before thee, that I may hear the tread of thy feet at thy return; for my eyes behold thee not, fairhaired Fovar-gormo ! He went, he met the foe; he fell. Rothmar advances to Crema. He who flew my ſon is near, with all his pointed ſpears.” <!--  -->
<!-- K 2 Tris -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110132' facs='1773-437.pbm'/>
<!-- £22 CR O M A: -->
</p><p><sc>This</sc> is no time to fill the ſhell, I replied, and took my ſpear! My people ſaw the fire of my eyes ; they all aroſe around. Through night we ſtrode along the heath. Grey morning roſe in the eaſt. A green narrow vale appeared before us; nor wanting was its winding ſtream. The dark hoſt of Rothmar are on its banks, with all their glittering arms. We fought along the vale. They fled. Rothmar ſunk beneath my ſword ! Day had not deſcended in the weſt, when I brought his arms to Crothar. The aged hero felt them with his hands; and joy brightened over all his thoughts.</p><p><sc>The</sc> people gather to the hall. The ſhells of the feaſt are heard. Ten harps are ſtrung ; five bards advance, and ſing, by turns<ptr target='#N_4'/>, the praiſe <!--  -->
<!-- of -->
<!--  -->
<!-- FixsT -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110133' facs='1773-440.pbm'/>
<!-- A P O E M, 132 -->
 of Oſſian ; they poured forth their burning ſouls, and the ſtring anſwered to their voice. The joy of Croma was great : for peace returned to the <!--  -->
<!-- land. -->
<!--  -->
<!-- K 5 1] he -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110134' facs='1773-443.pbm'/>
<!-- 134 C R O M 8a: -->
 land. The night came on with ſilence; the morning returned with joy. No foe came in darkneſs, with his glittering ſpear. The joy of Croma was great; for the gloomy Rothmar had fallen! <!--  -->
<!-- I xaristD -->
<!--  -->
<!-- yes -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110135' facs='1773-446.pbm'/>
<!-- A P O E M. 136 -->
 <sc>I raised</sc> my voice for Fovar-gormo, when they laid the chief in earth. The aged Crothar was there, but his ſigh was not heard. He <!--  -->
<!-- ſearched -->
<!--  -->
<!-- k 4 15 -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110136' facs='1773-449.pbm'/>
<!-- 136 CR oO M A: -->
 ſearched for the wound of his ſon, and ſound it in his breaſt. Joy roſe in the face of the aged. <!--  -->
<!-- — Hg -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110137' facs='1773-452.pbm'/>
<!--  -->
<!-- A P O E M. 137 -->
</p><p>He came and ſpoke to Oſſian, “King of ſpears !” he ſaid, “my ſon has not fallen without his fame. The young warrior did not fly; but met death, as he went forward in his ſtrength. Happy are they who die in youth, when their renown is heard! The feeble will not behold them in the hall; or ſmile at their trembling hands. Their memory ſhall be honoured in ſong ; the young tear of the virgin will fall. But the aged wither away, by degrees, the fame of their youth, while yet they live is all forgot. They fall in ſecret. The ſigh of their ſon is not heard. Joy is around their tomb; the ſtone of their fame is placed without a tear. Happy are they who die in youth, when their renown is around them. <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='73110138' facs='1773-416.pbm'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
</p></div>
<div type='notes'> <note xml:id='N_1'><p> Mor'-ruth, <hi>great ſtream.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_2'><p> <hi>Inisfail</hi>, one of the ancient names of Ireland. </p></note><note xml:id='N_3'><p> Faobhar-gorm, <hi>the blue point of ſteel.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_4'><p> Thoſe extempore compoſitions were in great repute among ſucceeding bards. The pieces extant of that kind ſhew more of the good ear, than of the poetical genius of their authors. The tranſlator has only met with one poem of this ſort, which he thinks worthy of being preſerved. It is a thouſand years later than Oſſian, but the authors ſeem to have obſerved his manner, and adopted ſome of his expreſſions. The ſtory of it is this. Five bards, paſſing the night in the houſe of a chief, who was a poet himſelf, went ſeverally to make their obſervations on, and returned with an extempore deſcription of, night. The night happened to be one in October, as appears from the poem, and in the north of Scotland, it has all that variety which the bards aſcribe to it, in their deſcriptions.</p><sp><speaker><sc>First Bard.</sc></speaker><p> <sc>Night</sc> is dull and dark. The clouds reſt on the hills. No ſtar with green trembling beam; no moon looks from the ſky. I hear the blaſt in the wood ; but I hear it diſtant far. The ſtream of the valley murmurs; but its murmur is ſullen and ſad. From the tree at the grave of the dead the long-howling owl is heard. I ſee a dim form on the plain! It is a ghoſt ! it fades, it flies. Some funeral ſhall paſs this way : the meteor marks the path.</p><p>The diſtant dog is howling from the hut of the hill, The ſtag lies on the mountain moſs :the hind is at his hide, She hears the wind in his branchy horns. She ſtarts, but lies again,</p><p>The roe is in the cleft of the rock ; the heath-cock's head is beneath his wing. No beaſt, no bird is abroad, but the owl and the howling fox. She on a leafleſs tree: he in a cloud on the hill,</p><p>Dark, panting, trembling, ſad the traveller has loſt his way, Through ſhrubs, through thorns, he goes, along the gurgling rill. He fears the rock and the fen. He fears the ghoſt of night. The old tree groans to the blaſt; the falling branch reſounds. The wind drives the withered burs, clung together, along the graſs. It is the light tread of a ghoſt! He trembles amidſt the night.</p><p>Dark, duſky, howling is night, cloudy, windy, and full of ghoſts! The dead are abroad! my friends, receive me from the night.</p><p></p></sp><sp><speaker><sc>Second Bard,</sc></speaker><p> The wind is up. The ſhower deſcends. The ſpirit of the mountain ſhrieks. Woods fall from high. Windows flap. The growing river roars. The traveller attempts the ford.</p><p> Hark that ſhriek! he dies; The ſtorm drives the horſe from the hill, the goat, the lowing cow. They tremble as drives the ſhower, beſide the mouldering bank,</p><p>The hunter ſtarts from ſleep, in his lonely hut; he wakes the fire decayed. His wet dogs ſmoke around him. He fills the chinks with heath, Loud roar two mountain ſtreams which meet beſide his booth.</p><p>Sad on the ſide of a hill the wandering ſhepherd ſits. The tree reſounds above him. The ſtream roars down the rock. He waits for the riſing moon to guide him to his home.</p><p>Ghoſts ride on the ſtorm to-night. Sweet is their voice between the ſqualls of wind. Their ſongs are of other worlds.</p><p>The rain is paſt. The dry wind blows. Streams roar, and windows flap. Cold drops fall from the roof. I ſee the ſtarry ſky. But the ſhower gathers again. The weſt is gloomy and dark. Night is ſtormy and diſmal; receive me, my friends, from night. </p><p></p></sp><sp><speaker><sc>Third Bard</sc>.</speaker><p> The wind ſtill ſounds between the hills: and whiſtles through the graſs of the rock. The firs fall from their place. The turfy hut is torn. The clouds, divided, fly over the ſky, and ſhew the burning ſtars. The meteor, token of death! flies ſparkling through the gloom. It reſts on the hill. I ſee the withered fern, the dark-browed rock, the fallen oak. Who is that in his ſhrowd beneath the tree, by the ſtream ?</p><p>The waves dark-tumble on the lake, and laſh its rocky ſides. The boat is brimfull in the cove; the oars on the rocking tide. A maid ſits ſad beſide the rock, and eyes the rolling ſtream. Her lover promiſed to come. She ſaw his boat, when</p><p>yet it was light, on the lake. Is this his broken boat on the ſhore ? Are theſe his groans on the wind?</p><p>Hark! the hail rattles around. The flaky ſnow deſcends, The tops of the hills are white. The ſtormy winds abate. Various is the night and cold; receive me, my friends, from night. </p></sp><sp><speaker><sc>Fourth Bard.</sc></speaker><p> Night is calm and fair; blue, ſtarry, ſettled is night. The winds, with the clouds, are gone. They ſink behind the hill. The moon is up on the mountain. Trees gliſter : ſtreams ſhine on the rock. Bright rolls the ſettled lake ; bright the ſtream of the vale.</p><p>I ſee the trees overturned ; the ſhocks of corn on the plain. The wakeful hind rebuilds the ſhocks, and whiſtles on the diſtant field.</p><p>Calm, ſettled, fair is night! Who comes from the place of the dead ? That form with the robe of ſnow ; white arms and dark-brown hair! It is the daughter of the chief of the people : ſhe that lately fell! Come, let us view thee, O maid! thou that haſt been the delight of heroes! The blaſt drives the phantom away; white, without form, it aſcends the hill.</p><p>The breezes drive the blue miſt, ſlowly over the narrow vale. It riſes on the hill, and joins its head to heaven. Night is ſettled, calm, blue, ſtarry, bright with the moon. Receive me not, my friends, for lovely is the night. </p></sp><sp><speaker><sc>Fifth Bard.</sc></speaker><p> Night is calm, but dreary. The moon is in a cloud in the weſt. Slow moves that pale beam along the ſhaded hill, The giant wave is heard. The torrent murmurs on the rock. The cock is heard from the booth. More than half the night</p><p>is paſt, The houſe-wife, groping in the gloom, rekindles the ſettled fire. The hunter thinks that day approaches, and calls his bounding dogs. He aſcends the hill and whiſtles on his way. A blaſt removes the cloud. He ſees the ſtarry plough of the north Much of the night is to paſs. He nods by the moſſy rock.</p><p>Hark! the whirlwind is in the wood ! A low murmur in the vale! it is the mighty army of the dead returning from the air.</p><p>The moon reſts behind the hill. The beam is ſtill on that lofty rock. Long are the ſhadows of the trees. Now it is dark over all. Night is dreary, ſilent, and dark; receive me, my friends, from night.</p><p></p></sp><sp><speaker><sc>The Chief.</sc></speaker><p> Let clouds reſt on the hills: ſpirits fly and travellers fear. Let the winds of the woods ariſe, the ſounding ſtorms deſcend. Roar ſtreams and windows flap, and green winged meteors fly ; riſe the pale moon from behind her hills, or incloſe her head in clouds; night is alike to me, blue, ſtormy, or gloomy the ſky. Night flies before the beam, when it is poured on the hill. The young day returns from his clouds, but we return no more.</p><p>Where are our chiefs of old? Where our kings of mighty name? The ſhields of their battles are ſilent. Scarce their moſſy tombs remain. We ſhall alſo be forgot. This lofty houſe ſhall fall. Our ſons ſhall not behold the ruins in graſs. They ſhall aſk of the aged, “Where ſtood the walls of our fathers ?”</p><p>Raiſe the ſong, and ſtrike the harp ; ſend round the ſhells of joy, Suſpend a hundred tapers on high. Youths and maids begin the dance. Let ſome gray bard be near me to tell the deeds of other times ; of kings renowned in our land, of chiefs we behold no more. Thus let the night paſs until morning ſhall appear in our halls. Then let the bow be at hand, the dogs, the youths of the chace. We ſhall aſcend the hill with day ; and awake the deer. </p></sp> </note></div></body>
