<body>
<pb n='1773-684.pbm.txt'/>
 <div><head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. In SIX BOOKS.</head><p></p><p></p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-687.pbm.txt'/>
 <div><head>ARGUMENT to <sc>Book</sc> I.</head><p> Cuthullin, (general of the Iriſh tribes, in the minority of Cormac, king of Ireland) ſitting alone beneath a tree, at the gate of Tura, a caſtle of Ulſter, (the other chiefs having gone on a hunting party to Cromla, a neighbouring hill) is informed of the landing of Swaran, king of Lochlin, by Moran, the ſon of Fithil, one of his ſcouts. He convenes the chiefs ; a council is held, and diſputes run high about giving, battle to the enemy. Connal, the petty king of Togorma, and an intimate friend of Cuthullin, was for retreating till Fingal, king of thoſe Caledonians who inhabited the north-weſt coaſt of Scotland, whoſe aid had been previouſly ſollicited, ſhould arrive ; but Calmar, the ſon of Matha, lord of Lara, a country in Connaught, was for engaging the enemy immediately. Cuthullin, of himſelf willing to fight, went into the opinion of Calmar. Marching towards the enemy, he miſſed three of his braveſt heroes, Fergus, Duchomar, and Cathba. Fergus arriving, tells Cuthullin of the death of the two other chiefs ; which introduces the affecting epiſode of Morna, the daughter of Cormac. The army of Cuthullin is deſcried at a diſtance by Swaran, who ſent the ſon of Arno to obſerve the motions of the enemy, while he himſelf ranged his forces in order of battle. The ſon of Arno returning to Swaran, deſcribes to him Cuthullin's chariot, and the terrible appearance of that hero. The armies engage, but night coming on, leaves the victory undecided. Cuthullin, according to the hoſpitality of the times, ſends to Swaran a formal invitation to a feaſt, by his bard Carril, the ſon of Kinfena. Swaran refuſes to come, Carril relates to Cuthullin the ſtory of Grudar and Braſſolis. A party, by Connal's advice, is ſent to obſerve the enemy ; which cloſes the action of the firſt day. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-690.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- [ 219 ] -->
 <div><head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. In SIX BOOKS. BOOK I. </head><p> <sc>Cuthullin</sc><ptr target='#N_1'/> ſat by Tura's wall : by the tree of the ruſtling ſound. His ſpear leaned againſt a rock. His ſhield lay on graſs, by his <!--  -->
<!-- ſide. -->
<pb n='1773-693.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 220 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 ſide. Amid his thoughts of mighty Carbar<ptr target='#N_2'/>, a hero ſlain by the chief in war; the ſcout<ptr target='#N_3'/> of acean comes, Moran<ptr target='#N_4'/> the ſon of Fithil !</p><p>“<sc>Arise</sc>,” ſays the youth, “Cuthullin, ariſe. I ſee the ſhips of the north ! Many, chief of men, are the foe. Many the heroes of the ſeaborne Swaran !'' “Moran!” replied the blue-eyed chief, “thou ever trembleſt, ſon of Fithil ! “Thy fears have increaſed the foe. It is Fingal, king<ptr target='#N_5'/> of deſarts, with aid to green Erin of ſtreams.” “I beheld their chief,” ſays Moran, “tall as a glittering rock. His ſpear is a blaſted <!--  -->
<!-- pine. -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-696.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 221 -->
 pine. His ſhield the riſing moon ! He ſat on the ſhore ! like a cloud of miſt on the ſilent hill ! Many, chief of heroes ! I ſaid, many are our hands of war. Well art thou named, the Mighty Man : but many mighty men are ſeen from Tura's windy walls.”</p><p>“<sc>He</sc> ſpoke, like a wave on a rock, who in this land appears like me? Heroes ſtand not in my preſence: they fall to earth from my hand. Who can meet Swaran in fight? Who but Fingal, king of Selma of ſtorms? Once we wreſtled on Malmor<ptr target='#N_05'/> ; our heels overturned the woods. Rocks fell from their place ; rivulets, changing their courſe, fled murmuring from our ſide ? Three days we renewed the ſtrife; heroes ſtood at a diſtance and trembled. On the fourth, Fingal ſays, that the king of the ocean fell ! but Swaran ſays, he ſtood ! Let dark Cuthullin yield to him, that is ſtrong as the ſtorms of his land !”?</p><p>“<sc>No</sc>!” replied the blue-eyed chief, “I never yield to mortal man ! Dark Cuthullin ſhall be great or dead! Go, ſon of Fithil, take my ſpear. Strike the ſounding ſhield of Semo<ptr target='#N_6'/>. <!--  -->
<!-- It -->
<pb n='1773-699.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 222 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 It hangs at Tura's ruſtling gate. The ſound of peace is not its voice! My heroes ſhall hear and obey.” He went. He ſtruck the boſſy ſhield. The hills, the rocks reply. The ſound ſpreads along the wood: deer ſtart by the lake of roes. Curach<ptr target='#N_7'/> leaps from the ſounding rock; and Connal of the bloody ſpear ! Crugal's<ptr target='#N_8'/> breaſt of ſnow beats high. The ſon of Fari leaves the dark-brown hind. It is the ſhield of war, ſaid Ronnar ! the ſpear of Cuthullin, ſaid Lugar! ſon of the ſea put on thy arms! Calmar lift thy ſounding ſteel   Puno! dreadful hero, ariſe! Cairbar from thy red tree of Cromla ! Bend thy knee, O Eth; deſcend from the ſtreams of Lena. Ca-olt ſtretch thy ſide as thou moveſt along the whiſtling heath of Mora : thy ſide that is white as the foam of the troubled ſea, when the dark winds pour it on rocky Cuthon<ptr target='#N_9'/>.</p><p><sc>Now</sc> I behold the chiefs, in the pride of their former deeds! Their ſouls are kindled at the battles of old; at the actions of other times. Their eyes are flames of fire. They roll in ſearch of the foes of the land. Their mighty hands are on their ſwords. Lightning pours from their ſides of ſteel. They come like ſtreams from the <!--  -->
<!-- mountains ; -->
<pb n='1773-702.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 223 -->
 mountains ; each ruſhes roaring from his hill. Bright are the chiefs of battle, in the armour of their fathers. Gloomy and dark their heroes follow, like the gathering of the rainy clouds behind the red meteors of heaven. The ſounds of craſhing arms aſcend. The grey dogs howl between. Unequal burſts the ſong of battle. Rocking Cromla<ptr target='#N_10'/> ecchoes round. On Lena's duſky heath they ſtand, like miſt that ſhades the hills of autumn : when broken and dark it ſettles high, and lifts its head to heaven !</p><p>“<sc>Hail</sc>,” ſaid Cuthullin, “ſons of the narrow vales ! hail, hunters of the deer ! Another ſport is drawing near : It is like the dark rolling of that wave on the coaſt ! Or ſhall we fight, ye ſons of war ! or yield green Erin<ptr target='#N_11'/> to Lochlin ! O Connal<ptr target='#N_12'/> ſpeak, thou firſt of men! thou breaker of the ſhields! thou haſt often fought with Lochlin : wilt thou lift thy father's ſpear ? <!--  -->
<!-- “CUTHUL- -->
<!-- 2 -->
<pb n='1773-705.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 224 FINGAL, Book I. -->
 “<sc>Cuthullin</sc>!” calm the chief replied, “the ſpear of Connal is keen. It delights to ſhine in battle; to mix with the blood of thouſands. But tho' my hand is bent on fight, my heart is for the peace of Erin<ptr target='#N_13'/>. Behold, thou firſt in Cormac's war, the ſable fleet of Swaran. His maſts are many on our coaſt, like reeds in the lake of Lego. His ſhips are foreſts cloathed with miſt, when the trees yield by turns to the ſqually wind. Many are his chiefs in battle. Connal is for peace! Fingal would ſhun his arm the firſt of mortal men ! Fingal, who ſcatters the mighty, as ſtormy winds the heath; when ſtreams roar thro' ecchoing Cona : and night ſettles with all her clouds on the hill !</p><p>“<sc>Fly</sc>, thou man of peace,” ſaid Calmar<ptr target='#N_14'/>, « fly,” ſaid the ſon of Matha ; “go, Connal, to thy ſilent hills, where the ſpear never brightens in war ! Purſue the dark-brown deer of Cromla : ſtop with thine arrows the bounding roes of Lena. But, blue-eyed ſon of Semo, <!--  -->
<!-- Cuthullin, -->
<pb n='1773-708.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book 1. An EPIC POEM. 225 -->
 Cuthullin, ruler of the field, ſcatter thou the ſons of Lochlin<ptr target='#N_15'/>; roar thro' the ranks of their pride, Let no veſſel of the kingdom of Snow bound on the dark-rolling waves of Inis tore<ptr target='#N_16'/>. Riſe, ye dark winds of Erin riſe ! roar whirlwinds of Lara of hinds! Amid the tempeſt let me die, torn, in a cloud, by angry ghoſts of men ; amid the tempeſt let Calmar die, if ever chace was ſport to him, ſo much as the battle of ſhields !”</p><p>“<sc>Calmar</sc> !” Connal ſlow replied, “I never fled, young ſon of Matha! I was ſwift with my friends in fight ; but ſmall is the fame of Connal ! The battle was won in my preſence; the valiant overcame! But, ſon of Semo, hear my voice, regard the ancient throne of Cormac. Give wealth and half the land for peace, till Fingal ſhall arrive on our coaſt. Or, if war be thy choice, I lift the ſword and ſpear. My Joy ſhall be in the midſt of thouſands; my ſoul thall lighten through the gloom of the fight!”</p><p>“To me,” Cuthullin replies, “pleaſant is the noiſe of arms ! pleaſant as the thunder of heaven, before the ſhower of ſpring ! But gather all the ſhining tribes that I may view the ſons of war! Let them paſs along the heath, bright as <!--  -->
<!-- VOL. I. Q the -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-711.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 226 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 the ſun-ſhine before a ſtorm ; when the weſt wind collects the clouds and Morven ecchoes over all her oaks ! But where are my friends in battle ? The ſupporters of my arm in danger ? Where art thou, white-boſom'd Cathbar? Where is that cloud in war, Duchômar<ptr target='#N_016'/> ? Haſt thou left me; O Fergus<ptr target='#N_17'/>! in the day of the ſtorm? Fergus, firſt in our joy at the feaſt ! ſon of Roſſa! arm of death ! comeſt thou like a roe from Malmor. Like a hart from thy echoing hills? Heil thou ſon of Roſſa! what ſhades the ſoul of war ?”</p><p>“<sc>Four</sc> ſtones<ptr target='#N_18'/>,” replied the chief, “riſe on the grave of Câthba. Theſe hands have laid in earth Duchômar, that cloud in war ! Câthba, ſon of Torman! thou wert a ſun-beam in Erin. And thou, O valiant Duchômar, a miſt of the marſhy Lano ; when it moves on the plains of autumn, bearing the death of thouſands along; Morna! faireſt of maids ! calm is thy ſleep in <!--  -->
<!-- the -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-714.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 227 -->
 the cave of the rock ! Thou haſt fallen in darkneſs, like a ſtar, that ſhoots acroſs the deſart ; when the traveller is alone, and mourns the tranſient beam !”</p><p>“<sc>Say</sc>,” ſaid Semo's blue-eyed ſon, “ſay how fell the chiefs of Erin? Fell they by the ſons of Lochlin, ſtriving in the battle of heroes ? Or what confines the ſtrong in arms to the dark and narrow houſe ?” “<sc>Cathba</sc>,” replied the hero, “fell by the ſword of Duchômar at the oak of the noiſy ſtreams. Duchômar came to Tura's cave; he ſpoke to the lovely Morna. Morna<ptr target='#N_19'/>, faireſt among women, lovely daughter of ſtrong-armed Cormac! Why in the circle of ſtones? in the cave of the rock alone? The ſtream murmurs along. The old tree groans in the wind. The lake is troubled before thee ; dark are the clouds of the ſky! But thou art ſnow on the heath ; thy hair is the miſt of Cromla ; when it curls on the hill; when it ſhines to the beam of the weſt ! Thy breaſts are two ſmooth rocks ſeen from Branno of ſtreams. Thy arms, like two white pillars, in the halls of the great Fingal.</p><p>“<sc>From</sc> whence,” the fair-haired maid replied, “from whence, Duchômar, moſt gloomy of men? Dark are thy brows and terrible! Red <!--  -->
<!-- Q 2 are -->
<pb n='1773-717.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 228 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 are thy rolling eyes! Does Swaran appear on the ſea? What of the foe, Duchômar ?” “From the hill I return, O Morna, from the hill of the dark-brown hinds. Three have I ſlain with my bended yew. Three with my long bounding dogs of the chace. Lovely daughter of Cormac, I love thee as my ſoul! I have ſlain one ſtately deer for thee. High was his branchy head; and fleet his feet of wind.” “Duchômar!” calm the maid replied, “I love thee not, thou gloomy man ! hard is thy heart of rock; dark is thy terrible brow. But Cathba, young ſon of Torman<ptr target='#N_20'/>, thou art the love of Morna. Thou art a ſun-beam, in the day of the gloomy ſtorm. Saweſt thou the ſon of Torman, lovely on the hill of his hinds? Here the daughter of Cormac waits the coming of Câthba !”</p><p>“<sc>Long</sc> ſhall Morna wait,” Duchomar ſaid, “long ſhall Morna wait for Câthba ! Behold this ſword unſheathed ! Here wanders the blood of Câthba. Long ſhall Morna wait. He fell by the ſtream of Branno ! On Croma I will raiſe his tomb, daughter of blue-ſhielded Cormac ! Turn on Duchômar thine eyes; his arm is ſtrong as a ſtorm.” “Is the ſon of Torman fallen ?” ſaid the wildly burſting voice of the maid, “Is he fallen on his ecchoing hills, the <!--  -->
<!-- youth -->
<pb n='1773-720.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 229 -->
 youth with the breaſt of ſnow ? The firſt in the chace of hinds? The foe of the ſtrangers of ocean ? Thou art dark<ptr target='#N_21'/> to me, Duchômar, cruel is thine arm to Morna ! Give me that ſword, my foe! I love the wandering blood of Câthba !”</p><p><sc>He</sc> gave the ſword to her tears. She pierced his manly breaſt! He fell, like the bank of a mountain-ſtream, and ſtretching forth his hand, he ſpoke. “Daughter of blue-ſhielded Cormac! Thou haſt ſlain me in youth ! The ſword is cold in my breaſt: Morna, I feel it cold. Give me to Moina<ptr target='#N_22'/> the maid. Duchômar was the dream of her night ! She will raiſe my tomb ; the hunter ſhall raiſe my fame. But draw the ſword from my breaſt. Morna, the ſteel is cold !” She came, in all her tears, ſhe came; ſhe drew the ſword from his breaſt. He pierced her white ſide! He ſpread her fair locks on the ground ! Her burſting blood ſounds from her ſide: her white arm is ſtained with red. Rolling in death ſhe lay. The cave re-ecchoed to her ſighs.”</p><p>“<sc>Peace</sc>,” ſaid Cuthullin, “to the ſouls of the heroes! their deeds were great in fight. Let them ride around<ptr target='#N_23'/> me on clouds. Let them <!--  -->
<!-- Q 3 ſhew -->
<pb n='1773-723.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 230 FIN G A L, Book I. -->
 ſhew their features of war. My ſoul ſhall then be firm in danger; mine arm like the thunder of heaven ! But be thou on a moon-beam, O Morna ! near the window of my reſt; when my thoughts are of peace; when the din of arms is paſt. Gather the ſtrength of the tribes ! Move to the wars of Erin! Attend the car of my battles! Rejoice in the noiſe of my courſe! Place three ſpears by my ſide : follow the bounding of my ſteeds! That my ſoul may be ſtrong in my friends, when battle darkens round the beams of my ſteel !</p><p><sc>As</sc> ruſhes a ſtream of foam from the dark ſhady deep of Cromla; when the thunder is travelling above, and dark-brown night ſits on half the hill. Through the breaches of the tempeſt look forth the dim faces of ghoſts. So fierce, ſo vaſt, ſo terrible ruſhed on the ſons of Erin. The chief like a whale of ocean, whom all his billows purſue, poured valour forth, as a ſtream, rolling his might along the ſhore. The ſons of Lochlin heard the noiſe, as the ſound of a winterform. Swaran ſtruck his boſſy ſhield: he called the ſon of Arno, “What murmur rolls along the hill, like the gathered flies of the eve? The ſons of Erin deſcend, or ruſtling winds roar in the diſtant wood! Such is the noiſe of Gormal, before the white tops of my waves ariſe. <!--  -->
<!-- O ſon -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-726.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 231 -->
 O ſon of Arno, aſcend the hill; view the dark face of the heath!”</p><p><sc>He</sc> went. He trembling, ſwift returned. His eyes rolled wildly round. His heart beat high againſt his ſide. His words were faultering, broken, ſlow. “Ariſe, ſon of ocean, ariſe, chief of the dark-brown ſhields! I ſee the dark, the mountain-ſtream of battle ! The deepmoving ſtrength of the ſons of Erin! The car, the car of war comes on, like the flame of death ! the rapid car of Cuthullin, the noble ſon of Semo ! It bends behind like a wave near a rock ; like the ſun-ſtreaked miſt of the heath. Its ſides are emboſſed with ſtones, and ſparkle like the ſea round the boat of night. Of poliſhed yew is its beam; its ſeat of the ſmootheſt bone. The ſides are repleniſhed with ſpears; the bottom is the foot-ſtool of heroes ! Before the right ſide of the car is ſeen the ſnorting horſe! The high-maned, broad-breaſted, proud, wide-leaping, ſtrong ſteed of the hill. Loud and reſounding is his hoof; the ſpreading of his mane above is like a ſtream of ſmoke on a ridge of rocks. Bright are the ſides of the ſteed ! his name is SulinSifadda!”</p><p>“<sc>Before</sc> the left ſide of the car is ſeen the ſnorting horſe ! The thin-maned, high-headed, ſtrong-hoofed, fleet, bounding ſon of the hill : his name is Duſronnal, among the ſtormy ſons <!--  -->
<!-- Q 4 of -->
<pb n='1773-729.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 232 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 of the ſword! A thouſand thongs bind the car on high. Hard poliſhed bits ſhine in a wreath of foam. Thin thongs bright-ſtudded with gems, bend on the ſtately necks of the ſteeds. The ſteeds that like wreaths of miſt fly over the ſtreamy vales! The wildneſs of deer is in their courſe, the ſtrength of eagles deſcending on the prey. Their noiſe is like the blaſt of winter, on the ſides of the ſnow-headed Gormal.</p><p>Within the car is ſeen the chief; the ſtrongarmed ſon of the ſword. The hero's name is Cuthullin, ſon of Semo king of ſhells. His red cheek is like my poliſhed yew. The look of his blue-rolling eye is wide, beneath the dark arch of his brow. His hair flies from his head like a flame, as bending forward he wields the ſpear, Fly, king of ocean, fly! He comes, like a ſtorm, along the ſtreamy vale !</p><p>“When did I fly,” replied the king? When fled Swaran from the battle of ſpears? When did I ſhrink from danger, chief of the little ſoul? I met the ſtorm of Gormal, when the foam of my waves beat high. I met the ſtorm of the clouds; ſhall Swaran fly from a hero? Were Fingal himſelf before me, my ſoul ſhould not darken with fear. Ariſe to battle, my thouſands! pour round me like the ecchoing main, Gather round the bright ſteel of your <!--  -->
<!-- King 3 -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-732.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I An EPIC POEM. 233 -->
 king; ſtrong as the rocks of my land; that meet the ſtorm, with joy, and ſtretch their dark pines to the wind !”</p><p><sc>Like</sc> autumn's dark ſtorms, pouring from two ecchoing hills, toward each other approached the heroes. Like two deep ſtreams from high rocks meeting, mixing, roaring on the plain; loud, rough and dark in battle meet Lochlin and Innis-fail. Chief mixes his ſtrokes with chief, and man with man ; ſteel, clanging, ſounds on ſteel. Helmets are cleft on high. Blood burſts and ſmokes around. Strings murmur on the poliſhed yews. Darts ruſh along the ſky. Spears fall like the circles of light, which gild the face of night. As the noiſe of the troubled ocean, when roll the waves on high. As the laſt peal of thunder in heaven, ſuch is the din of war! Though Cormac's hundred bards were there, to give the fight to ſong; feeble was the voice of a hundred bards to ſend the deaths to future times ! For many were the deaths of heroes; wide poured the blood of the brave !</p><p><sc>Mourn</sc>, ye ſons of ſong, mourn the death of the noble Sithâllin<ptr target='#N_24'/>. Let the ſighs of Fina riſe, on the lone plains of her lovely Ardan. <!--  -->
<!-- They -->
<pb n='1773-735.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 234 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 They fell, like two hinds of the deſart, by the hands of the mighty Swaran; when, in the midſt of thouſands, he roared; like the ſhrill ſpirit of a ſtorm. He ſits dim, on the clouds of the north, and enjoys the death of the mariner. Nor ſlept thy hand by thy ſide, chief of the iſle of miſt<ptr target='#N_25'/>! many were the deaths of thine arm, Cathullin, thou ſon of Semo ! His ſword was like the beam of heaven when it pierces the ſons of the vale; when the people are blaſted and fall, and all the hills are burning around. Duſronnal<ptr target='#N_26'/> ſnorted over the bodies of heroes. Sifadda<ptr target='#N_27'/> bathed his hoof in blood. The battle lay behind them, as groves overturned on the deſart of Cromla ; when the blaſt has paſſed the heath, laden with the ſpirits of night!</p><p><sc>Weep</sc> on the rocks of roaring winds, O maid of Iniſtore<ptr target='#N_28'/>! Bend thy fair head over the waves, <!--  -->
<!-- thou -->
<!--  -->
<!-- heroes -->
<!-- 5 -->
<pb n='1773-738.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 235 -->
 thou lovelier than the ghoſt of the hills; when it moves, in a ſun-beam, at noon, over the ſilence of Morven ! He is fallen! thy youth is low ! pale beneath the ſword of Cuthullin! No more ſhall valour raiſe thy love to match the blood of kings. Trenar, graceful Trenar died, O maid of Iniſtore. His grey dogs are howling at home ; they ſee his paſſing ghoſt. His bow is in the hall unſtrung. No ſound is in the hill of his hinds !</p><p>As roll a thouſand waves to the rocks, ſo Swaran's hoſt came on. As meets a rock a thouſand waves, ſo Erin met Swaran of ſpears. Death raiſes all his voices around, and mixes with the ſounds of ſhields. Each hero is a pillar of darkneſs; the ſword a beam of fire in his hand. The field ecchoes from wing to wing, as a hundred hammers that riſe, by turns, on the red ſon of the furnace. Who are theſe on Lena's heath, theſe ſo gloomy and dark ? Who are theſe like two clouds and their ſwords like lightning above them? The little hills are troubled around; the rocks tremble with all their moſs. Who is it but Ocean's ſon and the <!--  -->
<!-- car -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-741.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 236 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 car-borne chief of Erin? Many are the anxious eyes of their friends, as they ſee them dim on the heath. But night conceals the chiefs in clouds, and ends the dreadful ſight !</p><p><sc>It</sc> was on Cromla's ſhaggy ſide that Dorglas had placed the deer<ptr target='#N_29'/>; the early fortune of the chace, before the heroes left the hill. A hundred youths collect the heath; ten warriors wake the fire; three hundred chuſe the poliſh'd ſtones. The feaſt is ſmoaking wide! Cuthullin, chief of Erin's war, reſumed his mighty ſoul. He ſtood upon his beamy ſpear, and ſpoke to the ſon of ſongs ; to Carril of other times, the grey-haired ſon of Kinfena<ptr target='#N_30'/>. “Is this feaſt ſpread ſor me alone and the king of Lochlin on Erin's ſhore ; far from the deer of his hills, and ſounding halls of his feaſts? Riſe, Carril of other times; carry my words to Swaran. Te!l him from the roaring of waters, that Cuthullin gives his feaſt. <!--  -->
<!-- Here -->
<pb n='1773-744.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Pook I. An EPIC POEM. 237 -->
 Here let him liſten to the ſound of my groves, amidſt the clouds of night. For cold and bleak the bluſtering winds ruſh over the foam of his ſeas. Eere let him praiſe the trembling harp, and hear the ſongs of heroes !”</p><p><sc>Old</sc> Carril went, with ſofteſt voice. He called the king of dark-brown ſhields! “Riſe from the ſkins of thy chace, riſe, Swaran king of groves! Cuthullin gives the joy of ſhells. Partake the feaſt of Erin's blue-eyed chief!” He anſwered like the ſullen ſound of Cromla before a ſtorm. “Though all thy daughters, Inis-fail! ſhould ſtretch their arms of ſnow; ſhould raiſe the heavings of their breaſts, and ſoftly roll their eyes of love; yet, fixed as Lochlin's thouſand rocks, here Swaran ſhould remain ; till morn, with the young beams of the eaſt, ſhall light me to the death of Cuthullin. Pleaſant to my ear is Lochlin's wind ! It ruſhes over my ſeas ! It ſpeaks aloft in all my ſhrouds, and brings my green foreſts to my mind: The green foreſts of Gormal, which often ecchoed to my winds, when my ſpear was red in the chace of the boar. Let dark Cuthullin yield to me the ancient thrones of Cormac; or Erin's torrents ſhall ſhew from their hills the red foam of the blood of his pride !” <!--  -->
<!-- « SAD -->
<pb n='1773-747.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 238 F I N G A L, Book I. -->
 “<sc>Sad</sc> is tbe ſound of Swaran's voice,” ſaid Carril of other times! “Sad to himſelf alone,” ſaid the blue-eyed ſon of Semo. “But, Carril, raiſe the voice on high; tell the deeds of other times. Send thou the night away in ſong ; and give the joy of grief. For many heroes and maids of love, have moved on Inis-fail : And lovely are the ſongs of woe that are heard in Albion's rocks; when the noiſe of the chace is paſt, and the ſtreams of Cona anſwer to the voice of Oſſian<ptr target='#N_31'/>.”</p><p>“<sc>In</sc> other days<ptr target='#N_32'/>,” Carril replies, “came the ſons of Ocean to Erin! A thouſand veſſels bounded on waves to Ullin's lovely plains, The ſons of Inis-fail aroſe, to meet the race of dark-brown ſhields. Cairbar, firſt of men, was there, and Grudar, ſtately youth ! Long had they ſtrove for the ſpotted bull, that lowed on <!--  -->
<!-- Gol- -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-750.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 239 -->
 Golbun's<ptr target='#N_33'/> ecchoing heath. Each claimed him as his own. Death was often at the point of their ſteel ! Side by ſide the heroes fought ; the ſtrangers of Ocean fled. Whoſe name was fairer on the hill, than the name of Cairbar and Grudar! But ah! why ever lowed the bull, on Golbun's ecchoing heath. They ſaw him leaping like ſnow. The wrath of the chiefs returned !”</p><p>“<sc>On</sc> Lubar's<ptr target='#N_34'/> graſſy banks they fought ; Grudar fell in his blood. Fierce Cairbar came to the vale, where Braſſolis<ptr target='#N_35'/>, faireſt of his ſiſters, all alone, raiſed the ſong of grief. She ſang of the actions of Grudar, the youth of her ſecret ſoul! She mourned him in the field of blood ; but ſtill ſhe hoped for his return. Her white boſom is ſeen from her robe, as the moon from the clouds of night, when its edge heaves white on the view, from the darkneſs, which covers its orb. Her voice was ſofter than the harp to raiſe the ſong of grief. Her ſoul was fixed on Grudar. The ſecret look of her eye was his. “When ſhalt thou come in thine arms, thou mighty in the war?”</p><p>“<sc>Take</sc>, Braſſiolis,” Cairbar came and ſaid, “take, Braſſiolis, this ſhield of blood. Fix it <!--  -->
<!-- On -->
<pb n='1773-753.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 240 F ING A L, Book I. -->
 on high within my hall, the armour of my foe ! Her ſoft heart beat againſt her ſide. Diſtracted, pale, ſhe flew. She ſound her youth in all his blood; ſhe died on Cromla's heath. Here reſts their duſt, Cuthullin ; theſe lonely yews ſprung from their tombs, and ſhade them from the ſtorm. Fair was Braſſolis on the plain! Stately was Grudar on the hill ! The bard thall preſerve their names, and ſend them down to future times !”</p><p>“<sc>Pleasant</sc> is thy voice, O Carril,” ſaid the blue-eyed chief of Erin. “Pleaſant are the words of other times! They are like the calm ſhower of ſpring; when the ſun looks on the field, and the light cloud flies over the hills. O ſtrike the harp in praiſe of my love, the lonely fun-beam of Dunſcaith. Strike the harp in the praiſe of Bragéla ; ſhe that I left in the Iſle of Miſt, the ſpouſe of Semo's ſon! Doſt thou raiſe thy fair face from the rock to find the ſails of Cuthullin? The ſea is rolling diſtant far ; its white foam deceives thee for my ſails. Retire, for it is night, my love; the dark winds ſign in thy hair. Retire to the halls of my feaſts ; think of the times that are paſt. I will not return till the ſtorm of war is ceaſed. O Connal, ſpeak of war and arms, and ſend her from my mind. Lovely with her flowing hair is the whiteboſomed daughter of Sorglan,” <!--  -->
<!-- 9 Con- -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-756.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 241 -->
 <sc>Connal</sc>, ſlow to ſpeak, replied, “Guard againſt the race of Ocean. Send thy troop of night abroad, and watch the ſtrength of Swaran. Cuthullin ! I am for peace till the race of Selma come; till Fingal come, the firſt of men, and beam, like the ſun, on our fields !” The hero ſtruck the ſhield of alarms, the warriors of the night moved on! The reſt lay in the heath of the deer, and ſlept bcneath the duſky wind. The ghoſts<ptr target='#N_36'/> of the lately dead were near, and ſwam on the gloomy clouds: And far diſtant, in the dark ſilence of Lena, the feeble voices of death were faintly heard. <!--  -->
<!-- VoL. I.  F I N- -->
<pb n='1773-760.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
</p></div>
<div type='notes'> <note xml:id='N_1'><p> Cuthullin the ſon of Semo and grandſon to Caithbat a druid celebrated in tradition for his wiſdom and valour. Cuthullin when very young married Bragela the daughter of Sorglan, and paſſing over into Ireland, lived for ſome time with Connal, grandſon by a daughter to Congal the petty king of Ulſter. His wiſdom and valour in a ſhort time gained him ſuch reputation, that in the minority of Cormac the ſupreme king of Ireland, he was choſen guardian to the young king, and ſole manager of the war againſt Swaran king of Lochlin. After a ſeries of great actions he was killed in battle ſomewhere in Connaught, in the twenty-ſeventh year of his age. He was ſo remarkable for his ſtrength, that to deſcribe a ſtrong man it has paſſed into a proverb, “He has the ſtrength of Cuthullin,” They ſhew the remains of his palace at Dunſcaich in the Iſle of Skye ; and a ſtone to which he bound his dog Luath, goes ſtill by his name. </p></note><note xml:id='N_2'><p> Cairbar or Cairbre, ſignifies <hi>a ſtrong man</hi>. </p></note><note xml:id='N_3'><p> Cuthullin having previous intelligence of the invaſion intended by Swaran, ſent ſcouts a!l over the coaſt of Ullin or Ulſter, to give early notice of the firſt appearance of the enemy, at the ſame time that he ſent Munan the ſon of Stirmal to implore the aſſiſtance of Fingal. He himſelf collected the flower of the Iriſh youth to Tura, a caſtle on the coaſt, to ſtop the progreſs of the enemy till Fingal ſhould arrive from Scotland. We may conclude from Cuthullin's applying ſo early for foreign aid, that the Iriſh were not then ſo numerous as they have ſince been; which is a great preſumption againſt the high antiquities of that people. We have the teſtimony of Tacitus that one legion only was thought ſufficient, in the time of Agricola, to reduce the whole iſland under the Roman yoke ; which would not probably have been the caſe had the iſland been inhabited for any number of centuries before. </p></note><note xml:id='N_4'><p> Moran ſignifies <hi>many</hi>; and Fithil, or rather Fili, <hi>an inferior bard.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_5'><p> Fingal the ſon of Comhal and Morna the daughter of Thaddu. His grandfather was Trathal, and great grandfather Trenmor, both of whom are often mentioned in the poem. </p></note><note xml:id='N_05'><p> Meal-mór, <hi>a great hill.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_6'><p> Cabait, or rather Cathbait, grandfather to the hero, was ſo remarkable for his valour, that his ſhield was made uſe of to alarm his poſterity to the battles of the family. We find Fingal making the ſame uſe of his own ſhield in the 4th book. A horn was the moſt common inſtrument to call the army together. </p></note><note xml:id='N_7'><p> Cu raoch ſignifies <hi>the madneſs of battle.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_8'><p> Cruth-geal, <hi>fair-complexioned.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_9'><p> Cu-thón, <hi>the mournful ſound of waves.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_10'><p> Crom-leach ſignified a place of worſhip among the Druids. It is here the proper name of a hill on the coaſt of Ullin or Ulſter. </p></note><note xml:id='N_11'><p> Ireland ſo called from a colony that ſettled there called Falans. Innis-fail, the iſland of the Fa-il or Falans. </p></note><note xml:id='N_12'><p> Connal, the friend of Cuthullin, was the ſon of Caithbait prince of the Tongorma or the <hi>iſland of blue waves</hi>, probably one of the Hebrides. His mother was Fioncoma the daughter of Congal. He had a ſon by Foba of Conachar-neſſar, who was afterwards petty king of Ulſter. For his ſervices in the war againſt Swaran he had lands conferred on him, which, from his name, were called Tir-chonnuil or Tir-connel, <hi>i. e.</hi> the land of Connal. </p></note><note xml:id='N_13'><p>Erin, a name of Ireland; from <hi>ear</hi> or <hi>iar</hi> Weſt, and <hi>in</hi> an iſland. This name was not always confined to Ireland, for there is the higheſt probability that the <hi>Ierne</hi> of the ancients was Britain to the North of the Forth, For Ierne is ſaid to be to the North of Britain, which could not be meant of Ireland. <sc>Strabo</sc>, I, 2, &amp; 4. <sc>Casaub</sc>.l.1. </p></note><note xml:id='N_14'><p> Cálm-er, <hi>a ſtrong man.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_15'><p> The Galic name of Scandinavia in general. </p></note><note xml:id='N_16'><p>The Orkney iſlands. </p></note><note xml:id='N_016'><p> Dubhchomar, <hi>a black well made man.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_17'><p> Fear-guth, <hi>the man of the word</hi>; or a commander of an army. </p></note><note xml:id='N_18'><p> This paſſage alludes to the manner of burial among the ancient Scots. They opened a grave ſix or eight feet deep : the bottom was lined with fine clay: and on this they laid the body of the deceaſed, and, if a warrior, his ſword, and the heads of twelve arrows by his ſide. Above they laid another ſtratum of clay, in which they placed the horn of a deer, the ſymbol of hunting. The whole was covered with a fine mold, and four ſtones placed on end to mark the extent of the grave. Theſe are the four ſtones alluded to here.</p></note><note xml:id="N_19"><p>Muirne, or Morna, <hi>a woman beloved by all.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_20'><p> Torman, <sc>thunder</sc>. This is the true origin of the Jupiter Taramis of the ancients. </p></note><note xml:id='N_21'><p> She alludes to his name, <hi>the dark man.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_22'><p> Moina, <hi>ſoft in temper and perſon.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_23'><p> It was the opinion then, as indeed it is to this day, of ſome of the Highlanders, that the ſouls of the deceaſed hovered round their living friends; and ſometimes appeared to them when they were about to enter on any great undertaking. </p></note><note xml:id='N_24'><p> Sithallin ſignifies <hi>a handſome man</hi>; Fiona, <hi>a fair maid;</hi> and Ardan, <hi>pride</hi>. </p></note><note xml:id='N_25'><p> The Iſle of Sky ; not improperly called the <hi>iſle of miſt</hi>, as its high hills, which catch the clouds from the weſtern ocean, occaſion almoſt continual rains. </p></note><note xml:id='N_26'><p> One of Cuthullin's horſes. Dubhſtron gheal. </p></note><note xml:id='N_27'><p> Sith-fadda, <hi>i. e. a long ſtride.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_28'><p> <hi>The maid of Iniſtore</hi> was the daughter of Gorlo king of Iniſtore or Orkney iſlands. Trenar was brother to the king of Iniſcon, ſuppoſed to be one of the iſlands of Shetland. The Orkneys and Shetland were at that time ſubject to the king of Lochlin. We find that the dogs of Trenar are ſenſible at home of the death of their maſter, the very inſtant he is killed. It was the opinion of the times, that the ſouls of</p><p>heroes went immediately after death to the hills of their country, and the ſcenes they frequented the moſt happy time of their life. It was thought too that dogs and horſes ſaw the ghoſts of the deceaſed. </p></note><note xml:id='N_29'><p> The ancient manner of preparing feaſts after hunting, is handed down by tradition. A pit lined with ſmooth ſtones was made ; and near it ſtood a heap of ſmooth flat ſtones of the flint kind. The ſtones as well as the pit were properly heated with heath. Then they laid ſome veniſon in the bottom, and a ſtratum of the ſtones above it; and thus they did alternately till the pit was full, The whole was covered over with heath to confine the ſteam. Whether this is probable I cannot ſay ; but ſome pits are ſhewn, which the vulgar ſay, were uſed in that manner. </p></note><note xml:id='N_30'><p> Cean-ſeana, <hi>i. e, the head of the people.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_31'><p> The Cona here mentioned is that ſmall river that runs through Glenco in Argyleſhire. One of the hills which environ that romantic valley is ſtill called Scornafena, or the hill of Fingal's people, </p></note><note xml:id='N_32'><p> This epiſode is introduced with propriety. Calmar and Connal, two of the Iriſh heroes, had diſputed warmly before the battle about engaging the enemy, Carril endeavours to reconcile them with the ſtory of Cairbar and Grudar ; who, tho' enemies before, fought <hi>ſide by ſide</hi> in the war, The poet obtained his aim, for we find Calmar and Connal perfectly reconciled in the third book. </p></note><note xml:id='N_33'><p> Golb-bhean, as well as Cromleach, ſignifies <hi>a crooked hill.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_34'><p> Lubar, a river in Ulſter. <hi>Lalhar</hi>, loud, noiſy. </p></note><note xml:id='N_35'><p> Braſſolis ſignifies <hi>a woman with a white breaſt.</hi> </p></note><note xml:id='N_36'><p> It was long the opinion of the ancient Scots, that a ghoſt was heard ſhrieking near the place where a death was to happen ſoon after. The accounts given, to this day, amorg the vulzar, of this extraordinary matter, are very poetical, The ghoſt comes mounted on a meteor, and ſurrounds twice or thrice the place deſtined for the perſon to die; and then goes along the road through which the funeral is to paſs, ſhrieking at intervals; at laſt, the meteor and ghoſt diſappear above the burial place. </p></note></div></body>
