<body>
<pb n='1773-674.pbm.txt'/>
 <div><head>A DISSERTATION CONCERNING THE ÆRA of OSSIAN.</head><p> </p></div> <!--  -->
<!-- P 2 -->
<pb n='1773-677.pbm.txt'/>

<pb n='1773-680.pbm.txt'/>
<!--   -->
 <div><head>A DISSERTATION CONCERNING THE ÆRA of OSSIAN.</head><p></p><p><sc>Inquiries</sc> into the antiquities of nations afford more pleaſure than any real advantage to mankind. The ingenious may form ſyſtems of hiſtory on probabilities and a few facts; but at a great diſtance of time, their accounts muſt be vague and uncertain. The infancy of ſtates and kingdoms is as deſtitute of great events, as of the means of tranſmitting them to poſterity: The arts of poliſhed life, by which alone facts can be preſerved with certainty, are the production of a well-formed community. It is then hiſtorians begin to write, and public tranſactions to be worthy remembrance. The actions of former times are left in obſcurity, or magnified by uncertain traditions, Hence it is that we find ſo <!--  -->
<!-- P 3 much -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-683.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 214 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 much of the marvellous in the origin of every nation; poſterity being always ready to believe any thing, however fabulous, that reflects honour on their anceſtors.</p><p><sc>The</sc> Greeks and Romans were remarkable for this weakneſs. They ſwallowed the moſt abſurd fables concerning the high antiquities of their reſpectve nations. Good hiſtorians, however, roſe very early amongſt them, and tranſmitted, with luſtre, their great actions to poſterity. Tt is to them that they owe that unrivalled fame they now enjoy, while the great actions of other nations are involved in fables, or loſt in obſcurity. The Celtic nations afford a ſtriking inſtance of this kind, They, though once the maſters of Europe from the mouth of the river Oby<ptr target='#N_1'/>, in Ruſſia, to Cape Finiſterre, the weſtern point of Gallicia in Spain, are very little mentioned in hiſtory. They truſted their fame to tradition and the ſongs of their bards, which, by the viciſſitude of human affairs, are long ſince loſt. Their ancient language is the only monument that remains of them ; and the traces of it being ſound in places ſo widely diſtant from each other, ſerves only to ſhew the extent of their ancient power, but throws very little light on their hiſtory. <!--  -->
<!-- Of -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-686.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 21g -->
 <sc>Of</sc> all the Celtic nations, that which poſſeſſed old Gaul is the moſt renowned ; not perhaps on account of worth ſuperior to the reſt, but for their wars with a people who had hiſtorians to tranſmit the fame of their enemies, as well as their own, to poſterity. Britain was firſt peopled by them, according to the teſtimony of the beſt authors<ptr target='#N_2'/> ; its ſituation in reſpect to Gaul makes the opinion probable ; but what puts it beyond all diſpute, is that the ſame cuſtoms and language prevailed among the inhabitants of both in the days of Julius Cæſar<ptr target='#N_3'/>.</p><p><sc>The</sc> colony from Gaul poſſeſſed themſelves; at firſt, of that part of Britain which was next to their own country ; and ſpreading northward, by degrees, as they increaſed in numbers, peopled the whole iſland. Some adventurers paſſing over from thoſe parts of Britain that are within ſight of Ireland, were the ſounders of the Iriſh nation: which is a more probable ſtory than the idle fables of Mileſian and Gallician colonies. Diodorus Siculus<ptr target='#N_4'/> mentions it as a thing well known in his time, that the inhabitants of Ireland were originally Britons, and his teſtimony is unqueſtionable, when we conſider <!--  -->
<!-- P 4 that, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-689.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 216 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 that, for many ages, the language and cuſtoms of both nations were the ſame.</p><p><sc>Tacitus</sc> was of opinion that the ancient Caledonians were of German extract; but even the ancient Germans themſelves were Gauls. The preſent Germans, properly ſo called, were not the ſame with the ancient Celtæ. The manners and cuſtoms of the two nations were ſimilar ; but their language different. The Germans<ptr target='#N_5'/> are the genuine deſcendants of the ancient Scandinavians, who croſſed, in an early period, the Baltic. The Celtæ<ptr target='#N_6'/>, anciently, ſent many colonies into Germany, all of whom retained their own laws, language, and cuſtoms, till they were diſſipated, in the Roman empire ; and it is of them, if any colonies came from Germany into Scotland, that the ancient Caledonians were deſcended.</p><p><sc>But</sc> whether the Caledonians were a colony of the Celtic Germans, or the ſame with the Gauls that firſt poſſeſſed themſelves of Britain, is a matter of no moment at this diſtance of time. Whatever their origin was, we find them very. numerous in the time of Julius Agricola, which is a preſumption that they were long before ſettled in the country, The form of their government was a mixture of ariſtocracy and <!--  -->
<!-- monarchy -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-692.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 217 -->
 monarchy, as it was in all the countries where the Druids bore the chief ſway. This order of men ſeems to have been formed on the ſame principles with the Dactyli Idæi and Curetes of the ancients. Their pretended intercourſe with heaven, their magic and divination were the ſame. The knowlege of the Druids in natural cauſes, and the properties of certain things, the fruit of the experiments of ages, gained them a mighty reputation among the people. The eſteem of the populace ſoon increaſed into a veneration for the order; which theſe cunning and ambitious prieſts took care to improve, to ſuch a degree, that they, in a manner, ingroſſed the management of civil, as well as religious, matters. It is generally allowed that they did not abuſe this extraordinary power ; the preſerving their character of ſanctity was ſo eſſential to their influence, that they never broke out into violence or oppreſſion. The chiefs were allowed to execute the laws, but the legiſlative power was entirely in the hands of the Druids<ptr target='#N_7'/>. It was by their authority that the tribes were united, in times of the greateſt danger, under one head. This temporary king, or Vergobretus<ptr target='#N_8'/>, was choſen by them, and generally laid down his office at the end of the war. Theſe prieſts en<!--  -->
<!-- joyed -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-695.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 218 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 joyed long this extraordinary privilege among the Celtic nations who lay beyond the pale of the Roman empire. It was in the beginning of the ſecond century that their power among the Caledonians begun to decline. The traditions concerning Trathal and Cormac, anceſtors to Fingal, are full of the particulars of the fall of the Druids: a fingular fate, it muſt be owned, of prieſts, who had once eſtabliſhed their ſuperſtition !</p><p><sc>The</sc> continual wars of the Caledonians againſt the Romans hindered the better ſort from initiating themſelves, as the cuſtom formerly was, into the order of the Druids. The precepts of their religion were confined to a few, and were not much attended to by a people inured to war. The Vergobretus, or chief magiſtrate, was choſen without the concurrence of the hierarchy, or continued in his office againſt their will. Continual power ſtrengthened his intereſt among the tribes, and enabled him to ſend down, as hereditary to his poſterity, the office he had only received himſelf by election.</p><p><sc>On</sc> occaſion of a new war againſt the King of the World, as tradition emphatically calls the Roman emperor, the Druids, to vindicate the honour of the order, began to reſume their ancient privilege of chuſing the Vergobretus. Garmal, the ſon of Tarno, being deputed by <!--  -->
<!-- 4 them, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-698.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 219 -->
 them, came to the grandfather of the celebrated Fingal, who was then Vergobretus, and commanded him, in the name of the whole order, to lay down his office. Upon his refuſal, a civil war commenced, which ſoon ended in almoſt the total extinction of the religious order of the Druids. A few that remained, retired to the dark receſſes of their groves, and the caves they had formerly uſed for their meditations. It is then we find them in <hi>the circle of ſtones</hi>, and unheeded by the world. A total diſregard for the order, and utter abhorrence of the Druidical rites enſued. Under this cloud of public hate, all that had any knowlege of the religion of the Druids became extinct, and the nation fell into the laft degree of ignorance of their rites and ceremonies.</p><p><sc>It</sc> is no matter of wonder then, that Fingal and his ſon Oſſian diſliked the Druids, who were the declared enemies to their ſucceſſion in the ſupreme magiſtracy. It is a fingular caſe, it muſt be allowed, that there are no traces of religion in the poems aſcribed to Oſſian ; as the poetical compoſitions of other nations are fo cloſely connected with their mythology. But gods are not neceſſary, when the poet has genius. It is hard to account for it to thoſe who are not made acquainted with the manner of the old Scottiſh <!--  -->
<!-- bards. -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-701.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 220 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 bards. That race of men carried their notions of martial honour to an extravagant pitch. Any aid given their heroes in battle, was thought to derogate from their fame ; and the bards immediately transferred the glory of the action to him who had given that aid.</p><p><sc>Had</sc> the poet brought down gods, as often as Homer hath done, to aſſiſt his heroes, his work had not conſiſted of eulogiums on men, but of hymns to ſuperior beings. Thoſe who write in the Galic language ſeldom mention religion in their profane poetry ; and when they profeſſedly write of religion, they never mix with their compoſitions, the actions of their heroes, This cuſtom alone, even though the religion of the Druids had not been previouſly extinguiſhed, may, in ſome meaſure, excuſe the author's ſilence concerning the religion of ancient times.</p><p><sc>To</sc> allege, that a nation is void of all religion, would betray ignorance of the hiſtory of mankind. The traditions of their fathers, and their own obſervations on the works of nature, together with that ſuperſtition which is inherent in the human frame, have, in all ages, raiſed in the minds of men ſome idea of a ſuperior being. Hence it is, that in the darkeſt times, and amongſt the moſt barbarous nations, the very populace themſelves had ſome faint no<!--  -->
<!-- tion, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-704.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 221 -->
 tion, at leaſt, of a divinity. The Indians, who worſhip no God, believe that he exiſts. It would be doing injuſtice to the author of theſe poems, to think, that he had not opened his conceptions to that primitive and greateſt of all truths. But let his religion be what it will, it is certain he has not alluded to Chriſtianity, or any of its rites, in his poems ; which ought to fix his opinions, at leaſt, to an æra prior to that religion. Conjectures, on this ſubject, muſt ſupply the place of proof. The perſecution begun by Dioclefian, in the year 303, is the moſt probable time in which the firſt dawning of Chriſtianity in the north of Britain can be fixed. The humane and mild character of Conſtantius Chlorus, who commanded then in Britain, induced the perſecuted Chriftians to take refuge under him. Some of them, through a zeal to propagate their tenets, or through fear, went beyond the pale of the Roman empire, and ſettled among the Caledonians; who were ready to hearken to their doctrines, if the religion of the Druids was exploded long before.</p><p><sc>These</sc> miſſionaries, either through choice, or to give more weight to the doctrine they advanced, took poſſeſſion of the cells and groves of the Druids; and it was from this retired life they had the name of <hi>Culdees</hi><ptr target='#N_9'/>, which in the lan<!--  -->
<!-- guage -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-707.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 222 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
<!--  -->
<!-- guage of the country ſignified <hi>ſequeſtered perſons</hi>. -->
<!-- It was with one of the <hi>Culdees</hi> that Oſſian, in his -->
<!-- extreme old age, is ſaid to have diſputed con- -->
<!-- cerning the Chriftian religion. This diſpute, they -->
<!-- ſay, is extant, and is couched in verſe, according -->
<!-- to the cuſtom of the times. The extreme igno- -->
<!-- rance on the part of Oſſian, of the Chriſtian te- -->
<!-- nets, ſhews, that that religion had only been -->
<!-- lately introduced, as it is not eafy to conceive, -->
<!-- how one of the firſt rank could be totally unac- -->
<!-- quainted with a religion that had been known -->
<!-- for any time in the country. The diſpute bears -->
<!-- the genuine marks of antiquity. The obſolete -->
<!-- phraſes and expreſſions peculiar to the  times, -->
<!-- prove it to be no forgery. If Oſſian then lived -->
<!-- at the introduction of Chriſtianity, as by all ap- -->
<!-- pearance he did, his epoch will be the latter end -->
<!-- of the third, and beginning of the fourth cen- -->
<!-- tury. Tradition here ſteps in with a kind of -->
<!-- proof. -->
<!--  -->
<!-- <sc>The</sc> exploits of Fingal againſt Caracul<ptr target='#N_9'/>, the -->
<!-- ſon of the <hi>king of the world</hi>, are among the firſt -->
<!-- brave actions of his youth. A complete poem, -->
<!-- which relates to this ſubject, is printed in this -->
<!-- collection. -->
<!--  -->
<!-- Is -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-710.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- EZRA of OSSIAN. 223 -->
</p><p><sc>In</sc> the year 210 the emperor Severus, after returning from his expedition againſt the Caledonians, at York fell into the tedious illneſs of which he afterwards died. The Caledonians and Maiatæ, reſuming courage from his indiſpoſition, took arms in order to recover the poſſeſſions they had loſt. The enraged emperor commanded his army to march into their country, and to deſtroy it with fire and ſword. His orders were but ill executed, for his ſon, Caracalla, was at the head of the army, and his thoughts were entirely taken up with the hopes of his father's death, and with ſchemes to ſupplant his brother Geta. --- He ſcarcely had entered the enemy's country, when news was brought him that Severus was dead. --- A ſudden peace is patched up with the Caledonians, and, as it appears from Dion Caſſius, the country they had loft to Severus was reſtored to them.</p><p><sc>The</sc> Caracul of Fingal is no other than Caracalla, who, as the ſon of Severus, the Emperor of Rome, whoſe dominions were extended almoſt over the known world, was not without reaſon called <hi>the Son of the King of the world</hi>. The ſpace of time between 211, the year Severus died, and the beginning of the fourth century, is not ſo great, but Oſſian the ſon of Fingal, might have ſeen the Chriſtians whom the perſe<!--  -->
<!-- cution -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-713.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 224 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 cution under Diocleſian had driven beyond the pale of the Roman empire.</p><p><sc>In</sc> one of the many lamentations on the death of Oſcar, a battle which he fought againſt Caros, king of ſhips, on the banks of the winding Carun<ptr target='#N_10'/>, is mentioned among his great actions. It is more than probable, that the Caros mentioned here, is the ſame with the noted uſurper Caraufius, who aſſumed the purple in the year 287, and ſeizing on Britain, defeated the emperor Maximian Herculius, in ſeveral naval engagements, which gives propriety to his being called <hi>the King of Ships</hi>. The <hi>winding Carun</hi> is that ſmall river retaining ſtill the name of Carron, and runs in the neighbourhood of Agricola's wall, which Carauſius repaired to obſtruct the incurſions of the Caledonians. Several other paſſages in traditions allude to the wars of the Romans ; but the two juſt mentioned clearly fix the epocha of Fingal to the third century ; and this account agrees exactly with the Iriſh hiſtories, which place the death of Fingal, the ſon of Comhal, in the year 283, and that of Oſcar and their own celebrated Cairbre, in the year 296.</p><p><sc>Some</sc> people may imagine, that the alluſions to the Roman hiſtory might have been derived <!--  -->
<!-- by -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-716.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 22 -->
 by tradition, from learned men, more than from ancient poems. This muſt then have happened at leaſt three ages ago, as theſe alluſions are mentioned often in the compoſitions of thoſe times.</p><p><sc>Every</sc> one knows what a cloud of ignorance and barbariſm overſpread the north of Europe three hundred years ago. The minds of men, addicted to ſuperſtition, contracted a narrowneſs that deſtroyed genius. Accordingly we find the compoſitions of thoſe times trivial and puerile to the laſt degree. But let it be allowed, that, amidſt all the untoward circumſtances of the age, a genius might ariſe, it is not eaſy to determine what could induce him to allude to the Roman times. We find no fact to favour any deſigns which could be entertained by any man who lived in the fifteenth century.</p><p><sc>The</sc> ſtrongeſt objection to the antiquity of the poems now given to the public under the name of Oſſian, is the improbability of their being handed down by tradition through ſo many centuries. Ages of barbariſm ſome will ſay, could not produce poems abounding with the diſintereſted and generous ſentiments ſo conſpicuous in the compoſitions of Oſſian; and could theſe ages produce them, it is impoſſible but they muſt be loſt, or altogether corrupted in a long ſucceſſion of barbarous generations. <!--  -->
<!-- Vol. II. Q THESE -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-719.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 226 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
</p><p><sc>These</sc> objections naturally ſuggeſt themſelves to men unacquainted with the ancient ſtate of the northern parts of Britain. The bards, who were an inferior order of the Druids, did not ſhare their bad fortune. They were ſpared by the victorious king, as it was through their means only he could hope for immortality to his fame. They attended him in the camp, and contributed to eſtabliſh his power by their ſongs. His great actions were magnified, and the populace, who had no ability to examine into his character narrowly, were dazzled with his fame in the rhimes of the bards. In the mean time, men aſſumed ſentiments that are rarely to be met with in an age of barbariſm. The bards who were originally the diſciples of the Druids, had their minds opened, and their ideas enlarged, by being initiated in the learning of that celebrated order. They could form a perfect hero in their own minds, and aſcribe that character to their prince. The inferior chiefs made this ideal character the model of their conduct, and by degrees brought their minds to that generous ſpirit which breathes in all the poetry of the times. The prince, flattered by his bards, and rivalled by his own heroes, who imitated his character as deſcribed in the eulogies of his poets, endeavoured to excel his people in merit, <!--  -->
<!-- as -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-722.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 227 -->
 as he was above them in ſtation. This emulation continuing, formed at laſt the general character of the nation, happily compounded of what is noble in barbarity, and virtuous and generous in a poliſhed people.</p><p><sc>When</sc> virtue in peace, and bravery in war, are the characteriſtics of a nation, their actions become intereſting, and their fame worthy of immortality. A generous ſpirit is warmed with noble actions, and becomes ambitious of perpetuating them. This is the true ſource of that divine inſpiration, to which the poets of all ages pretended. When they found their themes inadequate to the warmth of their imaginations, they varniſhed them over with fables, ſupplied by their own fancy, or furniſhed by abſurd traditions. Theſe fables, however ridiculous, had their abettors; poſterity either implicitly believed them, or through a vanity natural to mankind, pretended that they did. They loved to place the founders of their families in the days of fable, when poetry, without the fear of contradiction, could give what characters ſhe pleaſed of her heroes. It is to this vanity that we owe the preſervation of what remain of the more ancient poems. Their poetical merit made their heroes famous in a country where heroiſm was much eſteemed and admired. The poſterity of thoſe <!--  -->
<!-- Q 2 heroes, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-725.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 228 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 heroes, or thoſe who pretended to be deſcended from them, heard with pleaſure the eulogiums of their anceſtors ; bards were employed to repeat the poems, and to record the connection of their patrons with chiefs ſo renowned. Every chief in proceſs of time had a bard in his family, and the office became at laſt hereditary. By the ſucceſſion of theſe bards, the poems concerning the anceſtors of the family were handed down from generation to generation; they were repeated to the whole clan on ſolemn occaſions, and always alluded to in the new compoſitions of the bards. This cuſtom came down to near our own times; and after the bards were diſcontinued, a great number in a clan retained by memory, or committed to writing, their compoſitions, and founded the antiquity of their families on the authority of their poems.</p><p><sc>The</sc> uſe of letters was not known in the north of Europe till long after the inſtitution of the bards : the records of the families of their patrons, their own, and more ancient poems were handed down by tradition. Their poetical compoſitions were admirably contrived for that purpoſe. They were adapted to muſic; and the moſt perfect harmony was obſerved. Each verſe was ſo connected with thoſe which preceded or ſollowed it, that if one line had been remem<!--  -->
<!-- _— bered -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-728.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIA N. ZLY -->
 bered in a ſtanza, it was almoſt impoſſible to forget the reſt. The cadences followed in ſo natural a gradation, and the words were ſo adaptcd to the common turn of the voice, after it is raiſed to a certain key, that it was almoſt impoſſible, from a ſimilarity of ſound, to ſubſtitute one word for another. This excellence is peculiar to the Celtic tongue, and is perhaps to be met with in no other language. Nor does this choice of words clog the ſenſe or weaken the expreſſion. The numerous flections of conſonants, and variation in declenſion, make the language very copious.</p><p><sc>The</sc> deſcendants of the Celtæ, who inhabited Britain and its iſles, were not ſingular in this method of preſerving the moſt precious monuments of their nation. The ancient laws of the Greeks were couched in verſe, and handed down by tradition. The Spartans, through a long habit, became ſo fond of this cuſtom, that they would never allow their laws to be committed to writing. The actions of great men, and the eulogiums of kings and heroes, were preſerved in the ſame manner. All the hiſtorical monuments of the old Germans were comprehended in their ancient ſongs<ptr target='#N_11'/>! which were either hymns to their gods, or elegies in praiſe of their heroes, <!--  -->
<!-- Q 3 . and -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-731.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- 230 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 and were intended to perpetuate the great events in their nation which were carefully interwoven with them. This ſpecies of compoſition was not committed to writing, but delivered by oral tradition<ptr target='#N_12'/>. The care they took to have the poems taught to their children, the uninterrupted cuſtom of repeating them upon certain occaſions, and the happy meaſure of the verſe, ſerved to preſerve them for a long time uncorrupted. This oral chronicle of the Germans was not forgot in the eighth century, and it probably would have remained to this day, had not learning, which thinks every thing, that is not committed to writing, fabulous, been introduced. It was from poetical traditions that Garcillaſſo compoſed his account of the Yncas of Peru. The Peruvians had loft all other monuments of their hiſtory, and it was from ancient poems which his mother, a princeſs of the blood of the Yncas, taught him in his youth, that he collected the materials of his hiſtory. If other nations then, that had been often overrun by enemies, and had ſent abroad and received colonies, could, for many ages, preſerve, by oral tradition, their laws and hiſtories uncorrupted, it is much more probable that the ancient Scots, a people ſo free of intermixture <!--  -->
<!-- with -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-734.pbm.txt'/>
<!-- ARA of OSSIAN. 231 -->
 with foreigners, and ſo ſtrongly attached to the memory of their anceſtors, had the works of their bards handed down with great purity.</p><p><sc>What</sc> is advanced, in this ſhort Diſſertation, it muſt be confeſſed, is mere conjecture. Beyond the reach of records, is ſettled a gloom, which no ingenuity can penetrate. The manners deſcribed, in theſe poems, ſuit the ancient Celtic times, and no other period, that is known in hiſtory. We muſt, therefore, place the heroes far back in antiquity; and it matters little, who were their contemporaries in other parts of the world. If we have placed Fingal in his proper period, we do honour to the manners of barbarous times. He exercifed every manly virtue in Caledonia, while Heliogabalus difgraced human nature at Rome. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-737.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-740.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-743.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->

<div type='notes'> <note xml:id='N_1'><p> Plin. 1. 6. </p></note><note xml:id='N_2'><p> Cæſ. 1.5. Tac. Agric. c. 2. </p></note><note xml:id='N_3'><p> Cæſar. Pomp. Mel. Tacitus. </p></note><note xml:id='N_4'><p> Diod. Sic. 1. 5. </p></note><note xml:id='N_5'><p> Strabo, 1.7. </p></note><note xml:id='N_6'><p> Cæſ. 1. 6. Liv. 1. 5. Tac de mor. Germ. </p></note><note xml:id='N_7'><p> Cæſ.1.6. </p></note><note xml:id='N_8'><p> Fer-gubreth, <hi>the man to judge</hi>. </p></note><note xml:id='N_9'><p> Culdich. </p></note><note xml:id='N_9'><p> Carac'huil, <hi>terrible eye</hi>. Carac-'healla, <hi>terrible look</hi>, Carac-challamh, a <hi>ſort of upper garment</hi>. </p></note><note xml:id='N_10'><p> Car-avon, <hi>Winding river</hi>. </p></note><note xml:id='N_11'><p> Tacitus de mor. Germ. </p></note><note xml:id='N_12'><p> <hi>Abbé de la Bleterie Remargues ſur la Germaine.</hi> </p></note></div></body>
