<body>
<pb n='1773-020.pbm.txt'/>
<div type="advertisements">
 <p><hi>This Day is Publiſhed</hi>,</p><p>By T. BECKET, Corner of the Adelphi Buildings in the STRAND,</p><p>Bookſeller to their Royal Highneſſes the Prince of <sc>Wales</sc> and Biſhop of <sc>Osnaburgh</sc>,</p><p>FABLES de La FONTAINE,</p><p>Printed at Paris, in Four Volumes Folio.</p><p>This very magnificent Work is propoſed to the Publick at only <hi>Eight</hi> Guineas in Sheets, being but Half the original Price.</p><p>This Edition, which coſt the Artiſts near twenty Years Labour, and the Proprietors upwards of <hi>Fourteen thouſand Pounds Sterling</hi>, is undoubtedly one of the moſt ſuperb Monuments ever erected to the Memory of an Author.</p><p>It is printed with a new Letter, on a fine Paper, manufactured expreſsly for the Work ; every Fable being ornamented by a Head and Tail-piece, deſigned in a new Taſte, by M. <sc>Bachelier</sc>, and executed by M. <sc>T. Papillon</sc> and <sc>Le Sueur</sc>,</p><p>To the Beauty this Work derives from the Printing-preſs, is alſo added the capital Embelliſhment of no leſs than <sc>Two Hundred</sc> and <sc>Seventy-six</sc> Copper-plates; the Deſigns applicable to the Subjects, drawn after Nature, by <sc>Oudry</sc>, one of the moſt celebrated Painters France ever produced for delineating the Animal Creation. The Engravings by the moſt expert Artiſts in their ſeveral Departments, under the Direction of the celebrated M. <sc>Cochin</sc> ; who reviſed and ſuperintended the Whole.</p><p><sc>La Fontaine</sc>'s Life is prefixed, containing many Anecdotes of that exquiſite Fabuliſt, not to be met with elſewhere.</p><p> * * Such Ladies and Gentlemen who are deſirous of being poſſeſſed of this magnificent Work, are requeſted to ſavour the Proprietors with their Commands. <!--  -->
<!-- Vol. II, A The -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-023.pbm.txt'/>
 The following <sc>books</sc> are publiſhed by <sc>t. becket</sc>:</p><p>1. <sc>The</sc> Iliad of Homer. Tranſlated by James Macpherſon, Eſq; in 2 Vols. Royal Paper. 4to. Second Edition, reviſed throughout, and carefully corrected. Price One Guinea and a Half in Boards.</p><p>2. An Introduction to the Hiſtory of Great Britain and Ireland. The Third Edition, reviſed and greatly enlarged. In one Volume 4to. Price 15 s. in Boards.</p><p>3. Memoirs of Ruſſia, from the Year 1727 to the Year 1944. Tranſlated from the Original Manuſcript of the Baron de <sc>Manstein</sc>. Illuſtrated with Maps and Plans, and with the Life of the Author. The Second Edition, carefully corrected throughout, and greatly improved. In one Volume 4to. Price 18s. in Boards.</p><p>4. The Hiſtory of the Britiſh Dominions in North America; from the firſt Diſcovery of that vaſt Continent by Sebaſtian Cabot, in 1497, to its glorious Eſtabliſhment, as confirmed by the late Treaty of Peace in 1763. In 14 Books. Illuſtrated with a new and accurate Map, coloured. In one Volume 4to. Price 18s. in Boards.</p><p>5. A Journal of the Swediſh Ambaſſy, in the Years 1653 and 1054, from the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. Written by the Ambaſſador the Lord Commiſſioner <sc>White-locke</sc>, With an <sc>Appendix</sc> of Original Papers. 2 Vols. 4to. 1l. 11s. 6d. Boards.</p>
 <p>** This very curious and valuable Work is printed from the Author's own Manuſcript (which is depoſited in the Britiſh Muſeum for public Inſpection) and at the Requeſt of his Grandſon Carleton Whitelocke, of Prior's Wood, near Dublin, Eſq; of Lord Chancellor Bowes, late of the Kingdom of Ireland ; of Archbiſhop Secker, late Primate of all England; and of Arthur Onflow, Eſq; late Speaker of the Houſe of Commons.</p><p>6. Dr. Goldſmith's Hiſtory of England, to the Acceſſion of his preſent Majeſty. Tlluſtrated with the Heads of all the Kings and Queens. 4 Vols. 8vo. 1l. 4s. bound.</p><p>7. Atkyn's Antiquities of Gloceſterſhire, With a great Number of fine Plates. Folio. Large Paper. 3l. 3s.</p><p>8. The ſame Book. Small Paper, 2l. 10s.</p><p>9. Harrington's Works. New Edition. Royal Quarto, 1l. 1s.</p>
 <p>10. Ludlow's Memoirs, New Edition. Royal Quarto. 1l. 1s.</p>
 <p>11. The Works of Algernon Sidney. New Edition. Royal Quarto, 1l. 7s.</p><p>12. Addiſon's Works. Beautifully printed by Baſkerville. 4 Vols. Royal Quarto. 4l. 4s.</p><p>13. Pope's Works. New Edition. 6 Vols. 12mo. 18s.</p>
 <p>14. —— Homer. New Edition. 9 Vols. 12mo. 1l. 7s.</p><p>15. —— Ditto. New Edition. 9 Vols. Small 8vo. 1l. 11s. 6d. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--   -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-026.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-029.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-032.pbm.txt'/>
 <div><head>THE POEMS OF O S S I A N.</head><p> TRANSLATED By JAMES MACPHERSON, Eſq</p><p>VOL. II.</p><p>A NEW EDITION,</p><p>Carefully corrected, and greatly improved.</p><p>LONDON:</p><p>Printed for <sc>W.Strahan</sc>; and <sc>T.Becket</sc>, in the Strand. Bookſeller to their Royal Highneſſes the Prince of <sc>Wales</sc> and Biſhop of <sc>Osnabrugh</sc>.</p><p>MDCCLXXI</p><p></p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-035.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-038.pbm.txt'/>
<!--   -->
<!--  -->
<!--   -->
 <div><head>CONTENTS OF THE SECOND VOLUME.</head><p></p><p>TEMORA, Book I — — Page 1 Book II. — — 29 Book III. — — 53 Book IV. — — 75 Book V. — — 97 Book VI. — — 117 Book VII. — — 139 Book VIII. — — 157</p><p>CONLATH and CUTHONA, — 181</p><p>BERRATHON, — — — 191</p><p>A DISSERTATION concerning the ÆRA of OSSIAN, — — 211</p><p>A DISSERTATION concerning the POEMS of OSSIAN, — 233</p><p>A critical DISSERTATION on the POEMS of OSSIAN, — 281 </p></div> <!--  -->
<!-- 3 TE- -->
<!--  -->
<pb n='1773-041.pbm.txt'/>
 <!--  -->

</body>
