<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <front>
  <titlePage source="NYPL">
   <titlePart>CARRIC-THURA: A POEM.</titlePart>
  </titlePage>
  <pb xml:id="P73110052" facs="../img/1773-201.pbm"/>
  <div>
   <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>Fingal, returning from an expedition which he had made into the Roman province, reſolved to
    viſit Cathulla king of Iniſtore, and brother to Comala, whoſe ſtory is related, at large, in the
    preceding dramatic poem. Upon his coming in ſight of Carric-thura, the palace of Cathulla, he
    obſerved a flame on its top, which, in thoſe days, was a ſignal of diſtreſs. The wind drove him
    into a bay, at ſome diſtance from Carric-thura, and he was obliged to paſs the night on the
    ſhore. Next day he attacked the army of Frothal king of Sora, who had beſieged Cathulla in his
    palace of Carric-thura, and took Frothal himſelf priſoner, after he had engaged him in a ſingle
    combat. The deliverance of Carric-thura is the ſubject of the poem, but ſeveral other epiſodes
    are interwoven with it. It appears from tradition, that this poem was addreſſed to a Culdee, or
    one of the firſt Chriſtian miſſionaries, and that the ſtory of the <hi>Spirit of Loda</hi>,
    ſuppoſed to be the ancient Odin of Scandinavia, was introduced by Oſſian in oppoſition to the
    Culdee's doctrine. Be this as it will, it lets us into Oſſian's notions of a ſuperior being; and
    ſhews that he was not addicted to the ſuperſtition which prevailed all the world over, before
    the introduction of Chriſtianity. </p>
  </div>

  <pb xml:id="P73110053" facs="../img/1773-204.pbm"/>
  <!-- [ 53 ] -->
 </front>
 <body>
  <head>CARRIC-THURA: A POEM.</head>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Hast</hi><note>
   <p> The ſong of Ullin, with which the poem opens, is in a lyric meaſure. It was uſual with
    Fingal, when he returned from his expeditions, to ſend his bards ſinging before him. This
    ſpecies of triumph is called, by Oſſian, the <hi>ſong of victory</hi>. </p>
   </note> thou left thy blue courſe in heaven, golden-haired ſon of the ſky ! The weſt has opened
   its gates ; the bed of thy repoſe is there. The waves come to behold thy beauty. They lift their
   trembling heads. They ſee thee lovely in thy ſleep; they ſhrink away with fear. Reſt, in thy
   ſhadowy cave, O ſun! let thy return be in joy.</p>
  <p>But let a thouſand lights ariſe to the ſound of the harps of Selma : let the beam ſpread in the
   hall, the king of ſhells is returned ! The ſtrife of Carun is paſt<note>
   <p> Oſſian has celebrated the <hi>ſtrife of Crona</hi>, in a particular poem. This poem is
    connected with it, but it was impoſſible for the tranſlator to procure that part which relates
    to Crona, with any degree of purity. </p>
   </note>, like ſounds that are no more. Raiſe the ſong, O bards, the king is returned, with his
   fame!</p>
  <p>
   <!-- E3 SUCH -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110054" facs="../img/1773-207.pbm"/>
   <!-- 54 CARRIC-THURA: --> <hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were the words of Ullin, when Fingal returned
   from war: when he returned in the fair bluſhing of youth, with all his heavy locks. His blue arms
   were on the hero; like a light cloud on the ſun, when he moves in his robes of miſt, and ſhews
   but half his beams. His heroes follow the king : the feaſt of ſhells is ſpread. Fingal turns to
   his bards, and bids the ſong to riſe.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Voices</hi> of ecchoing Cona ! he ſaid, O bards of other times! Ye, on whoſe
   ſouls the blue hoſts of our fathers riſe! ſtrike the harp in my hall; and let me hear the ſong.
   Pleaſant is the joy of grief! it is like the ſhower of ſpring, when it ſoftens the branch of the
   oak, and the young leaf rears its green head. Sing on, O bards, to-morrow we lift the ſail. My
   blue courſe is through the ocean, to Carric-thura's walls; the moſſy walls of Sarno, where Comála
   dwelt, There the noble Cathulla, ſpreads the feaſt of ſhells. The boars of his woods are many ;
   the ſound of the chace ſhall ariſe !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Cronnan</hi><note>
   <p> One ſhould think that the parts of Shilric and Vinvela were repreſented by Cronnan and
    Minona, whoſe very names denote that they were ſingers, who performed in public. Cronnan
    ſignifies <hi>a mournful ſound</hi>, Minona, or Min-'onn, <hi>ſoft air.</hi>, All the dramatic
    poems of Oſſian appear to have been preſented before Fingal, upon ſolemn occaſions. </p>
   </note>, ſon of the ſong! ſaid Ullin, Minona, graceful at the harp! raiſe the tale of
   <!-- Shire, -->
   <!-- Q air -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110055" facs="../img/1773-210.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 55 --> Shilric, to pleaſe the king of Morven. Let Vinvela come in her beauty,
   like the ſhowery bow, when it ſhews its lovely head on the lake, and the ſetting ſun is bright.
   She comes, O Fingal ! her voice is ſoft but ſad. </p>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Vinvela.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">My</hi> love is a ſon of the hill. He purſues the flying deer. His grey dogs
    are panting around him ; his bow-ſtring ſounds in the wind. Doſt thou reſt by the fount of the
    rock, or by the noiſe of the mountain-ſtream? the ruſhes are nodding to the wind, the miſt flies
    over the hill. I will approach my love unſeen ; I will behold him from the rock. Lovely I ſaw
    thee firſt by the aged oak of Branno<note>
    <p> Bran, or Branno, ſignifies a <hi>mountain-ſtream </hi>: it is here ſome river known by that
     name, in the days of Oſſian. There are ſeveral ſmall rivers in the north of Scotland ſtill
     retaining the name of Bran ; in particular one which falls into the Tay at Dunkeld. </p>
    </note> ; thou wert returning tall from the chace ; the faireſt among thy friends. </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Shilric.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">What</hi> voice is that I hear ? that voice like the ſummer-wind ! I ſit not by
    the nodding <!-- FE 4 ruihes ; -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110056" facs="../img/1773-213.pbm"/>
    <!-- 56 CARRIC-THURA: --> ruſhes ; I hear not the fount of the rock. Afar, Vinvela<note>
    <p> Bhin bheul, <hi>a woman with a melodious voice</hi>. <hi>Bh</hi> in the Galic language has
     the ſame ſound with the <hi>v</hi> in Engliſh. </p>
    </note>, afar, I go to the wars of Fingal. My dogs attend me no more. No more I tread the hill.
    No more from on high I ſee thee, fair-moving by the ſtream of the plain; bright as the bow of
    heaven; as the moon on the weſtern wave. </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Vinvela.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Then</hi> thou art gone, O Shilric ! I am alone on the hill ! The deer are ſeen
    on the brow ; void of fear they graze along. No more they dread the wind; no more the ruſtling
    tree. The hunter is far removed; he is in the field of graves. Strangers! ſons of the waves!
    ſpare my lovely Shilric ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Shilric.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">If</hi> fall I muſt in the field, raiſe high my grave, Vinvela. Grey ſtones and
    heaped-up earth, ſhall mark me to future times. When the hunter ſhall ſit by the mound, and
    produce his food at noon, “Some warrior reſts here,” he will ſay ; and my fame ſhall live in his
    praiſe. Remember me, Vinvela, when low on earth I lie! <!-- VINvVELE4. -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110057" facs="../img/1773-216.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E M. 67 --> </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Vinvela.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Yes</hi>! I will remember thee; alas ! my Shilric will fall! What ſhall I do,
    my love ! when thou art for ever gone? Through theſe hills I will go at noon : I will go through
    the ſilent heath, There I will ſee the place of thy reſt, returning from the chace. Alas! my
    Shilric will fall ; but I will remember Shilric.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">And</hi> I remember the chief, ſaid the king of woody Morven; he conſumed the
    battle in his rage. But now my eyes behold him not. I met him, one day, on the hill; his cheek
    was pale; his brow was dark. The ſigh was frequent in his breaſt: his ſteps were towards the
    deſart. But now he is not in the crowd of my chiefs, when the ſounds of my ſhields ariſe. Dwells
    he in the narrow houſe<note>
    <p> The grave. </p>
    </note>, the chief of high Carmora<note>
    <p> Carn-mór, <hi>high rocky hill.</hi> </p>
    </note> ?</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Cronnan</hi> ! ſaid Ullin of other times, raiſe the ſong of Shilric; when he
    returned to his hills, and Vinvela was no more. He leaned on her grey moſſy ſtone ; he thought
    Vinvela lived. He ſaw her fair moving<note>
    <p>The diſtinction which the ancient Scots made between good and bad ſpirits, was, that the
     former appeared ſometimes in the day-time in lonely unfrequented places, but the latter never
     but by night, and in a diſmal gloomy ſcene. </p>
    </note>on the plain: but the <!-- bright -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110058" facs="../img/1773-219.pbm"/>
    <!-- 58 CARRIC-THURA: --> bright form laſted not : the ſun-beam fled from the field, and ſhe was
    ſeen no more. Hear the ſong of Shilric, it is ſoft but ſad!</p>
   <p>I <hi rend="sc">sit</hi> by the moſſy fountain; on the top of the hill of winds. One tree is
    ruſtling above me. Dark waves roll over the heath. The lake is troubled below. The deer deſcend
    fron the hill. No hunter at a diſtance is ſeen. It is mid-day : but all is ſilent. Sad are my
    thoughts alone. Didſt thou but appear, O my love, a wanderer on the heath ! thy hair floating on
    the wind behind thee; thy boſom heaving on the ſight; thine eyes full of tears for thy friends,
    whom the miſt of the hill had concealed ! Thee I would comfort, my love, and bring thee to thy
    father's houſe !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> is it ſhe that there appears, like a beam of light on the heath? bright
    as the moon in autumn, as the ſun in a ſummer-ſtorm, comeſt thou, O maid, over rocks, over
    mountains to me? She ſpeaks : but how weak her voice ! like the breeze in the reeds of the
    lake.</p>
   <p>“<hi rend="sc">Returnest</hi> thou ſafe from the war? Where are thy friends, my love? I heard
    of thy death on the hill; I heard and mourned thee, Shilric! Yes, my fair, I return; but I alone
    of my race. Thou ſhalt ſee them no more : their graves I raiſed on the plain, But <!-- why -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110059" facs="../img/1773-222.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E NM. 69g --> why art thou on the deſert hill? Why on the heath alone ?”</p>
   <p>“<hi rend="sc">Alone</hi> I am, O Shilric! alone in the winter-houſe, With grief for thee I
    fell. Shilric, I am pale in the tomb.”</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">She</hi> fleets, ſhe ſails away ; as miſt before the wind ! and, wilt thou not
    ſtay, Vinvela ? Stay and behold my tears ! fair thou appeareſt, Vinvela ! fair thou waſt, when
    alive !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">By</hi> the moſſy fountain I will ſit; on the top of the hill of winds. When
    mid-day is ſilent around, O talk with me, Vinvela! come on the light-winged gale ! on the breeze
    of the deſart, come! Let me hear thy voice, as thou paſſeſt, when mid-day is ſilent around !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> was the ſong of Cronnan, on the night of Selma's joy. But morning roſe
    in the eaſt ; the blue waters rolled in light. Fingal bade his ſails to riſe; the winds came
    ruſtling from their hills. Iniſtore roſe to fight, and Carric-thura's moſſy towers! But the ſign
    of diſtreſs was on their top : the warning flame edged with ſmoke. The king of Morven ſtruck his
    breaſt: he aſſumed, at once, his ſpear. His darkened brow bends forward to the coaſt: he looks
    back to the lagging winds. His hair is diſordered on his back. The ſilence of the king is
    terrible ! <!-- NiGuT --> </p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110060" facs="../img/1773-225.pbm"/>
    <!-- 60 CARRIC-THURA: --> <hi rend="sc">Night</hi> came down on the ſea; Rotha's bay received
    the ſhip. A rock bends along the coaſt with all its ecchoing wood. On the top is the circle<note>
    <p> <hi>The circle of Loda</hi> is ſuppoſed to be a place of worſhip among the Scandinavians, as
     the ſpirit of Loda is thought to be the ſame with their god Odin. </p>
    </note> of Loda, the moſſy ſtone of power! A narrow plain ſpreads beneath, covered with graſs
    and aged trees, which the midnight winds, in their wrath, had torn from the ſhaggy rock. The
    blue courſe of a ſtream is there ! the lonely blaſt of ocean purſues the thiſtle's beard. The
    flame of three oaks aroſe: the feaſt is ſpread around: but the ſoul of the king is ſad, for
    Carric-thura's Chief diſtreſt.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> wan, cold moon roſe, in the eaſt. Sleep deſcended on the youths! Their
    blue helmets glitter to the beam ; the fading fire decays. But ſleep did not reſt on the king :
    he roſe in the midſt of his arms, and ſlowly aſcended the hill to behold the flame of Sarno's
    tower.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> flame was dim and diſtant; the moon hid her red face in the eaſt. A
    blaſt came from the mountain, on its wings was the ſpirit of Loda. He came to his place in his terrors<note>
    <p> He is deſcribed, in a ſimile, in the poem concerning the death of Cuchullin. </p>
    </note>, and ſhook <!-- Es -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110061" facs="../img/1773-228.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E M. 61 --> his duſky ſpear. His eyes appear like flames in his dark face; his voice
    is like diſtant thunder. Fingal advanced his ſpear in night, and raiſed his voice on high.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of night, retire : call thy winds and fly ! Why doſt thou come to my
    preſence, with thy ſhadowy arms? Do I fear thy gloomy form, ſpirit of diſmal Loda? Weak is thy
    ſhield of clouds : feeble is that meteor, thy ſword. The blaſt rolls them together; and thou
    thyſelf art loſt. Fly from my preſence ſon of night! call thy winds and fly !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Dost</hi> thou force me from my place, replied the hollow voice? The people bend
    before me. I turn the battle in the field of the brave. I look on the nations and they vaniſh:
    my noſtrils pour the blaſt of death. I come abroad on the winds: the tempeſts are before my
    face. But my dwelling is calm, above the clouds; the fields of my reſt are pleaſant.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Dwell</hi> in thy pleaſant fields, ſaid the king : Let Comhal's ſon be forgot.
    Do my ſteps aſcend, from my hills, into thy peaceful plains ? Do I meet thee, with a ſpear, on
    thy cloud, ſpirit of diſmal Loda? Why then doſt thou frown on me? why ſhake thine airy ſpear ?
    Thou frowneſt in vain: I never fled from the <!-- mighty -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110062" facs="../img/1773-231.pbm"/>
    <!-- G2 CARRIC-THURA: --> mighty in war. And ſhall the ſons of the wind frighten the king of
    Morven? No: he knows the weakneſs of their arms !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Fly</hi> to thy land, replied the form : receive the wind and fly ! The blaſts
    are in the hollow of my hand : the courſe of the ſtorm is mine. The king of Sora is my ſon, he
    bends at the ſtone of my power. His battle is around Carricthura ; and he will prevail ! Fly to
    thy land, ſon of Comhal, or feel my flaming wrath !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> lifted high his ſhadowy ſpear ! He bent forward his dreadful height.
    Fingal, advancing, drew his ſword; the blade of dark-brown Luno<note>
    <p> The famous ſword of Fingal, made by Lun, or Lano, a ſmith of Lochlin. </p>
    </note>. The gleaming path of the ſteel winds thro' the gloomy ghoſt. The form fell ſhapeleſs
    into air, like a column of ſmoke, which the ſtaff of the boy diſturbs, as it riſes from the
    half-extinguiſhed furnace.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſpirit of Loda ſhrieked, as, rolled into himſelf, he roſe on the wind.
    Iniſtore ſhook at the ſound. The waves heard it on the deep. They ſtopped, in their courſe, with
    fear : the friends of Fingal ſtarted, at once; and took their heavy ſpears. They miſſed the king
    : they roſe in rage; all their arms reſound ! <!-- THE -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110063" facs="../img/1773-234.pbm"/> </p>
   <p><!-- A P O E M. 63 --> The moon came forth in the eaſt. Fingal returned in the gleam of his
    arms. The joy of his youth was great, their ſouls ſettled, as a ſea from a ſtorm. Ullin raiſed
    the ſong of gladneſs. The hills of Iniſtore rejoiced. The flame of the oak aroſe; and the tales
    of heroes are told.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> Frothal, Sora's wrathful king, ſits in ſadneſs beneath a tree. The hoſt
    ſpreads around Carric-thura. He looks towards the walls with rage. He longs for the blood of
    Cathulla, who, once, overcame him in war. When Annir reigned<note>
    <p> Annir was alſo the father of Erragon, who was king after the death of his brother Frothal.
     The death of Erragon is the ſubject of <hi>the Battle of Lora</hi>, a poem in this collection.
    </p>
    </note> in Sora, the father of ſea-borne Frothal, a ſtorm aroſe on the ſea, and carried Frothal
    to Iniſtore. Three days he feaſted in Sarno's halls, and ſaw the ſlow rolling eyes of Comála. He
    loved her, in the flame of youth, and ruſhed to ſeize the white-armed maid. Cathulla met the
    chief. The gloomy battle roſe. Frothal was bound in the hall; three days he pined alone. On the
    fourth, Sarno ſent him to his ſhip, and he returned to his land. But wrath darkened in his ſoul
    againſt the noble <!-- Cathulla. -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110064" facs="../img/1773-237.pbm"/>
    <!-- 64. CARRIC-THURA: --> Cathulla. When Annir's ſtone<note>
    <p> That is, after the death of Annir. To erect the ſtone of one's fame, was, in other words, to
     ſay that the perſon was dead. </p>
    </note> of fame aroſe, Frothal came in his ſtrength. The battle burned round Carric-thura, and
    Sarno's moſſy walls.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Morning</hi> roſe on Iniſtore. Frothal ſtruck his dark-brown ſhield. His chiefs
    ſtarted at the ſound; they ſtood, but their eyes were turned to the ſea. They ſaw Fingal coming
    in his ſtrength; and firſt the noble Thubar ſpoke. “Who comes like the ſtag of the deſart, with
    all his herd behind him? Frothal, it is a foe! I fee his forward ſpear. Perhaps it is the king
    of Morven, Fingal the firſt of men. His deeds are well known in Lochlin; the blood of his foes
    is in Starno's halls. Shall I aſk the peace<note>
    <p> Honourable terms of peace. </p>
    </note> of kings? His ſword is the bolt of heaven!”</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of the feeble hand, ſaid Frothal, ſhall my days begin in a cloud? Shall
    I yield before I have conquered, chief of ſtreamy Tora? The people would ſay in Sora, Frothal
    flew forth like a meteor; but a darkneſs has met him; and his fame is no more. No: Thubar, I
    will never yield ; my fame ſhall ſurround me like light, No : I will never yield, chief of
    ſtreamy Tora ! <!-- Hs. --> </p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110065" facs="../img/1773-240.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E M. 65 --> <hi rend="sc">He</hi> went forth with the ſtream of his people, but they
    met a rock: Fingal ſtood unmoved, broken they rolled back from his ſide. Nor did they ſafely
    fly; the ſpear of the king purſued their ſteps. The field is covered with heroes. A riſing hill
    preſerved the foe.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Frothal</hi> ſaw their flight. The rage of his boſom roſe. He bent his eyes to
    the ground, and called the noble Thubar. Thubar ! my people are fled. My fame has ceaſed to
    ariſe. I will fight the king; I feel my burning ſoul! Send a bard to demand the combat. Speak
    not against Frothal's words! But, Thubar! I love a maid; she dwells by Thano's ſtream, the
    white-boſomed daughter of Herman, Utha with ſoft-rolling eyes. She feared the low-laid Comála ;
    her ſecret ſighs roſe, when I ſpread the ſail. Tell to Utha of harps, that my ſoul delighted in
    her!</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were his words, reſolved to fight, The ſoft ſigh of Utha was near !
    She had followed her hero, in the armour of a man. She rolled her eye on the youth, in ſecret,
    from beneath her ſteel. She ſaw the bard as he went; the ſpear fell thrice from her hand ! Her
    looſe hair flew on the wind. Her white breaſt roſe, with ſighs. She raiſed her eyes to the king.
    She would ſpeak, but thrice ſhe failed, <!-- VoL.  . F FiNGAL --></p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110066" facs="../img/1773-243.pbm"/>
    <!-- 66 CARRIC-THURA: --> <hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> heard the words of the bard; he came in the
    ſtrength of his ſteel. They mixed their deathful ſpears: They raiſed the gleam of their arms.
    But the ſword of Fingal deſcended and cut Frothal's ſhield in twain. His fair ſide is expoſed ;
    half bent he foreſees his death. Darkneſs gathered on Utha's ſoul. The tear rolled down her
    cheek. She ruſhed to cover the chief with her ſhield; but a fallen oak met her ſteps. She fell
    on her arm of ſnow; her ſhield, her helmet flew wide. Her white boſom heaved to the ſight; her
    dark-brown hair is ſpread on earth.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> pitied the white-armed maid ! he ſtayed the uplifted ſword. The tear
    was in the eye of the king, as, bending forward, he ſpoke. “King of ſtreamy Sora ! fear not the
    ſword of Fingal. It was never ſtained with the blood of the vanquiſhed ; it never pierced a
    fallen foe. Let thy people rejoice by thy native ſtreams. Let the maids of thy love be glad. Why
    ſhouldeſt thou fall in thy youth, King of ſtreamy Sora ?” Frothal heard the words of Fingal, and
    ſaw the riſing maid: they<note>
    <p> Frothal and Utha, </p>
    </note> ſtood in ſilence, in their beauty : like two young trees of the plain, when the ſhower
    of ſpring is on their leaves, and the loud winds are laid. <!-- DAUGHTER --> </p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110067" facs="../img/1773-246.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E AM. 67 --> <hi rend="sc">Daughter</hi> of Herman, ſaid Frothal, didſt thou come
    from Tora's ſtreams ; didſt thou come, in thy beauty, to behold thy warrior low ? But he was low
    before the mighty, maid of the ſlow-rolling eye ! The feeble did not overcome the ſon of
    car-borne Annir ! Terrible art thou, O king of Morven! in battles of the ſpear. But, in peace,
    thou art like the ſun, when he looks thro' a ſilent ſhower: the flowers lift their fair heads
    before him ; the gales ſhake their ruſtling wings. O that thou wert in Sora ! that my feaſt were
    ſpread The future kings of Sora would ſee thy arms and rejoice. They would rejoice at the fame
    of their fathers, who beheld the mighty Fingal !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Annir, replied the king, the fame of Sora's race ſhall be heard !
    When chiefs are ſtrong in war, then does the ſong ariſe ! But if their ſwords are ſtretched over
    the feeble : if the blood of the weak has ſtained their arms; the bard ſhall forget them in the
    ſong, and their tombs ſhall not be known. The ſtranger ſhall come and build there, and remove
    the heaped-up earth. An half-worn ſword ſhall riſe before him; bending above it, he will ſay,
    “Theſe are the arms of the chiefs of old, but their names are not in ſong.” Come thou, O
    Frothal, to <!-- F 2 the -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110068" facs="../img/1773-249.pbm"/>
    <!-- 68 CARRIC-THURA: --> the feaſt of Iniſtore ; let the maid of thy love be there ; let our
    faces brighten with joy !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> took his ſpear, moving in the ſteps of his might. The gates of
    Carric-thura are opened wide. The feaſt of ſhells is ſpread. The ſoft ſound of muſic aroſe.
    Gladneſs brightened in the hall. The voice of Ullin was heard; the harp of Selma was ſtrung.
    Utha rejoiced in his preſence, and demanded the ſong of grief; the big tear hung in her eye,
    when the ſoft<note>
    <p> There is a propriety in introducing this epiſode, as the ſituations of Crimora and Utha were
     ſo ſimilar. </p>
    </note> Crimora ſpoke. Crimora the daughter of Rinval, who dwelt at Lotha's<note>
    <p> Lotha was the ancient name of one of the great rivers in the north of Scotland. The only one
     of them that ſtill retains a name of a like ſound is Locky, in Inverneſsſhire; but whether it
     is the river mentioned here, the tranſlator will not pretend to ſay. </p>
    </note> roaring ſtream ! The tale was long, but lovely ; and pleaſed the bluſhing Utha. </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora</hi>.</speaker>
   <note>
    <p> Cri-móra, <hi>a woman of a great ſoul.</hi> </p></note>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Who</hi> cometh from the hill, like a cloud tinged with the beam of the weſt?
    Whoſe voice is that, loud as the wind, but pleaſant as the harp of Carril<note>
    <p> Perhaps the Carril mentioned here is the ſame with Carril the ſon of Kinſena, Cuchullin's
     bard. The name itſelf is proper to any bard, as it ſignifies <hi>a ſprightly and harmonious
     ſound.</hi> </p>
    </note>? It is my love in the light of <!-- şteel ; -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110069" facs="../img/1773-252.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O EB M. 6g --> ſteel; but ſad is his darkened brow ! Live the mighty race of Fingal? or
    what darkens in Connal's ſoul<note>
    <p> Connal, the ſon of Diaran, was one of the moſt famous heroes of Fingal; he was ſlain in a
     battle againſt Dargo a Briton ; but whether by the hand of the enemy, or that of his miſtreſs,
     tradition does not determine. </p>
    </note> ?</p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Connal.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">They</hi> live. They return from the chace, like a ſtream of light. The ſun is
    on their ſhields. Like a ridge of fire they deſcend the hill. Loud is the voice of the youth !
    the war, my love, is near ! To-morrow the dreadful Dargo comes to try the force of our race. The
    race of Fingal he defies; the race of battle and wounds ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Connal</hi>, I ſaw his ſails like grey miſt on the dark-brown wave. They ſlowly
    came to land, Connal, many are the warriors of Dargo! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Connal.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Bring</hi> me thy father's ſhield ; the boſſy, iron ſhield of Rinval ; that
    ſhield like the full-orbed moon, when ſhe moves darkened through heaven. <!-- F 3 CRIMORA, -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110070" facs="../img/1773-255.pbm"/>
    <!-- 70 CARRIC-THURA: --> </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">That</hi> ſhield I bring, O Connal; but it did not defend my father. By the
    ſpear of Gormar he fell. Thou may'ft fall, O Connal ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Connal.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Fall</hi> I may! But raiſe my tomb, Crimora ! Grey ſtones, a mound of earth,
    ſhall ſend my name to other times. Bend thy red eye over my grave, beat thy mournful heaving
    breaſt. Though fair thou art, my love, as the light; more pleaſant than the gale of the hill;
    yet I will not here remain. Raiſe my tomb, Crimora ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Then</hi> give me thoſe arms that gleam; that ſword, and that ſpear of ſteel. I
    ſhall meet Dargo with Connal, and aid him in the fight. Farewel, ye rocks of Ardven! ye deer !
    and ye ſtreams of the hill! We ſhall return no more. Our tombs are diſtant far ! </p>
  </sp>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">And</hi> did they return no more?” ſaid Utha's burſting figh. “Fell the mighty
   in battle, and did Crimora live? Her ſteps were lonely ; her ſoul was ſad for Connal. Was he not
   young and lovely; like the beam of the <!-- şetting -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110071" facs="../img/1773-258.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 71 --> ſetting ſun ?” Ullin ſaw the virgin's tear, he took the ſoftly-trembling
   harp : the ſong was lovely, but ſad, and ſilence was in Carric-thura,</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Autumn</hi> is dark on the mountains ; grey miſt reſts on the hills. The
   whirlwind is heard on the heath. Dark rolls the river through the narrow plain. A tree ſtands
   alone on the hill, and marks the ſlumbering Connal. The leaves whirl round with the wind, and
   ſtrew the grave of the dead. At times are ſeen here the ghoſts of the departed, when the muſing
   hunter alone ſtalks ſlowly over the heath.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Who</hi> can reach the ſource of thy race, O Connal ? who recount thy fathers?
   Thy family grew like an oak on the mountain, which meeteth the wind with its lofty head, But now
   it is torn from the earth. Who ſhall ſupply the place of Connal? Here was the din of arms; here
   the groans of the dying. Bloody are the wars of Fingal! O Connal! it was here thou didſt fall.
   Thine arm was like a ſtorm; thy ſword a beam of the ſky; thy height, a rock on the plain; thine
   eyes, a furnace of fire. Louder than a ſtorm was thy voice, in the battles of thy ſteel. Warriors
   fell by thy ſword, as the thiſtle by the ſtaff of a boy. Dargo the mighty came on, darkening in
   his rage. His brows were gathered into wrath. His eyes like two caves <!-- F 4 in -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110072" facs="../img/1773-261.pbm"/>
   <!--  CARRIC-THURA: --> in a rock, Bright roſe their ſwords on each ſide; loud was the clang of
   their ſteel.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> daughter of Rinval was near ; Crimora bright in the armour of man; her
   yellow hair is looſe behind, her bow is in her hand. She followed the youth to the war, Connal
   her much-beloved. She drew the ſtring on Dargo; but erring ſhe pierced her Connal. He falls like
   an oak on the plain; like a rock from the ſhaggy hill. What ſhall ſhe do, hapleſs maid ! He
   bleeds ; her Connal dies! All the night long ſhe cries, and all the day, “O Connal, my love, and
   my friend!” With grief the ſad mourner dies! Earth here incloſes the lovelieſt pair on the hill.
   The graſs grows between the ſtones of the tomb; I often ſit in the mournful ſhade. The wind ſighs
   through the graſs ; their memory ruſhes on my mind. Undiſturbed you now ſleep together; in the
   tomb of the mountain you reſt alone !</p>
  <p>And ſoft be their reſt, ſaid Utha, hapleſs children of ſtreamy Lotha! I will remember them with
   tears, and my ſecret ſong ſhall riſe; when the wind is in the groves of Tora, when the ſtream is
   roaring near. Then ſhall they come on my ſoul, with all their lovely grief !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Three</hi> days feaſted the kings : on the fourth their white ſails aroſe. The
   winds of the north <!--   drove -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110073" facs="../img/1773-264.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. -3 --> drove Fingal to Morven's woody land. But the ſpirit of Loda ſat, in his
   cloud, behind the ſhips of Frothal. He hung forward with all his blaſts, and ſpread the
   white-boſomed ſails. The wounds of his form were not forgot ; he ſtill feared<note>
   <p> The ſtory of Fingal and the ſpirit of Loda, ſuppoſed to be the famous Odin, is the moſt
    extravagant fiction in all Oſſian's poems. It is not, however, without precedents in the beſt
    poets; and it muſt be ſaid for Oſſian, that he ſays nothing but what perfectly agreed with the
    notions of the times, concerning ghoſts. They thought the ſouls of the dead were material, and
    conſequently ſuſceptible of pain. Whether a proof could be drawn from this paſſage, that Oſſian
    had no notion of a divinity, I ſhall leave to others to determine: it appears, however, that he
    was of opinion, that ſuperior beings ought to take no notice of what paſſed among men. </p>
   </note> the hand of the king ! <!-- CARTHORN: -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110074" facs="../img/1773-268.pbm"/> </p>
 </body>
</text>
