<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <front>
  <titlePage source="NYPL">
   <titlePart>CARRIC-THURA: A POEM.</titlePart>
  </titlePage>
  <pb xml:id="P73110052" facs="../img/1773-201.pbm"/>
  <div>
   <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>Fingal, returning from an expedition which he had made into the Roman province, reşolved to
    vişit Cathulla king of Iniştore, and brother to Comala, whoşe ştory is related, at large, in the
    preceding dramatic poem. Upon his coming in şight of Carric-thura, the palace of Cathulla, he
    obşerved a flame on its top, which, in thoşe days, was a şignal of diştreşs. The wind drove him
    into a bay, at şome diştance from Carric-thura, and he was obliged to paşs the night on the
    şhore. Next day he attacked the army of Frothal king of Sora, who had beşieged Cathulla in his
    palace of Carric-thura, and took Frothal himşelf prişoner, after he had engaged him in a şingle
    combat. The deliverance of Carric-thura is the şubject of the poem, but şeveral other epişodes
    are interwoven with it. It appears from tradition, that this poem was addreşşed to a Culdee, or
    one of the firşt Chriştian mişşionaries, and that the ştory of the <hi>Spirit of Loda</hi>,
    şuppoşed to be the ancient Odin of Scandinavia, was introduced by Oşşian in oppoşition to the
    Culdee's doctrine. Be this as it will, it lets us into Oşşian's notions of a şuperior being; and
    şhews that he was not addicted to the şuperştition which prevailed all the world over, before
    the introduction of Chriştianity. </p>
  </div>

  <pb xml:id="P73110053" facs="../img/1773-204.pbm"/>
  <!-- [ 53 ] -->
 </front>
 <body>
  <head>CARRIC-THURA: A POEM.</head>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Hast</hi><note>
   <p> The şong of Ullin, with which the poem opens, is in a lyric meaşure. It was uşual with
    Fingal, when he returned from his expeditions, to şend his bards şinging before him. This
    şpecies of triumph is called, by Oşşian, the <hi>şong of victory</hi>. </p>
   </note> thou left thy blue courşe in heaven, golden-haired şon of the şky ! The weşt has opened
   its gates ; the bed of thy repoşe is there. The waves come to behold thy beauty. They lift their
   trembling heads. They şee thee lovely in thy şleep; they şhrink away with fear. Reşt, in thy
   şhadowy cave, O şun! let thy return be in joy.</p>
  <p>But let a thouşand lights arişe to the şound of the harps of Selma : let the beam şpread in the
   hall, the king of şhells is returned ! The ştrife of Carun is paşt<note>
   <p> Oşşian has celebrated the <hi>ştrife of Crona</hi>, in a particular poem. This poem is
   connected with it, but it was impoşşible for the tranşlator to procure that part which relates to
   Crona, with any degree of purity. </p></note>, like şounds that are no more. Raişe the şong, O
   bards, the king is returned, with his fame!</p>
  <p>
   <!-- E3 SUCH -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110054" facs="../img/1773-207.pbm"/>
   <!-- 54 CARRIC-THURA: --> <hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were the words of Ullin, when Fingal returned
   from war: when he returned in the fair bluşhing of youth, with all his heavy locks. His blue arms
   were on the hero; like a light cloud on the şun, when he moves in his robes of mişt, and şhews
   but half his beams. His heroes follow the king : the feaşt of şhells is şpread. Fingal turns to
   his bards, and bids the şong to rişe.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Voices</hi> of ecchoing Cona ! he şaid, O bards of other times! Ye, on whoşe
   şouls the blue hoşts of our fathers rişe! ştrike the harp in my hall; and let me hear the şong.
   Pleaşant is the joy of grief! it is like the şhower of şpring, when it şoftens the branch of the
   oak, and the young leaf rears its green head. Sing on, O bards, to-morrow we lift the şail. My
   blue courşe is through the ocean, to Carric-thura's walls; the moşşy walls of Sarno, where Comála
   dwelt, There the noble Cathulla, şpreads the feaşt of şhells. The boars of his woods are many ;
   the şound of the chace şhall arişe !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Cronnan</hi><note>
   <p> One şhould think that the parts of Shilric and Vinvela were repreşented by Cronnan and
   Minona, whoşe very names denote that they were şingers, who performed in public. Cronnan
   şignifies <hi>a mournful şound</hi>, Minona, or Min-'onn, <hi>şoft air.</hi>, All the dramatic
   poems of Oşşian appear to have been preşented before Fingal, upon şolemn occaşions. </p></note>,
   şon of the şong! şaid Ullin, Minona, graceful at the harp! raişe the tale of <!-- Shire, -->
   <!-- Q air -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110055" facs="../img/1773-210.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 55 --> Shilric, to pleaşe the king of Morven. Let Vinvela come in her beauty,
   like the şhowery bow, when it şhews its lovely head on the lake, and the şetting şun is bright.
   She comes, O Fingal ! her voice is şoft but şad. </p>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Vinvela.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">My</hi> love is a şon of the hill. He purşues the flying deer. His grey dogs
    are panting around him ; his bow-ştring şounds in the wind. Doşt thou reşt by the fount of the
    rock, or by the noişe of the mountain-ştream? the ruşhes are nodding to the wind, the mişt flies
    over the hill. I will approach my love unşeen ; I will behold him from the rock. Lovely I şaw
    thee firşt by the aged oak of Branno<note>
    <p> Bran, or Branno, şignifies a <hi>mountain-ştream </hi>: it is here şome river known by that
     name, in the days of Oşşian. There are şeveral şmall rivers in the north of Scotland ştill
     retaining the name of Bran ; in particular one which falls into the Tay at Dunkeld. </p></note>
    ; thou wert returning tall from the chace ; the faireşt among thy friends. </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Shilric.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">What</hi> voice is that I hear ? that voice like the şummer-wind ! I şit not by
    the nodding <!-- FE 4 ruihes ; -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110056" facs="../img/1773-213.pbm"/>
    <!-- 56 CARRIC-THURA: --> ruşhes ; I hear not the fount of the rock. Afar, Vinvela<note>
    <p> Bhin bheul, <hi>a woman with a melodious voice</hi>. <hi>Bh</hi> in the Galic language has
    the şame şound with the <hi>v</hi> in Englişh. </p> </note>, afar, I go to the wars of Fingal.
    My dogs attend me no more. No more I tread the hill. No more from on high I şee thee,
    fair-moving by the ştream of the plain; bright as the bow of heaven; as the moon on the weştern
    wave. </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Vinvela.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Then</hi> thou art gone, O Shilric ! I am alone on the hill ! The deer are şeen
    on the brow ; void of fear they graze along. No more they dread the wind; no more the ruştling
    tree. The hunter is far removed; he is in the field of graves. Strangers! şons of the waves!
    şpare my lovely Shilric ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Shilric.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">If</hi> fall I muşt in the field, raişe high my grave, Vinvela. Grey ştones and
    heaped-up earth, şhall mark me to future times. When the hunter şhall şit by the mound, and
    produce his food at noon, “Some warrior reşts here,” he will şay ; and my fame şhall live in his
    praişe. Remember me, Vinvela, when low on earth I lie! <!-- VINvVELE4. -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110057" facs="../img/1773-216.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E M. 67 --> </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Vinvela.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Yes</hi>! I will remember thee; alas ! my Shilric will fall! What şhall I do,
    my love ! when thou art for ever gone? Through theşe hills I will go at noon : I will go through
    the şilent heath, There I will şee the place of thy reşt, returning from the chace. Alas! my
    Shilric will fall ; but I will remember Shilric.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">And</hi> I remember the chief, şaid the king of woody Morven; he conşumed the
    battle in his rage. But now my eyes behold him not. I met him, one day, on the hill; his cheek
    was pale; his brow was dark. The şigh was frequent in his breaşt: his şteps were towards the
    deşart. But now he is not in the crowd of my chiefs, when the şounds of my şhields arişe. Dwells
    he in the narrow houşe<note>
    <p> The grave. </p></note>, the chief of high Carmora<note>
    <p> Carn-mór, <hi>high rocky hill.</hi> </p></note> ?</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Cronnan</hi> ! şaid Ullin of other times, raişe the şong of Shilric; when he
    returned to his hills, and Vinvela was no more. He leaned on her grey moşşy ştone ; he thought
    Vinvela lived. He şaw her fair moving<note>
    <p>The diştinction which the ancient Scots made between good and bad şpirits, was, that the
    former appeared şometimes in the day-time in lonely unfrequented places, but the latter never
    but by night, and in a dişmal gloomy şcene. </p> </note>on the plain: but the <!-- bright -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110058" facs="../img/1773-219.pbm"/>
    <!-- 58 CARRIC-THURA: --> bright form laşted not : the şun-beam fled from the field, and şhe was
    şeen no more. Hear the şong of Shilric, it is şoft but şad!</p>
   <p>I <hi rend="sc">sit</hi> by the moşşy fountain; on the top of the hill of winds. One tree is
    ruştling above me. Dark waves roll over the heath. The lake is troubled below. The deer deşcend
    fron the hill. No hunter at a diştance is şeen. It is mid-day : but all is şilent. Sad are my
    thoughts alone. Didşt thou but appear, O my love, a wanderer on the heath ! thy hair floating on
    the wind behind thee; thy boşom heaving on the şight; thine eyes full of tears for thy friends,
    whom the mişt of the hill had concealed ! Thee I would comfort, my love, and bring thee to thy
    father's houşe !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> is it şhe that there appears, like a beam of light on the heath? bright
    as the moon in autumn, as the şun in a şummer-ştorm, comeşt thou, O maid, over rocks, over
    mountains to me? She şpeaks : but how weak her voice ! like the breeze in the reeds of the
    lake.</p>
   <p>“<hi rend="sc">Returnest</hi> thou şafe from the war? Where are thy friends, my love? I heard
    of thy death on the hill; I heard and mourned thee, Shilric! Yes, my fair, I return; but I alone
    of my race. Thou şhalt şee them no more : their graves I raişed on the plain, But <!-- why -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110059" facs="../img/1773-222.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E NM. 69g --> why art thou on the deşert hill? Why on the heath alone ?”</p>
   <p>“<hi rend="sc">Alone</hi> I am, O Shilric! alone in the winter-houşe, With grief for thee I
    fell. Shilric, I am pale in the tomb.”</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">She</hi> fleets, şhe şails away ; as mişt before the wind ! and, wilt thou not
    ştay, Vinvela ? Stay and behold my tears ! fair thou appeareşt, Vinvela ! fair thou waşt, when
    alive !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">By</hi> the moşşy fountain I will şit; on the top of the hill of winds. When
    mid-day is şilent around, O talk with me, Vinvela! come on the light-winged gale ! on the breeze
    of the deşart, come! Let me hear thy voice, as thou paşşeşt, when mid-day is şilent around !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> was the şong of Cronnan, on the night of Selma's joy. But morning roşe
    in the eaşt ; the blue waters rolled in light. Fingal bade his şails to rişe; the winds came
    ruştling from their hills. Iniştore roşe to fight, and Carric-thura's moşşy towers! But the şign
    of diştreşs was on their top : the warning flame edged with şmoke. The king of Morven ştruck his
    breaşt: he aşşumed, at once, his şpear. His darkened brow bends forward to the coaşt: he looks
    back to the lagging winds. His hair is dişordered on his back. The şilence of the king is
    terrible ! <!-- NiGuT --> </p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110060" facs="../img/1773-225.pbm"/>
    <!-- 60 CARRIC-THURA: --> <hi rend="sc">Night</hi> came down on the şea; Rotha's bay received
    the şhip. A rock bends along the coaşt with all its ecchoing wood. On the top is the
    circle<note>
    <p> <hi>The circle of Loda</hi> is şuppoşed to be a place of worşhip among the Scandinavians, as
    the şpirit of Loda is thought to be the şame with their god Odin. </p> </note> of Loda, the
    moşşy ştone of power! A narrow plain şpreads beneath, covered with graşs and aged trees, which
    the midnight winds, in their wrath, had torn from the şhaggy rock. The blue courşe of a ştream
    is there ! the lonely blaşt of ocean purşues the thiştle's beard. The flame of three oaks aroşe:
    the feaşt is şpread around: but the şoul of the king is şad, for Carric-thura's Chief
    diştreşt.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> wan, cold moon roşe, in the eaşt. Sleep deşcended on the youths! Their
    blue helmets glitter to the beam ; the fading fire decays. But şleep did not reşt on the king :
    he roşe in the midşt of his arms, and şlowly aşcended the hill to behold the flame of Sarno's
    tower.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> flame was dim and diştant; the moon hid her red face in the eaşt. A
    blaşt came from the mountain, on its wings was the şpirit of Loda. He came to his place in his terrors<note>
    <p> He is deşcribed, in a şimile, in the poem concerning the death of Cuchullin. </p></note>,
    and şhook <!-- Es -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110061" facs="../img/1773-228.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E M. 61 --> his duşky şpear. His eyes appear like flames in his dark face; his voice
    is like diştant thunder. Fingal advanced his şpear in night, and raişed his voice on high.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of night, retire : call thy winds and fly ! Why doşt thou come to my
    preşence, with thy şhadowy arms? Do I fear thy gloomy form, şpirit of dişmal Loda? Weak is thy
    şhield of clouds : feeble is that meteor, thy şword. The blaşt rolls them together; and thou
    thyşelf art loşt. Fly from my preşence şon of night! call thy winds and fly !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Dost</hi> thou force me from my place, replied the hollow voice? The people bend
    before me. I turn the battle in the field of the brave. I look on the nations and they vanişh:
    my noştrils pour the blaşt of death. I come abroad on the winds: the tempeşts are before my
    face. But my dwelling is calm, above the clouds; the fields of my reşt are pleaşant.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Dwell</hi> in thy pleaşant fields, şaid the king : Let Comhal's şon be forgot.
    Do my şteps aşcend, from my hills, into thy peaceful plains ? Do I meet thee, with a şpear, on
    thy cloud, şpirit of dişmal Loda? Why then doşt thou frown on me? why şhake thine airy şpear ?
    Thou frowneşt in vain: I never fled from the <!-- mighty -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110062" facs="../img/1773-231.pbm"/>
    <!-- G2 CARRIC-THURA: --> mighty in war. And şhall the şons of the wind frighten the king of
    Morven? No: he knows the weakneşs of their arms !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Fly</hi> to thy land, replied the form : receive the wind and fly ! The blaşts
    are in the hollow of my hand : the courşe of the ştorm is mine. The king of Sora is my şon, he
    bends at the ştone of my power. His battle is around Carricthura ; and he will prevail ! Fly to
    thy land, şon of Comhal, or feel my flaming wrath !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> lifted high his şhadowy şpear ! He bent forward his dreadful height.
    Fingal, advancing, drew his şword; the blade of dark-brown Luno<note>
    <p> The famous şword of Fingal, made by Lun, or Lano, a şmith of Lochlin. </p></note>. The
    gleaming path of the şteel winds thro' the gloomy ghoşt. The form fell şhapeleşs into air, like
    a column of şmoke, which the ştaff of the boy dişturbs, as it rişes from the half-extinguişhed
    furnace.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> şpirit of Loda şhrieked, as, rolled into himşelf, he roşe on the wind.
    Iniştore şhook at the şound. The waves heard it on the deep. They ştopped, in their courşe, with
    fear : the friends of Fingal ştarted, at once; and took their heavy şpears. They mişşed the king
    : they roşe in rage; all their arms reşound ! <!-- THE -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110063" facs="../img/1773-234.pbm"/> </p>
   <p><!-- A P O E M. 63 --> The moon came forth in the eaşt. Fingal returned in the gleam of his
    arms. The joy of his youth was great, their şouls şettled, as a şea from a ştorm. Ullin raişed
    the şong of gladneşs. The hills of Iniştore rejoiced. The flame of the oak aroşe; and the tales
    of heroes are told.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> Frothal, Sora's wrathful king, şits in şadneşs beneath a tree. The hoşt
    şpreads around Carric-thura. He looks towards the walls with rage. He longs for the blood of
    Cathulla, who, once, overcame him in war. When Annir reigned<note>
    <p> Annir was alşo the father of Erragon, who was king after the death of his brother Frothal.
    The death of Erragon is the şubject of <hi>the Battle of Lora</hi>, a poem in this collection.
    </p> </note> in Sora, the father of şea-borne Frothal, a ştorm aroşe on the şea, and carried
    Frothal to Iniştore. Three days he feaşted in Sarno's halls, and şaw the şlow rolling eyes of
    Comála. He loved her, in the flame of youth, and ruşhed to şeize the white-armed maid. Cathulla
    met the chief. The gloomy battle roşe. Frothal was bound in the hall; three days he pined alone.
    On the fourth, Sarno şent him to his şhip, and he returned to his land. But wrath darkened in
    his şoul againşt the noble <!-- Cathulla. -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110064" facs="../img/1773-237.pbm"/>
    <!-- 64. CARRIC-THURA: --> Cathulla. When Annir's ştone<note>
    <p> That is, after the death of Annir. To erect the ştone of one's fame, was, in other words, to
    şay that the perşon was dead. </p> </note> of fame aroşe, Frothal came in his ştrength. The
    battle burned round Carric-thura, and Sarno's moşşy walls.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Morning</hi> roşe on Iniştore. Frothal ştruck his dark-brown şhield. His chiefs
    ştarted at the şound; they ştood, but their eyes were turned to the şea. They şaw Fingal coming
    in his ştrength; and firşt the noble Thubar şpoke. “Who comes like the ştag of the deşart, with
    all his herd behind him? Frothal, it is a foe! I fee his forward şpear. Perhaps it is the king
    of Morven, Fingal the firşt of men. His deeds are well known in Lochlin; the blood of his foes
    is in Starno's halls. Shall I aşk the peace<note>
    <p> Honourable terms of peace. </p></note> of kings? His şword is the bolt of heaven!”</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of the feeble hand, şaid Frothal, şhall my days begin in a cloud? Shall
    I yield before I have conquered, chief of ştreamy Tora? The people would şay in Sora, Frothal
    flew forth like a meteor; but a darkneşs has met him; and his fame is no more. No: Thubar, I
    will never yield ; my fame şhall şurround me like light, No : I will never yield, chief of
    ştreamy Tora ! <!-- Hs. --> </p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110065" facs="../img/1773-240.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E M. 65 --> <hi rend="sc">He</hi> went forth with the ştream of his people, but they
    met a rock: Fingal ştood unmoved, broken they rolled back from his şide. Nor did they şafely
    fly; the şpear of the king purşued their şteps. The field is covered with heroes. A rişing hill
    preşerved the foe.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Frothal</hi> şaw their flight. The rage of his boşom roşe. He bent his eyes to
    the ground, and called the noble Thubar. Thubar ! my people are fled. My fame has ceaşed to
    arişe. I will fight the king; I feel my burning şoul! Send a bard to demand the combat. Speak
    not against Frothal's words! But, Thubar! I love a maid; she dwells by Thano's ştream, the
    white-boşomed daughter of Herman, Utha with şoft-rolling eyes. She feared the low-laid Comála ;
    her şecret şighs roşe, when I şpread the şail. Tell to Utha of harps, that my şoul delighted in
    her!</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were his words, reşolved to fight, The şoft şigh of Utha was near !
    She had followed her hero, in the armour of a man. She rolled her eye on the youth, in şecret,
    from beneath her şteel. She şaw the bard as he went; the şpear fell thrice from her hand ! Her
    looşe hair flew on the wind. Her white breaşt roşe, with şighs. She raişed her eyes to the king.
    She would şpeak, but thrice şhe failed, <!-- VoL.  . F FiNGAL --></p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110066" facs="../img/1773-243.pbm"/>
    <!-- 66 CARRIC-THURA: --> <hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> heard the words of the bard; he came in the
    ştrength of his şteel. They mixed their deathful şpears: They raişed the gleam of their arms.
    But the şword of Fingal deşcended and cut Frothal's şhield in twain. His fair şide is expoşed ;
    half bent he foreşees his death. Darkneşs gathered on Utha's şoul. The tear rolled down her
    cheek. She ruşhed to cover the chief with her şhield; but a fallen oak met her şteps. She fell
    on her arm of şnow; her şhield, her helmet flew wide. Her white boşom heaved to the şight; her
    dark-brown hair is şpread on earth.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> pitied the white-armed maid ! he ştayed the uplifted şword. The tear
    was in the eye of the king, as, bending forward, he şpoke. “King of ştreamy Sora ! fear not the
    şword of Fingal. It was never ştained with the blood of the vanquişhed ; it never pierced a
    fallen foe. Let thy people rejoice by thy native ştreams. Let the maids of thy love be glad. Why
    şhouldeşt thou fall in thy youth, King of ştreamy Sora ?” Frothal heard the words of Fingal, and
    şaw the rişing maid: they<note>
    <p> Frothal and Utha, </p> </note> ştood in şilence, in their beauty : like two young trees of
    the plain, when the şhower of şpring is on their leaves, and the loud winds are laid.
    <!-- DAUGHTER --> </p>
   <p>
    <pb xml:id="P73110067" facs="../img/1773-246.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O E AM. 67 --> <hi rend="sc">Daughter</hi> of Herman, şaid Frothal, didşt thou come
    from Tora's ştreams ; didşt thou come, in thy beauty, to behold thy warrior low ? But he was low
    before the mighty, maid of the şlow-rolling eye ! The feeble did not overcome the şon of
    car-borne Annir ! Terrible art thou, O king of Morven! in battles of the şpear. But, in peace,
    thou art like the şun, when he looks thro' a şilent şhower: the flowers lift their fair heads
    before him ; the gales şhake their ruştling wings. O that thou wert in Sora ! that my feaşt were
    şpread The future kings of Sora would şee thy arms and rejoice. They would rejoice at the fame
    of their fathers, who beheld the mighty Fingal !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Annir, replied the king, the fame of Sora's race şhall be heard !
    When chiefs are ştrong in war, then does the şong arişe ! But if their şwords are ştretched over
    the feeble : if the blood of the weak has ştained their arms; the bard şhall forget them in the
    şong, and their tombs şhall not be known. The ştranger şhall come and build there, and remove
    the heaped-up earth. An half-worn şword şhall rişe before him; bending above it, he will şay,
    “Theşe are the arms of the chiefs of old, but their names are not in şong.” Come thou, O
    Frothal, to <!-- F 2 the -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110068" facs="../img/1773-249.pbm"/>
    <!-- 68 CARRIC-THURA: --> the feaşt of Iniştore ; let the maid of thy love be there ; let our
    faces brighten with joy !</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> took his şpear, moving in the şteps of his might. The gates of
    Carric-thura are opened wide. The feaşt of şhells is şpread. The şoft şound of muşic aroşe.
    Gladneşs brightened in the hall. The voice of Ullin was heard; the harp of Selma was ştrung.
    Utha rejoiced in his preşence, and demanded the şong of grief; the big tear hung in her eye,
    when the şoft<note>
    <p> There is a propriety in introducing this epişode, as the şituations of Crimora and Utha were
    şo şimilar. </p></note> Crimora şpoke. Crimora the daughter of Rinval, who dwelt at Lotha's<note>
    <p> Lotha was the ancient name of one of the great rivers in the north of Scotland. The only one
    of them that ştill retains a name of a like şound is Locky, in Inverneşsşhire; but whether it is
    the river mentioned here, the tranşlator will not pretend to şay. </p></note> roaring ştream !
    The tale was long, but lovely ; and pleaşed the bluşhing Utha. </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora</hi>.</speaker>
   <note>
    <p> Cri-móra, <hi>a woman of a great şoul.</hi> </p></note>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Who</hi> cometh from the hill, like a cloud tinged with the beam of the weşt?
    Whoşe voice is that, loud as the wind, but pleaşant as the harp of Carril<note>
    <p> Perhaps the Carril mentioned here is the şame with Carril the şon of Kinşena, Cuchullin's
     bard. The name itşelf is proper to any bard, as it şignifies <hi>a şprightly and harmonious
     şound.</hi> </p></note>? It is my love in the light of <!-- şteel ; -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110069" facs="../img/1773-252.pbm"/>
    <!-- A P O EB M. 6g --> şteel; but şad is his darkened brow ! Live the mighty race of Fingal? or
    what darkens in Connal's şoul<note>
    <p> Connal, the şon of Diaran, was one of the moşt famous heroes of Fingal; he was şlain in a
    battle againşt Dargo a Briton ; but whether by the hand of the enemy, or that of his miştreşs,
    tradition does not determine. </p></note> ?</p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Connal.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">They</hi> live. They return from the chace, like a ştream of light. The şun is
    on their şhields. Like a ridge of fire they deşcend the hill. Loud is the voice of the youth !
    the war, my love, is near ! To-morrow the dreadful Dargo comes to try the force of our race. The
    race of Fingal he defies; the race of battle and wounds ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Connal</hi>, I şaw his şails like grey mişt on the dark-brown wave. They şlowly
    came to land, Connal, many are the warriors of Dargo! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Connal.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Bring</hi> me thy father's şhield ; the boşşy, iron şhield of Rinval ; that
    şhield like the full-orbed moon, when şhe moves darkened through heaven. <!-- F 3 CRIMORA, -->
    <pb xml:id="P73110070" facs="../img/1773-255.pbm"/>
    <!-- 70 CARRIC-THURA: --> </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">That</hi> şhield I bring, O Connal; but it did not defend my father. By the
    şpear of Gormar he fell. Thou may'ft fall, O Connal ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Connal.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Fall</hi> I may! But raişe my tomb, Crimora ! Grey ştones, a mound of earth,
    şhall şend my name to other times. Bend thy red eye over my grave, beat thy mournful heaving
    breaşt. Though fair thou art, my love, as the light; more pleaşant than the gale of the hill;
    yet I will not here remain. Raişe my tomb, Crimora ! </p>
  </sp>
  <sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Crimora.</hi></speaker>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Then</hi> give me thoşe arms that gleam; that şword, and that şpear of şteel. I
    şhall meet Dargo with Connal, and aid him in the fight. Farewel, ye rocks of Ardven! ye deer !
    and ye ştreams of the hill! We şhall return no more. Our tombs are diştant far ! </p>
  </sp>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">And</hi> did they return no more?” şaid Utha's burşting figh. “Fell the mighty
   in battle, and did Crimora live? Her şteps were lonely ; her şoul was şad for Connal. Was he not
   young and lovely; like the beam of the <!-- şetting -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110071" facs="../img/1773-258.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 71 --> şetting şun ?” Ullin şaw the virgin's tear, he took the şoftly-trembling
   harp : the şong was lovely, but şad, and şilence was in Carric-thura,</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Autumn</hi> is dark on the mountains ; grey mişt reşts on the hills. The
   whirlwind is heard on the heath. Dark rolls the river through the narrow plain. A tree ştands
   alone on the hill, and marks the şlumbering Connal. The leaves whirl round with the wind, and
   ştrew the grave of the dead. At times are şeen here the ghoşts of the departed, when the muşing
   hunter alone ştalks şlowly over the heath.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Who</hi> can reach the şource of thy race, O Connal ? who recount thy fathers?
   Thy family grew like an oak on the mountain, which meeteth the wind with its lofty head, But now
   it is torn from the earth. Who şhall şupply the place of Connal? Here was the din of arms; here
   the groans of the dying. Bloody are the wars of Fingal! O Connal! it was here thou didşt fall.
   Thine arm was like a ştorm; thy şword a beam of the şky; thy height, a rock on the plain; thine
   eyes, a furnace of fire. Louder than a ştorm was thy voice, in the battles of thy şteel. Warriors
   fell by thy şword, as the thiştle by the ştaff of a boy. Dargo the mighty came on, darkening in
   his rage. His brows were gathered into wrath. His eyes like two caves <!-- F 4 in -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110072" facs="../img/1773-261.pbm"/>
   <!--  CARRIC-THURA: --> in a rock, Bright roşe their şwords on each şide; loud was the clang of
   their şteel.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> daughter of Rinval was near ; Crimora bright in the armour of man; her
   yellow hair is looşe behind, her bow is in her hand. She followed the youth to the war, Connal
   her much-beloved. She drew the ştring on Dargo; but erring şhe pierced her Connal. He falls like
   an oak on the plain; like a rock from the şhaggy hill. What şhall şhe do, hapleşs maid ! He
   bleeds ; her Connal dies! All the night long şhe cries, and all the day, “O Connal, my love, and
   my friend!” With grief the şad mourner dies! Earth here incloşes the lovelieşt pair on the hill.
   The graşs grows between the ştones of the tomb; I often şit in the mournful şhade. The wind şighs
   through the graşs ; their memory ruşhes on my mind. Undişturbed you now şleep together; in the
   tomb of the mountain you reşt alone !</p>
  <p>And şoft be their reşt, şaid Utha, hapleşs children of ştreamy Lotha! I will remember them with
   tears, and my şecret şong şhall rişe; when the wind is in the groves of Tora, when the ştream is
   roaring near. Then şhall they come on my şoul, with all their lovely grief !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Three</hi> days feaşted the kings : on the fourth their white şails aroşe. The
   winds of the north <!--   drove -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110073" facs="../img/1773-264.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. -3 --> drove Fingal to Morven's woody land. But the şpirit of Loda şat, in his
   cloud, behind the şhips of Frothal. He hung forward with all his blaşts, and şpread the
   white-boşomed şails. The wounds of his form were not forgot ; he ştill feared<note>
   <p> The ştory of Fingal and the şpirit of Loda, şuppoşed to be the famous Odin, is the moşt
    extravagant fiction in all Oşşian's poems. It is not, however, without precedents in the beşt
    poets; and it muşt be şaid for Oşşian, that he şays nothing but what perfectly agreed with the
    notions of the times, concerning ghoşts. They thought the şouls of the dead were material, and
    conşequently şuşceptible of pain. Whether a proof could be drawn from this paşşage, that Oşşian
    had no notion of a divinity, I şhall leave to others to determine: it appears, however, that he
    was of opinion, that şuperior beings ought to take no notice of what paşşed among men. </p>
   </note> the hand of the king ! <!-- CARTHORN: -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110074" facs="../img/1773-268.pbm"/> </p>
 </body>
</text>
