<div type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73110243" facs="../img/1773-762.pbm"/>
 <head> FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. BOOK II.</head>
 <!-- R 2 -->

 <pb xml:id="P73110244" facs="../img/1773-763.pbm"/>
 <div type="argument">
  <head>ARGUMENT to <hi rend="sc">Book</hi> II.</head>
  <p> The ghoſt of Crugal, one of the Iriſh heroes who was killed in battle, appearing to Connal,
   foretels the defeat of Cuthullin in the next battle; and earneſtly adviſes him to make peace with
   Swaran. Connal communicates the viſion; but Cuthullin is inflexible; from a principle of honour
   he would not be the firſt to ſue for peace, and he reſolved to continue the war. Morning comes;
   Swaran propoſes diſhonourable terms to Cuthullin, which are rejected. The battle begins, and is
   obſtinately fought for ſome time, until, upon the flight of Grumal, the whole Iriſh army gave
   way. Cuthullin and Connal cover their retreat: Carril leads them to a neighbouring hill, whither
   they are ſoon followed by Cuthullin himſelf, who deſcries the fleet of Fingal making towards the
   coaſt; but, night coming on, he loſt ſight of it again. Cuthullin, dejected after his defeat,
   attributes his ill ſucceſs to the death of Ferda his friend, whom he had killed ſome time before.
   Carril, to ſhew that ill ſucceſs did not always attend thoſe who innocently killed their friends,
   introduces the epiſode of Comal and Galvina. </p>
 </div>
 <div type="poem">
  <pb xml:id="P73110245" facs="../img/1773-766.pbm"/>
  <!-- [ 245 ] -->
  <head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. In SIX BOOKS. BOOK II.</head>
  <p> <hi rend="sc">Connal</hi><note>
   <p> The ſcene here deſcribed will appear natural to thoſe who have been in the highlands of
    Scotland, The poet removes him to a diſtance from the army, to add more horror to the
    deſcription of Crugal's ghoſt by the lonelineſs of the place. </p>
   </note> lay by the ſound of the mountain ſtream, beneath the aged tree. A ſtone, with its moſs,
   ſupported his head. Shrill thro' the heath of Lena, he heard the voice of night. At diſtance from
   the heroes he lay ; the ſon of the ſword feared no foe! The hero beheld, in his reſt, a dark-red
   ſtream of fire ruſhing down from the hill. Crugal ſat upon the beam, a chief who fell in fight.
   He fell by the hand of Swaran, ſtriving in the battle of heroes. His face is like the beam of the
   ſetting <!-- R 3 moon. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110246" facs="../img/1773-769.pbm"/>
   <!-- 246 F I N G A L, Book II. --> moon. His robes are of the clouds of the hill. His eyes are
   two decaying flames ! Dark is the wound of his breaſt! “Crugal,” ſaid the mighty Connal, ſon of
   Dedgal famed on the hill of hinds ! “Why ſo pale and ſad, thou breaker of the ſhields? Thou haſt
   never been pale for fear! What diſturbs the departed Crugal?” Dim, and in tears, he ſtood and
   ſtretched his pale hand over the hero. Faintly he raiſed his feeble voice, like the gale of the
   reedy Lego !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">My</hi> ſpirit, Connal, is on my hills: my corſe on the ſands of Erin. Thou
   ſhalt never talk with Crugal, nor find his lone ſteps in the heath. I am light as the blaſt of
   Cromla. I move like the ſhadow of miſt ! Connal, ſon of Colgar, I ſee a cloud of death: it hovers
   dark over the plains of Lena. The ſons of green Erin muſt fall. Remove from the field of ghoſts.”
   Like the darkened moon he retired, in the midſt of the whiſtling blaſt. “Stay,” ſaid the mighty
   Connal, “ſtay my dark-red friend. Lay by that beam of heaven, ſon of the windy Cromla! What cave
   is thy lonely houſe ? What green-headed hill the place of thy repoſe ? Shall we not hear thee in
   the ſtorm ? In the noiſe of the mountain-ſtream? When the feeble ſons of the wind come forth, and
   ſcarcely ſeen, paſs over the deſart ?” <!-- THE --></p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73110247" facs="../img/1773-772.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 247 --> <hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſoft-voiced Connal rofe, in the midſt
   of his ſounding arms. He ſtruck his ſhield above Cuthullin. The ſon of battle waked. “Why,” ſaid
   the ruler of the car, “comes Connal through my night? My ſpear might turn againſt the ſound; and
   Cuthullin mourn the death of his friend. Speak, Connal; ſon of Colgar, ſpeak, thy counſel is the
   ſun of heaven!” “Son of Semo!” replied the chief, “the ghoſt of Crugal came from his cave. The
   ſtars dim-twinkled through his form. His voice was like the ſound of a diſtant ſtream. He is a
   meſſenger of death ! He ſpeaks of the dark and narrow houſe ! Sue for peace, O chief of Erin ! or
   fly over the heath of Lena.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">He</hi> ſpoke to Connal,” replied the hero, “though ſtars dim-twinkled through
   his form ! Son of Colgar, it was the wind that murmured acroſs thy ear. Or if it was the form<note>
   <p> The poet teaches us the opinions that prevailed in his time concerning the fate of ſeparate
    ſouls. From Connal's expreſſion, “That the ſtars dim-twinkled through the form of Crugal,” and
    Cuthullin's reply, we may gather that they both thought the ſoul was material, ſomething like
    the <hi>εἰδωλον</hi> of the ancient Greeks. </p>
   </note> of Crugal, why didſt thou not force him to my ſight ? Haſt thou enquired where is his
   cave? The houſe of that ſon of wind ? My ſword might find that voice, and force his knowlege from
   Crugal.<!--R 4 But-->
   <pb xml:id="P73110248" facs="../img/1773-775.pbm"/>
   <!-- 248 FINGAL, Book II. --> But ſmall is his knowlege, Connal; he was here to-day. He could not
   have gone beyond our hills! who could tell him there of our fall?” “Ghoſts fly on clouds and ride
   on winds,” ſaid Connal's voice of wiſdom. “They reſt together in their caves, and talk of mortal
   men.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Then</hi> let them talk of mortal men; of every man but Erin's chief. Let me be
   forgot in their cave, I will not fly from Swaran! If fall I muſt, my tomb ſhall riſe, amid the
   fame of future times. The hunter ſhall ſhed a tear on my ſtone; ſorrow ſhall dwell round the
   high-boſomed Bragéla. I fear not death, to fly I fear ! Fingal has ſeen me victorious ! Thou dim
   phantom of the hill, ſhew thyſelf to me ! come on thy beam of heaven, ſhew me my death in thine
   hand; yet I will not fly, thou feeble ſon of the wind! Go, ſon of Colgar, ſtrike the ſhield. It
   hangs between the ſpears. Let my warriors riſe to the ſound, in the midſt of the battles of Erin.
   Though Fingal delays his coming with the race of his ſtormy iſles; we ſhall fight, O Colgar's
   ſon, and die in the battle of heroes !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſound ſpreads wide. The heroes riſe, like the breaking of a blue-rolling
   wave. They ſtood on the heath, like oaks with all their <!-- 6 branches -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110249" facs="../img/1773-778.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An  EPIC POEM. 249 --> branches round them; when they eccho to the ſtream of froſt,
   and their withered leaves are ruſtling to the wind! High Cromla's head of clouds is grey. Morning
   trembles on the half-enlightened ocean. The blue miſt ſwims ſlowly by, and hides the ſons of
   Inis-fail !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Rise</hi> ye,” ſaid the king of the dark-brown ſhields, “ye that came from
   Lochlin's waves. The ſons of Erin have fled from our arms; purſue them over the plains of Lena!
   Morla, go to Cormac's hall. Bid them yield to Swaran before his people ſink to the tomb ; and
   ſilence ſpread over his iſle.” They roſe ruſtling like a flock of ſea-fowl, when the waves expel
   them from the ſhore. Their ſound was like a thouſand ſtreams that meet in Cona's vale, when after
   a ſtormy night, they turn their dark eddies, beneath the pale light of the morn.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> the dark ſhades of autumn fly over the hills of graſs: ſo gloomy, dark,
   ſucceſſive came the chiefs of Lochlin's ecchoing woods. Tall as the ſtag of Morven moved ſtately
   before them, the king. His ſhining ſhield is on his ſide, like a flame on the heath at night.
   When the world is ſilent and dark, and the traveller ſees ſome ghoſt ſporting in the beam! Dimly
   gleam the hills around, and ſhew indiſtinctly their oaks! A blaſt from the troubled ocean removed
   the <!-- şettled -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110250" facs="../img/1773-781.pbm"/>
   <!-- 250 F IN G A L, Book II. --> ſettled miſt. The ſons of Erin appear, like a ridge of rocks on
   the coaſt; when mariners, on ſhores unknown, are trembling at veering winds !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Go</hi>, Morla, go,” ſaid the king of Lochlin, “offer peace to theſe! Offer the
   terms we give to kings, when nations bow down to our ſwords. When the valiant are dead in war;
   when virgins weep on the field !” Tall Morla came, the ſon of Swarth, and ſtately ſtrode the
   youth along ! He ſpoke to Erin's blue-eyed chief, among the leſſer heroes. “Take Swaran's peace,”
   the warrior ſpoke, “the peace he gives to kings, when nations bow to his ſword. Leave Erin's
   ſtreamy plains to us, and give thy ſpouſe and dog. Thy ſpouſe high-boſom'd, heaving fair ! Thy
   dog that overtakes the wind ! Give theſe to prove the weakneſs of thine arm ; live then beneath
   our power ! ”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Tell</hi> Swaran, tell that heart of pride, Cuthullin never yields. I give him
   the dark rolling ſea; I give his people graves in Erin. But never ſhall a ſtranger have the
   pleaſing ſun-beam of my love. No deer ſhall fly on Lochlin's hills, before ſwift-footed Luäth.”
   “Vain ruler of the car,” ſaid Morla,“wilt thou then fight the king ? The king whoſe ſhips of many
   groves could carry off thine ile ? So little is thy green-hilled Erin to him who rules
   <!-- the -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110251" facs="../img/1773-784.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 251 --> the ſtormy waves!” “In words I yield to many, Morla. My ſword
   ſhall yield to none. Erin ſhall own the ſway of Cormac, while Connal and Cuthullin live! O
   Connal, firſt of mighty men, thou hear'ft the words of Morla. Shall thy thoughts then be of
   peace, thou breaker of the ſhields? Spirit of fallen Crugal ! why didſt thou threaten us with
   death? The narrow houſe ſhall receive me, in the midſt of the light of renown. Exalt, ye ſons of
   Erin, exalt the ſpear and bend the bow : ruſh on the foe in darkneſs, as the ſpirits of ſtormy
   nights !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Then</hi> diſmal, roaring, fierce, and deep the gloom of battle poured along; as
   miſt that is rolled on a valley, when ſtorms invade the ſilent ſun-ſhine of heaven! Cuthullin
   moves before in arms, like an angry ghoſt before a cloud ; when meteors incloſe him with fire;
   when the dark winds are in his hand. Carril, far on the heath, bids the horn of battle ſound. He
   raiſes the voice of ſong, and pours his ſoul into the minds of the brave.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Where</hi>,” ſaid the mouth of the ſong, “where is the fallen Crugal ? He lies
   forgot on earth; the hall of ſhells<note>
   <p> The ancient Scots, as well as the preſent Highlanders, drank in ſhells: ; hence it is that we
    ſo often meet, in the old poetry, with <hi>the chief of ſhells</hi>, and <hi>the halls of
    ſhells</hi>. </p>
   </note> is ſilent. Sad is the <!-- şpouşe -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110252" facs="../img/1773-787.pbm"/>
   <!-- 252 F IN G A L, Book II. --> ſpouſe of Crugal! She is a ſtranger<note>
   <p> Crugal had married Degrena but a little time before the battle, conſequently ſhe may with
    propriety be called a ſtranger in the hall of her grief. </p>
   </note> in the hall of her grief. But who is ſhe, that, like a ſunbeam, flies before the ranks of
   the foe? It is Degrena<note>
   <p> Deo-gréna ſignifies <hi>a ſun bean</hi>. </p>
   </note>, lovely fair, the ſpouſe of fallen Crugal. Her hair is on the wind behind. Her eye is red
   ; her voice is ſhrill, Pale, empty is thy Crugal now ! His form is in the cave of the hill. He
   comes to the ear of reſt; he raiſes his feeble voice ; like the humming of the mountain-bee ;
   like the collected flies of the eve ! But Degrena falls like a cloud of the morn; the ſword of
   Lochlin is in her ſide. Cairbar, ſhe is fallen, the riſing thought of thy youth. She is fallen, O
   Cairbar, the thought of thy youthful hours !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Fierce</hi> Cairbar heard the mournful ſound. He ruſhed along like ocean's whale.
   He ſaw the death of his daughter: He roared in the midſt of thouſands. His ſpear met a ſon of
   Lochlin ; battle ſpreads from wing to wing ! As a hundred winds in Lochlin's groves ; as fire in
   the pines of a hundred hills; ſo loud, ſo ruinous, ſo vaſt the ranks of men are hewn down.
   Cuthullin cut off heroes like thiſtle ; Swaran waſted Erin. Curach fell by his hand, Cairbar
   <!-- of -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110253" facs="../img/1773-790.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 253 --> of the boſſy ſhield ! Morglan lies in laſting reſt! Ca-olt
   trembles as he dies! His white breaſt is ſtained with blood ; his yellow hair ſtretched in the
   duſt of his native land ! He often had ſpread the feaſt where he fell. He often there had raiſed
   the voice of the harp: when his dogs leapt around for joy ; and the youths of the chace prepared
   the bow !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Still</hi> Swaran advanced, as a ſtream, that burſts from the deſart. The little
   hills are rolled in its courſe ; the rocks are half-ſunk by its ſide! But Cuthullin ſtood before
   him, like a hill, that catches the clouds of heaven. The winds contend on its head of pines; the
   hail rattles on its rocks. But, firm in its ſtrength, it ſtands, and ſhades the ſilent vale of
   Cona ! So Cuthullin ſhaded the ſons of Erin, and ſtood in the midſt of thouſands. Blood riſes
   like the fount of a rock, from panting heroes around. But Erin falls on either wing, like ſnow in
   the day of the ſun.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">O sons</hi> of Erin,” ſaid Grumal, “Lochlin conquers on the field. Why ſtrive we
   as reeds againſt the wind? Fly to the hill of dark-brown hinds.” He fled like the flag of Morven;
   his ſpear is a trembling beam of light behind him. Few fled with Grumal, chief of the little ſoul
   ; they fell in the battle of heroes, on Lena's <!-- ing -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110254" facs="../img/1773-793.pbm"/>
   <!-- 254 FIN G A L, Book II. --> ecchoing heath. High on his car, of many gems, the chief of Erin
   ſtood. He ſlew a mighty ſon of Lochlin, and ſpoke, in haſte, to Connal. “O Connal, firſt of
   mortal men, thou haſt taught this arm of death ! Though Erin's ſons have fled, ſhall we not fight
   the foe? Carril, ſon of other times, carry my friends to that buſhy hill. Here, Connal, let us
   ſtand, like rocks, and ſave our flying friends.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Connal</hi> mounts the car of gems. They ſtretch their ſhields, like the darkened
   moon, the daughter of the ſtarry ſkies, when ſhe moves, a dun circle, thro' heaven; and dreadful
   change is expected by men. Sithfadda panted up the hill, and Sronnal haughty ſteed. Like waves
   behind a whale behind them ruſhed the foe. Now on the riſing ſide of Cromla ſtood Erin's few ſad
   ſons; . like a grove through which the flame had ruſhed, hurried on by the winds of the ſtormy
   night; diſtant, withered, dark they ſtand, with not a leaf to ſhake in the gale.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Cuthullin</hi> ſtood beſide an oak. He rolled his red eye in ſilence, and heard
   the wind in his buſhy hair ; the ſcout of ocean came, Moran the ſon of Fithil. “The ſhips,” he
   cried,“the ſhips of the lonely iſles. Fingal comes the firſt of men, the breaker of the ſhields!
   The waves foam before his black prows ! His maſts with <!-- 4 şails -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110255" facs="../img/1773-796.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 255 --> ſails are like groves in clouds !” “Blow,” ſaid Cuthullin,
   “blow ye winds that ruſh along my iſle of miſt. Come to the death of thouſands, O king of
   reſounding Selma ! Thy ſails, my friend, are to me the clouds of the morning; thy ſhips the light
   of heaven ; and thou thyſelf a pillar of fire that beams on the world by night. O Connal, firſt
   of men, how pleaſing, in grief, are our friends! But the night is gathering around ! Where now
   are the ſhips of Fingal ? Here let us paſs the hours of darkneſs; here wiſh for the moon of
   heaven.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> winds come down on the woods. The torrents ruſh from the rocks. Rain
   gathers round the head of Cromla, The red ſtars tremble between the flying clouds. Sad, by the
   ſide of a ſtream whoſe ſound is ecchoed by a tree, ſad by the ſide of a ſtream the chief of Erin
   ſits. Connal ſon of Colgar is there, and Carril of other times. “Unhappy is the hand of
   Cuthullin,” ſaid the fon of Semo, “unhappy is the hand of Cuthullin, ſince he ſlew his friend !
   Ferda, ſon of Damman, I loved thee as myſelf !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">How</hi>, Cuthullin, ſon of Semo ! how fell the breaker of the ſhields? Well I
   remember,” ſaid Connal, “the ſon of the noble Damman. Tall and fair he was like the rain-bow of
   <!-- ven. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110256" facs="../img/1773-799.pbm"/>
   <!-- 256 FINGAL, Boox lI. --> heaven.” Ferda from Albion came, the chief of a hundred hills. In Muri's<note>
   <p> A place in Ulſter. </p>
   </note> hall he learned the ſword, and won the friendſhip of Cuthullin. We moved to the chace
   together : one was our bed in the heath !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Deugala</hi> was the ſpouſe of Cairbar, chief of the plains of Ullin. She was
   covered with the light of beauty, but her heart was the houſe of pride. She loved that ſun-beam
   of youth, the ſon of noble Damman. Cairbar, ſaid the whitearmed Deugala, give me half of the
   herd. No more I will remain in your halls. Divide the herd, dark Cairbar! “Let Cuthullin,” ſaid
   Cairbar, “divide my herd on the hill. His breaſt is the ſeat of juſtice, Depart, thou light of
   beauty !” I went and divided the herd. One ſnow-white bull remained. I gave that bull to Cairbar.
   The wrath of Deugala roſe !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Damman,” begun the fair, “Cuthullin hath pained my ſoul. I muſt hear
   of his death, or Lubar's ſtream ſhall roll over me. My pale ghoſt ſhall wander near thee, and
   mourn the wound of my pride. Pour out the blood of Cuthullin or pierce this heaving breaſt.”
   “Deugala,” ſaid the fair-haired youth, “how ſhall I ſlay the ſon of Semo ? He is the friend of my
   <!-- şecret -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110257" facs="../img/1773-802.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM, 257 --> ſecret thoughts. Shall I then lift the ſword ?” She wept
   three days before the chief, on the fourth he ſaid he would fight. “I will fight my friend,
   Deugala ! but may I fall by his ſword ! Could I wander on the hill alone ? Could I behold the
   grave of Cuthullin ?” We fought on the plain of Muri. Our ſwords avoid a wound. They ſlide on the
   helmets of ſteel ; or ſound on the ſlippery ſhields. Deugala was near with a ſmile, and ſaid to
   the ſon of Damman : “Thine arm is feeble, ſun-beam of youth ! Thy years are not ſtrong for ſteel.
   Yield to the fon of Semo. He is a rock on Malmor.” </p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">The</hi> tear is in the eye of youth. He faultering ſaid to me: “Cuthullin,
   raiſe thy boſſy ſhield. Defend thee from the hand of thy friend. My ſoul is laden with grief: for
   I muſt ſlay the chief of men !” I ſighed as the wind in the cleft of a rock. I lifted high the
   edge of my ſteel. The ſun-beam of battle fell : the firſt of Cuthullin's friends ! Unhappy is the
   hand of Cuthullin ſince the hero fell !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Mournful</hi> is thy tale, ſon of the car,” ſaid Carril of other times. “It
   ſends my ſoul back to the ages of old, to the days of other years. Often have I heard of Comal,
   who ſlew the friend he loved ; yet victory attended his ſteel: the battle was conſumed in his
   preſence ! <!-- Vol. I. S COMAL -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110258" facs="../img/1773-805.pbm"/>
   <!-- 258 FING A L, Book II. --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Comal</hi> was a ſon of Albion ; the chief of an hundred hills! His deer drunk of
   a thouſand ſtreams. A thouſand rocks replied to the voice of his dogs. His face was the mildneſs
   of youth. His hand the death of heroes. One was his love, and fair was ſhe ! the daughter of
   mighty Conloch. She appeared like a ſun-beam among women. Her hair was the wing of the raven. Her
   dogs were taught to the chace. Her bowſtring ſounded on the winds. Her ſoul was fixed on Comal.
   Often met their eyes of love. Their courſe in the chace was one. Happy were their words in
   ſecret. But Grumal loved the maid, the dark chief of the gloomy Ardven. He watched her lone ſteps
   in the heath; the foe of unhappy Comal !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">One</hi> day, tired of the chace, when the miſt had concealed their friends,
   Comal and the daughter of Conloch met, in the cave of Ronan. It was the wonted haunt of Comal.
   Its ſides were hung with his arms. A hundred ſhields of thongs were there; a hundred helms of
   ſounding ſteel. “Reſt here,” he ſaid, “my love Galbina : thou light of the cave of Ronan! A deer
   appears on Mora's brow. I go; but I will ſoon return.” “I fear,” ſhe ſaid, “dark Grumal my foe:
   he haunts the cave of Ronan ! <!-- I will -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110259" facs="../img/1773-808.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 259 --> I will reſt among the arms ; but ſoon return, my love !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> went to the deer of Mora. The daughter of Conloch would try his love. She
   cloathed her fair ſides with his armour ; ſhe ſtrode from the cave of Ronan! He thought it was
   his foe. His heart beat high. His colour changed, and darkneſs dimmed his eyes. He drew the bow.
   The arrow flew. Galbina fell in blood ! He run with wildneſs in his ſteps : he called the
   daughter of Conloch. No anſwer in the lonely rock. Where art thou, O my love? He ſaw, at length,
   her heaving heart, beating around the arrow he threw. “O Conloch's daughter, is it thou? He ſunk
   upon her breaſt! The hunters ſound the hapleſs pair; he afterwards walked the hill. But many and
   ſilent were his ſteps round the dark dwelling of his love. The fleet of the ocean came. He
   fought, the ſtrangers fled. He ſearched for death along the field. But who could ſlay the mighty
   Comhal ! He threw away his dark-brown ſhield. An arrow ſound his manly breaſt. He ſleeps with his
   loved Galbina at the noiſe of the ſounding ſurge ! Their green tombs are ſeen by the mariner,
   when he bounds on the waves of the north. <!-- S 2 F I N- -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110260" facs="../img/1773-642.pbm"/> </p>
 </div>
</div>
