<div type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73110315" facs="../img/1773-970.pbm"/>


 <head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. BOOK VI.</head>



 <pb xml:id="P73110316" facs="../img/1773-973.pbm"/>
 <div type="argument">
  <head>ARGUMENT to Book VI.</head>
  <p> Night comes on. Fingal gives a feaſt to his army, at which Swaran is preſent. The king
   commands Ullin his bard to give the <hi>ſong of peace</hi>; a cuſtom always obſerved at the end
   of a war. Ullin relates the actions of Trenmor, great grandfather to Fingal, in Scandinavia, and
   his marriage with Inibaca, the daughter of a king of Lochlin who was anceſtor to Swaran ; which
   conſideration, together with his being brother to Agandecca, with whom Fingal was in love in his
   youth, induced the king to releaſe him, and permit him to return, with the remains of his army,
   into Lochlin, upon his promiſe of never returning to Ireland, in a hoſtile manner. The night is
   ſpent in ſettling Swaran's departure, in ſongs of bards, and in a converſation in which the ſtory
   of Grumal is introduced by Fingal. Morning comes. Swaran departs; Fingal goes on a hunting party,
   and finding Cuthullin in the cave of Tura, comforts him, and ſets ſail, the next day, for
   Scotland; which concludes the poem. </p>
 </div>



 <div type="poem">
  <pb xml:id="P73110317" facs="../img/1773-976.pbm"/>
  <!-- [ 317 ] -->
  <head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. In SIX BOOKS. BOOK VI.</head>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> clouds of night come rolling down. Darkneſs reſts on the ſteeps of
   Cromla. The ſtars of the north ariſe over the rolling of Erin's waves: they ſhew their heads of
   fire, through the flying miſt of heaven. A diſtant wind roars in the wood. Silent and dark is the
   plain of death ! Still on the duſky Lena aroſe in my ears the voice of Carril. He ſung of the
   friends of our youth; the days of former years ! when we met on the banks of Lego: when we ſent
   round the joy of the ſhell. Cromla, anſwered to his voice. The ghoſts of thoſe he ſung came in
   their ruſtling winds. They were ſeen to bend with joy, towards the ſound of their praiſe !</p>
  <p>
   <!-- BE -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110318" facs="../img/1773-979.pbm"/>
   <!-- 318 F I N G A L, Book VI. --> <hi rend="sc">Be</hi> thy ſoul bleſt, O Carril, in the midſt
   of thy eddying winds. O that thou wouldſt come to my hall, when I am alone by night! And thou
   doſt come, my friend, I hear often thy light hand on my harp ; when it hangs, on the diſtant
   wall, and the feeble ſound touches my ear. Why doſt thou not ſpeak to me in my grief, and tell
   when I ſhall behold my friends ? But thou paſſeſt away in thy murmuring blaſt ; the wind whiſtles
   thro' the grey hair of Oſſian !</p>
  <p>Now, on the ſide of Mora, the heroes gathered to the feaſt. A thouſand aged oaks are burning to
   the wind. The ſtrength<note>
   <p> The ancient Celtæ brewed beer, and they were no ſtrangers to mead. Several ancient poems
    mention wax lights and wine as common in the halls of Fingal. The Caledonians in their frequent
    incurſions to the province might become acquainted with thoſe conveniencies of life, and
    introduce them into their own country, among the booty which they carried from South Britain.
   </p>
   </note> of the ſhells goes round. The ſouls of warriors brighten with joy. But the king of
   Lochlin is ſilent. Sorrow reddens in the eyes of his pride. He often turned toward Lena. He
   remembered that he fell. Fingal leaned on the ſhield of his fathers. His grey locks ſlowly waved
   on the wind, and glittered to the beam of night, He ſaw the grief of Swaran, and ſpoke to the
   firſt of bards. <!-- “RAISE, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110319" facs="../img/1773-982.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 319 --> </p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Raise</hi>, Ullin, raiſe the ſong of peace. O ſooth my ſoul from war. Let mine
   ear forget, in the ſound, the diſmal noiſe of arms. Let a hundred harps be near to gladden the
   king of Lochlin. He muſt depart from us with joy. None ever went ſad from Fingal. Oſcar ! the
   lightning of my ſword is againſt the ſtrong in fight. Peaceful it lies by my ſide when warriors
   yield in war.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Trenmor</hi><note>
   <p> Trenmor was great grandfather to Fingal. The ſtory is introduced to facilitate the diſmiſſion
    of Swaran. </p>
   </note>,” ſaid the mouth of ſongs, “lived in the days of other years. He bounded over the waves
   of the north : companion of the ſtorm ! The high rocks of the land of Lochlin; its groves of
   murmuring ſounds appeared to the hero through miſt : he bound his white-boſomed ſails. Trenmor
   purſued the boar, that roared through the woods of Gormal. Many had fled from its preſence: but
   it rolled in death on the ſpear of Trenmor. Three chiefs, who beheld the deed, told of the mighty
   ſtranger. They told that he ſtood, like a pillar of fire, in the bright arms of his valour. The
   king of Lochlin prepared the feaſt. He called the blooming Trenmor. Three days he feaſted at
   Gormal's windy towers; and received his choice in the combat. The land of Lochlin had no hero,
   that <!-- yielded -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110320" facs="../img/1773-985.pbm"/>
   <!-- 320 F I N G A L, Book VI. --> yielded not to Trenmor. The ſhell of joy went round with
   ſongs, in praiſe of the king of Morven. He that came over the waves, the firſt of mighty men
   !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Now</hi> when the fourth gray morn aroſe, the hero launched his ſhip. He walked
   along the ſilent ſhore, and called for the ruſhing wind: For loud and diſtant he heard the blaſt
   murmuring behind the groves. Covered over with arms of ſteel, a ſon of the woody Gormal appeared.
   Red was his cheek and fair his hair. His ſkin like the ſnow of Morven. Mild rolled his blue and
   ſmiling eye, when he ſpoke to the king of ſwords.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Stay</hi>, Trenmor, ſtay thou firſt of men, thou haſt not conquered Lonval's
   ſon. My ſword has often met the brave. The wiſe ſhun the ſtrength of my bow.” “Thou fair-haired
   youth,” Trenmor replied, “I will not fight with Lonval's ſon. Thine arm is feeble, ſunbeam of
   youth. Retire to Gormal's dark-brown hinds.” “But I will retire,” replied the youth, “with the
   ſword of Trenmor ; and exult in the ſound of my fame. The virgins ſhall gather with ſmiles,
   around him who conquered mighty Trenmor. They ſhall ſigh with the ſighs of love, and admire the
   length of thy ſpear ; when <!-- I şhall -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110321" facs="../img/1773-988.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 321 --> I ſhall carry it among thouſands ; when I lift the glittering
   point to the ſun.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Thou</hi> ſhalt never carry my ſpear,” ſaid the angry king of Morven. “Thy
   mother ſhall find thee pale on the ſhore; and, looking over the dark-blue deep, ſee the ſails of
   him that ſlew her ſon!” “I will not lift the ſpear,” replied the youth,“my arm is not ſtrong with
   years. But, with the feathered dart, I have learned to pierce a diſtant foe. Throw down that
   heavy mail of ſteel. Trenmor is covered from death. I firſt, will lay my mail on earth. Throw now
   thy dart, thou king of Morven !'” He ſaw the heaving of her breaſt. It was the ſiſter of the
   king. She had ſeen him in the hall; and loved his face of youth. The ſpear dropt from the hand of
   Trenmor : he bent his red cheek to the ground. She was to him a beam of light that meets the ſons
   of the cave; when they reviſit the fields of the ſun, and bend their aching eyes !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Chief</hi> of the windy Morven,” begun the maid of the arms of ſnow. “Let me
   reſt in thy bounding ſhip, far from the love of Corlo. For he, like the thunder of the deſart, is
   terrible to Inibaca. He loves me in the gloom of pride. He ſhakes ten thouſand ſpears !” “Reſt
   thou in peace,” ſaid the mighty Trenmor. “Reſt behind the ſhield of my fathers. I will not fly
   from the chief, though he ſhakes ten <!-- Vol. I. Y thouşand -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110322" facs="../img/1773-991.pbm"/>
   <!-- 322 F IN G A L, Boox VI. --> thouſand ſpears!” Three days he waited on the ſhore. He ſent
   his horn abroad. He called Corlo to battle, from all his ecchoing hills. But Corlo came not to
   battle, The king of Lochlin deſcends from his hall. He feaſted on the roaring ſhore. He gave the
   maid to Trenmor !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">King</hi> of Lochlin,” ſaid Fingal, “thy blood flows in the veins of thy foe.
   Our fathers met in battle, becauſe they loved the ſtrife of ſpears. But often did they feaſt in
   the hall: and ſend round the joy of the ſhell. Let thy face brighten with gladneſs, and thine ear
   delight in the harp. Dreadful as the ſtorm of thine ocean, thou haſt poured thy valour forth; thy
   voice has been like the voice of thouſands when they engage in war. Raiſe, to-morrow, raiſe thy
   white ſails to the wind, thou brother of Agandecca ! Bright as the beam of noon, ſhe comes on my
   mournful ſoul. I have ſeen thy tears for the fair one. I ſpared thee in the halls of Starno ;
   when my ſword was red with ſlaughter ; when my eye was full of tears for the maid. Or doſt thou
   chuſe the fight ? The combat which thy fathers gave to Trenmor is thine ! that thou mayeſt depart
   renowned, like the ſun ſetting in the weſt!”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">King</hi> of the race of Morven,” ſaid the chief of reſounding Lochlin! “never
   will Swaran fight with thee, firſt of a thouſand heroes! I have ſeen thee in the halls of Starno
   : few were <!-- thy -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110323" facs="../img/1773-994.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 323. --> thy years beyond my own. When ſhall I, I ſaid to my ſoul,
   lift the ſpear like the noble Fingal? We have fought heretofore, O warrior, on the ſide of the
   ſhaggy Malmor ; after my waves had carried me to thy halls, and the feaſt of a thouſand ſhells
   was ſpread. Let the bards ſend his name who overcame to future years, for noble was the ſtrife of
   Malmor! But many of the ſhips of Lochlin have loſt their youths on Lena. Take theſe, thou king of
   Morven, and be the friend of Swaran ! When thy ſons ſhall come to Gormal, the feaſt of ſhells
   ſhall be ſpread, and the combat offered on the vale.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> ſhip,” replied the king, “ſhall Fingal take, nor land of many hills.
   The deſart is enough to me, with all its deer and woods. Riſe on thy waves again, thou noble
   friend of Agandecca. Spread thy white ſails to the beam of the morning; return to the ecchoing
   hills of Gormal.” “Bleſt be thy ſoul, thou king of ſhells, ſaid Swaran of the dark-brown ſhield.
   “In peace thou art the gale of ſpring. In war the mountain-ſtorm. Take now my hand in friendſhip,
   king of ecchoing Selma! Let thy bards mourn thoſe who fell. Let Erin give the ſons of Lochlin to
   earth. Raiſe high the moſſy ſtones of their fame : that the children of the north hereafter may
   behold the place, where their fathers fought. The hunter may ſay, when he leans on a moſſy
   <!-- Y 2 tomb, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110324" facs="../img/1773-997.pbm"/>
   <!-- 324 F IN G A L, Book VI. --> tomb, here Fingal and Swaran fought, the heroes of other years.
   Thus hereafter ſhall he ſay, and our fame ſhall laſt for ever!”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Swaran</hi>, ſaid the king of hills,“to-day our fame is greateſt. We ſhall paſs
   away like a dream. No ſound will remain in our fields of war. Our tombs will be loſt in the
   heath. The hunter ſhall not know the place of our reſt. Our names may be heard in ſong. What
   avails it, when our ſtrength hath ceaſed? O Oſſian, Carril, and Ullin, you know of heroes that
   are no more. Give us the ſong of other years. Let the night paſs away on the ſound, and morning
   return with joy.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">We</hi> gave the ſong to the kings. An hundred harps mixed their ſound with our
   voice. The face of Swaran brightened, like the full moon of heaven ; when the clouds vaniſh away,
   and leave her calm and broad, in the midſt of the ſky !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Where</hi>, Carril,” ſaid the great Fingal, « Carril of other times! Where is
   the ſon of Semo ? the king of the iſle of miſt? has he retired, like the meteor of death, to the
   dreary cave of Tura ?” “Cuthullin,” ſaid Carril of other times, “lies in the dreary cave of Tura.
   His hand is on the ſword of his ſtrength. His thoughts on the battles he loſt. Mournful is the
   king of ſpears; till now unconquered in war. He ſends his ſword to reſt on the ſide of Fingal :
   <!-- For, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110325" facs="../img/1773-1000.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 325 --> For, like the ſtorm of the deſart, thou haſt ſcattered all
   his foes. Take, O Fingal, the ſword of the hero. His fame is departed like miſt, when it flies,
   before the ruſtling wind, along the brightening vale.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">No</hi>:” replied the king, “Fingal ſhall never take his ſword. His arm is
   mighty in war : his fame ſhall never fail. Many have been overcome in battle; whoſe renown aroſe
   from their fall. O Swaran, king of reſounding woods, give all thy grief away, The vanquiſhed, if
   brave, are renowned. They are like the ſun in a cloud, when he hides his face in the ſouth, but
   looks again on the hills of graſs !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Grumal</hi> was a Chief of Cona, He ſought the battle on every coaſt. His ſoul
   rejoiced in blood. His ear in the din of arms. He poured his warriors on Craca; Craca's king met
   him from his grove: for then, within the circle of Brumo<note>
   <p> This paſſage alludes to the religion of the king of Craca. </p>
   </note>, he ſpoke to the ſtone of power. Fierce was the battle of the heroes, for the maid of the
   breaſt of ſnow. The fame of the daughter of Craca had reached Grumal at the ſtream of Cona : he
   vowed to have the white-boſomed maid, or die on ecchoing Craca. Three days they ſtrove together,
   and Grumal on the fourth <!-- Y 3 was -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110326" facs="../img/1773-1003.pbm"/>
   <!-- 326 F IN G A L, Book VI. --> was bound. Far from his friends they placed him, in the horrid
   circle of Brumo ; where often, they ſaid, the ghoſts of the dead howled round the ſtone of their
   fear. But he afterwards ſhone, like a pillar of the light of heaven. They fell by his mighty
   hand. Grumal had all his fame !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Raise</hi>, ye bards of other times,” continued the great Fingal, “raiſe high
   the praiſe of heroes : that my ſoul may ſettle on their fame; that the mind of Swaran may ceaſe
   to be ſad.” They lay in the heath of Mora. The dark winds ruſtled over the chiefs. A hundred
   voices, at once, aroſe : a hundred harps were ſtrung. They ſung of other times ; the mighty
   chiefs of former years! When now ſhall I hear the bard? When rejoice at the fame of my fathers?
   The harp is not ſtrung on Morven. The voice of muſic aſcends not on Cona. Dead, with the mighty,
   is the bard. Fame is in the deſart no more.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Morning</hi> trembles with the beam of the eaſt; it glimmers on Comla's ſide.
   Over Lena is heard the horn of Swaran. The ſons of the ocean gather around. Silent and ſad they
   riſe on the wave. The blaſt of Erin is behind their ſails. White, as the miſt of Morven, they
   float along the ſea. “Call,” ſaid Fingal, “call my <!-- 8 dogs, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110327" facs="../img/1773-1006.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 327 --> dogs, the long-bounding ſons of the chace. Call
   white-breaſted Bran and the ſurly ſtrength of Luath! Fillan, and Ryno; but he is not here ! My
   ſon reſts on the bed of death. Fillan and Fergus ! blow the horn, that the joy of the chace may
   ariſe : that the deer of Cromla may hear and ſtart at the lake of roes.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſhrill ſound ſpreads along the wood. The ſons of heathy Cromla ariſe. A
   thouſand dogs fly off at once, grey-bounding through the heath. A deer fell by every dog ; three
   by the white-breaſted Bran. He brought them, in their flight, to Fingal, that the joy of the king
   might be great ! One deer fell at the tomb of Ryno. The grief of Fingal returned. He ſaw how
   peaceful lay the ſtone of him, who was the firſt at the chace ! “No more ſhalt thou riſe, O my
   ſon, to partake of the feaſt of Cromla. Soon will thy tomb be hid, and the graſs grow rank on thy
   grave. The ſons of the feeble ſhall paſs along. They ſhall not know where the mighty lie.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Ossian</hi> and Fillan, ſons of my ſtrength. Gaul, chief of the blue ſteel of
   war! let us aſcend the hill to the cave of Tura. Let us find the chief of the battles of Erin.
   Are theſe the walls of Tura ? grey and lonely they riſe on the heath. The chief of ſhells is ſad,
   and the halls <!-- Y 4 are -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110328" facs="../img/1773-1009.pbm"/>
   <!-- 328 F I N G A L, Book VI. --> are ſilent and lonely. Come, let us find Cuthullin, and give
   him all our joy. But is that Cuthullin, O Fillan, or a pillar of ſmoke on the heath? The wind of
   Cromla is on my eyes. I diſtinguiſh not my friend.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> !” replied the youth, “it is the ſon of Semo ! Gloomy and ſad is the
   hero! his hand is on his ſword. Hail to the ſon of battle, breaker of the ſhields?” “Hail to
   thee,” replied Cuthullin, “hail to all the ſons of Morven ! Delightful is thy preſence, O Fingal,
   it is the ſun on Cromla ; when the hunter mourns his abſence for a ſeaſon, and ſees him between
   the clouds. Thy ſons are like ſtars that attend thy courſe. They give light in the night. It is
   not thus thou haſt ſeen me, O Fingal, returning from the wars of thy land : when the kings of the world<note>
   <p> This is the only paſſage in the poem, wherein the wars of Fingal againſt the Romans are
    alluded to: the Roman emperor is diſtinguiſhed in old compoſition by the title of <hi>king of
    the world.</hi> </p>
   </note> had fled, and joy returned to the hill of hinds!” “Many are thy words, Cuthullin,” ſaid Connan<note>
   <p> Connan was of the family of Morni. He is mentioned in ſeveral other poems, and always
    appears, with the ſame character. The poet paſſed him over in ſilence till now, and his
    behaviour here deſerves no better uſage. </p>
   </note> of ſmall renown. “Thy words are many, ſon of Semo, but where are thy deeds in arms? Why
   did we come, over <!-- Ocean, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110329" facs="../img/1773-1012.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM, 329 --> ocean, to aid thy feeble ſword ? Thou flyeſt to thy cave of
   grief, and Connan fights thy battles. Reſign to me theſe arms of light. Yield them, thou chief of
   Erin!” “No hero,” replied the chief,“ever ſought the arms of Cuthullin ; and had a thouſand
   heroes ſought them, it were in vain, thou gloomy youth! I fled not to the cave of grief, till
   Erin failed at her ſtreams.”</p>
  <p>“Youth of the feeble arm,” ſaid Fingal, “Connan ceaſe thy words! Cuthullin is renowned in
   battle ; terrible over the world. Often have I heard thy fame, thou ſtormy chief of Inis-fail.
   Spread now thy white ſails for the iſle of miſt, See Bragela leaning on her rock. Her tender eye
   is in tears; the winds lift her long hair from her heaving breaſt. She liſtens to the breeze of
   night, to hear the voice of thy rowers<note>
   <p> The practice of ſinging when they row is univerſal among the inhabitants of the northweſt
    coaſt of Scotland and the iſles. It deceives time, and inſpirits the rowers. </p>
   </note>; to hear the ſong of the ſea ! the ſound of thy diſtant harp!</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Long</hi> ſhall ſhe liſten in vain. Cuthullin ſhall never return! How can I
   behold Bragela, to raiſe the ſigh of her breaſt? Fingal, I was always victorious, in battles of
   other ſpears !” “And hereafter thou ſhalt be victorious,” ſaid Fingal of generous ſhells. “The
   fame <!-- of -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110330" facs="../img/1773-1015.pbm"/>
   <!-- 330 FI NG A L Book VI. --> of Cuthullin ſhall grow, like the branchy tree of Cromla. Many
   battles await thee, O chief! Many ſhall be the wounds of thy hand ! Bring hither, Oſcar, the
   deer! Prepare the feaſt of ſhells. Let our ſouls rejoice after danger, and our friends delight in
   our preſence !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">We</hi> ſat. We feaſted, We ſung. The ſoul of Cuthullin roſe. The ſtrength of his
   arm returned. Gladneſs brightened along his face. Ullin gave the ſong ; Carril raiſed the voice.
   I joined the bards, and ſung of battles of the ſpear. Battles! where I often fought. Now I fight
   no more ! The fame of my former deeds is ceaſed. I ſit forlorn at the tombs of my friends !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Thus</hi> the night paſſed away in ſong. We brought back the morning with joy.
   Fingal aroſe on the heath, and ſhook his glittering ſpear. He moved firſt toward the plains of
   Lena. We followed in all our arms.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Spread</hi> the ſail,” ſaid the king, “ſeize the winds as they pour from Lena.”
   We roſe on the wave with ſongs. We ruſhed, with joy, through the foam of the deep. </p>
 </div>
</div>
