<div type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73110261" facs="../img/1773-812.pbm"/>
 <head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. BOOK III.</head>

 <pb xml:id="P73110262" facs="../img/1773-815.pbm"/>
 <div type="argument">
  <head>ARGUMENT to Book III.</head>
  <p> Cuthullin, pleaſed with the ſtory of Carril, inſiſts with that bard for more of his ſongs. He
   relates the actions of Fingal in Lochlin, and death of Agandecca the beautiful ſiſter of Swaran.
   He had ſcarce finiſhed when Calmar the ſon of Matha, who had adviſed the firſt battle, came
   wounded from the field, and told them of Swaran's deſign to ſurpriſe the remains of the Iriſh
   army. He himſelf propoſes to withſtand ſingly the whole force of the enemy, in a narrow paſs,
   till the Iriſh ſhould make good their retreat, Cuthullin, touched with the gallant propoſal of
   Calmar, reſolves to accompany him, and orders Carril to carry off the few that remained of the
   Iriſh. Morning comes, Calmar dies of his wounds ; and, the ſhips of the Caledonians appearing,
   Swaran gives over the purſuit of the Iriſh, and returns to oppoſe Fingal's landing. Cuthullin
   aſhamed, after his defeat, to appear before Fingal, retires to the cave of Tura. Fingal engages
   the enemy, puts them to flight; but the coming on of night makes the victory not deciſive, The
   King, who had obſerved the gallant behaviour of his grandſon Oſcar, gives him advices concerning
   his conduct in peace and war. He recommends to him to place the example of his fathers before his
   eyes, as the beſt model for his conduct ; which introduces the epiſode concerning Fainaſollis,
   the daughter of the king of Craca, whom Fingal had taken under his protection, in his youth.
   Fillan and Oſcar are diſpatched to obſerve the motions of the enemy by night ; Gaul the ſon of
   Morni deſires the command of the army, in the next battle; which Fingal promiſes to give him.
   Some general reflections of the poet cloſe the third day. </p>
 </div>
 <div type="translation">

  <pb xml:id="P73110263" facs="../img/1773-818.pbm"/>
  <!-- [ 263 ] -->
  <head>FINGAL, AN ANCIENT EPIC POEM. In SIX BOOKS. BOOK III.</head>
  <p><note>
   <p> The ſecond night, ſince the opening of the poem, continues ; and Cuthullin, Connal, and
     Carril ſtill ſit in the place deſcribed in the preceding book. The ſtory of Agandecca is
     introduced here with propriety, as great uſe is made of it in the courſe of the poem, and as
     it, in ſome meaſure, brings about the cataſtrophe. </p></note></p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Pleasant</hi> are the words of the ſong,” ſaid Cuthullin ! “lovely the tales of
   other times! They are, like the calm dew of the morning on the hill of roes; when the ſun is
   faint on its ſide, and the lake is ſettled and blue in the vale. O Carril, raiſe again thy voice
   ; let me hear the ſong of Selma : which was ſung in my halls of joy, when Fingal king of ſhields
   was there, and glowed at the deeds of his fathers.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi>! thou dweller of battle,” ſaid Carril, “early were thy deeds in
   arms. Lochlin <!-- S 4 was -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110264" facs="../img/1773-821.pbm"/>
   <!-- 264 FI N G A L, Boox III. --> was conſumed in thy wrath, when thy youth ſtrove with the
   beauty of maids. They ſmiled at the fair-blooming face of the hero; but death was in his hands.
   He was ſtrong as the waters of Lora. His followers were the roar of a thouſand ſtreams. They took
   the king of Lochlin in war; they reſtored him to his ſhips. His big heart ſwelled with pride ;
   the death of the youth was dark in his ſoul. For none ever, but Fingal, had overcome the ſtrength
   of the mighty Starno<note>
   <p> Starno was the father of Swaran as well as Agandecca. His fierce and cruel character is well
    marked in other poems concerning the times. </p>
   </note>. He ſat in the hall of his ſhells in Lochlin's woody land. He called the grey-haired
   Snivan, that often ſung round the circle<note>
   <p> This paſſage moſt certainly alludes to the religion of Lochlin, and <hi>the ſtone of
    power</hi> here mentioned is the image of one of the deities of Scandinavia. </p>
   </note> of Loda : when the ſtone of power heard his voice, and battle turned in the field of the
   valiant!</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Go</hi>; grey-haired Snivan,” Starno ſaid, “go to Ardven's ſea-ſurrounded rocks.
   Tell to the king of Selma; he the faireſt among his thouſands, tell him I give him my daughter,
   the lovelieſt maid, that ever heaved a breaſt of ſnow. Her arms are white as the foam of my
   waves. Her ſoul is generous and mild. Let him come with his braveſt heroes, to the daughter of
   the <!-- şecret -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110265" facs="../img/1773-824.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM. 265 --> ſecret hall!” Snivan came to Selma's hall : Fair-haired
   Fingal attended his ſteps. His kindled ſoul flew to the maid, as he bounded on the waves of the
   north. “Welcome,” ſaid the dark-brown Starno, “welcome, king of rocky Morven : Welcome his heroes
   of might ; ſons of the diftant iſle! Three days within my halls ſhall ye feaſt; three days purſue
   my boars; that your fame may reach the maid who dwells in the ſecret hall.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Starno</hi> deſigned their death. He gave the feaſt of ſhells. Fingal, who
   doubted the foe, kept on his arms of ſteel. The ſons of death were afraid : They fled from the
   eyes of the king. The voice of ſprightly mirth aroſe. The trembling harps of joy were ſtrung.
   Bards ſung the battle of heroes: They ſung the heaving breaſt of love. Ullin, Fingal's bard, was
   there : the ſweet voice of reſounding Cona. He praiſed the daughter of Lochlin; and Morven's<note>
   <p> All the North-weſt coaſt of Scotland probably went of old under the name of Morven, which
    ſignifies a ridge of very high hills. </p>
   </note> high-deſcended chief. The daughter of Lochlin overheard. She left the hall of her ſecret
   ſigh ! She came in all her beauty, like the moon from the cloud of the eaſt. Lovelineſs was
   around her as light. Her ſteps were the muſic of ſongs. She <!-- 8 şaw -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110266" facs="../img/1773-827.pbm"/>
   <!-- 266 F I N G A L, Book III. --> ſaw the youth and loved him. He was the ſtolen ſigh of her
   ſoul. Her blue eye rolled on him in ſecret : ſhe bleſt the chief of reſounding Morven.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> third day with all its beams, ſhone bright on the wood of boars. Forth
   moved the dark-browed Starno; and Fingal, king of ſhields. Half the day they ſpent in the chace ;
   the ſpear of Selma was red in blood. It was then the daughter of Starno, with blue eyes rolling
   in tears; it was then ſhe came with her voice of love and ſpoke to the king of Norven. “Fingal,
   high deſcended chief, truſt not Starno's heart of pride. Within that wood he has placed his
   chiefs. Beware of the wood of death. But, remember, ſon of the iſle, remember Agandecca : ſave me
   from the wrath of my father, king of the windy Morven !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> youth, with unconcern, went on ; his heroes by his ſide. The ſons of
   death fell by his hand; and Gormal ecchoed around ! Before the halls of Starno the ſons of the
   chace convened. The king's dark brows were like clouds. His eyes like meteors of night. “Bring
   hither,” he ſaid, “Agandecca to her lovely king of Morven ! His hand is ſtained with the blood of
   my people ; her words have not been in vain !” She came with the red eye of tears. She came
   <!-- with -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110267" facs="../img/1773-830.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM, 367 --> with looſely flowing locks. Her white breaſt heaved with
   broken ſighs, like the foam of the ſtreamy Lubar. Starno pierced her ſide with ſteel. She fell,
   like a wreath of ſnow, which ſlides from the rocks of Ronan ; when the woods are ſtill, and eccho
   deepens in the vale ! Then Fingal eyed his valiant chiefs, his valiant Chiefs took arms. The
   gloom of battle roared ; Lochlin fled or died. Pale, in his bounding ſhip he cloſed the maid of
   the ſofteſt ſoul. Her tomb aſcends on Ardven; the ſea roars round her narrow dwelling.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Blessed</hi> be her ſoul,” ſaid Cuthullin ; “bleſſed be the mouth of the ſong!
   Strong was the youth of Fingal; ſtrong is his arm of age. Lochlin ſhall fall again before the
   king of ecchoing Morven. Shew thy face from a cloud, O moon; light his white ſails on the wave:
   And if any ſtrong ſpirit<note>
   <p> This is the only paſſage in the poem that has the appearance of religion. But Cuthullin's
    apoſtrophe to this ſpirit is accompanied with a doubt, ſo that it is not eaſy to determine
    whether the hero meant a ſuperior being, or the ghoſts of deceaſed warriors, who were ſuppoſed
    in thoſe times to rule the ſtorms, and to tranſport themſelves in a guſt of wind from one
    country to another. </p>
   </note> of heaven ſits on that low-hung cloud; turn his dark ſhips from the rock, thou rider of
   the ſtorm ! <!-- SUCH -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110268" facs="../img/1773-833.pbm"/>
   <!-- 268 F I N G A L, Book III. --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were the words of Cuthullin at the ſound of the mountain-ſtream ; when
   Calmar aſcended the hill, the wounded ſon of Matha. From the field he came in his blood. He
   leaned on his bending ſpear. Feeble is the arm of battle ! but ſtrong the ſoul of the hero
   “Welcome! O ſon of Matha,” ſaid Connal, “welcome art thou to thy friends ! Why burſts that broken
   ſigh, from the breaſt of him who never feared before? And never, Connal, will he fear, chief of
   the pointed ſteel! My ſoul brightens in danger: in the noiſe of arms. I am of the race of battle.
   My fathers never feared.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Cormar</hi> was the firſt of my race. He ſported through the ſtorms of waves.
   His black ſkiff bounded on ocean; he travelled on the wings of the wind. A ſpirit once embroiled
   the night. Seas ſwell and rocks reſound. Winds drive along the clouds. The lightning flies on
   wings of fire. He feared and came to land: then bluſhed that he feared at all. He ruſhed again
   among the waves to find the ſon of the wind. Three youths guide the bounding bark ; he ſtood with
   ſword unſheathed. When the low-hung vapour paſſed, he took it by the curling head. He ſearched
   its dark womb with <!-- his -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110269" facs="../img/1773-836.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM. 269 --> his ſteel. The ſon of the wind forſook the air. The moon and
   ſtars returned ! Such was the boldneſs of my race. Calmar is like his fathers. Danger flies from
   the lifted ſword. They beſt ſucceed who dare !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> now, ye ſons of green Erin, retire from Lena's bloody heath. Collect the
   ſad remnant of our friends, and join the ſword of Fingal. I heard the ſound of Lochlin's
   advancing arms ! Calmar will remain and fight. My voice ſhall be ſuch, my friends, as if
   thouſands were behind me. But, ſon of Semo, remember me. Remember Calmar's lifeleſs corſe. When
   Fingal ſhall have waſted the field, place me by ſome ſtone of remembrance, that future times may
   hear my fame ; that the mother of Calmar may rejoice in my renown.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">No</hi>: ſon of Matha,” ſaid Cuthullin, “I will never leave thee here. My joy is
   in unequal fight: my ſoul increaſes in danger. Connal, and Carril of other times, carry off the
   ſad ſons of Erin. When the battle is over, ſearch for us in this narrow way. For near this oak we
   ſhall fall, in the ſtream of the battle of thouſands !” O Fithil's ſon, with flying ſpeed ruſh
   over the heath of Lena. Tell to Fingal that Erin is fallen. Bid the king of Morven come. O let
   <!-- him -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110270" facs="../img/1773-839.pbm"/>
   <!-- 270 F I N G A L, Book III. --> him come, like the ſun in a ſtorm, to lighten, to reſtore the
   iſle !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Morning</hi> is grey on Cromla. The ſons of the ſea aſcend. Calmar ſtood forth to
   meet them in the pride of his kindling ſoul. But pale was the face of the chief. He leaned on his
   father's ſpear. That ſpear which he brought from Lara, when the ſoul of his mother was ſad ; the
   ſoul of the lonely Alcletha, waining in the ſorrow of years. But ſlowly now the hero falls, like
   a tree on the plain. Dark Cuthullin ſtands alone like a rock in a ſandy vale. The ſea comes with
   its waves, and roars on its hardened ſides. Its head is covered with foam ; the hills are
   ecchoing around.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Now</hi> from the grey miſt of the ocean, the white-ſailed ſhips of Fingal
   appear. High is the grove of their maſts, as they nod, by turns, on the rolling wave. Swaran ſaw
   them from the hill. He returned from the ſons of Erin. As ebbs the reſounding ſea, through the
   hundred iſles of Iniſtore; ſo loud, ſo vaſt, ſo immenſe returned the ſons of Lochlin againſt the
   king. But bending, weeping, ſad, and ſlow, and dragging his long ſpear behind, Cuthullin ſunk in
   Cromla's wood, and mourned his fallen friends. He feared the face of Fingal, who was wont to
   greet him from the fields of renown ! <!-- 7 “How -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110271" facs="../img/1773-842.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM. 271 --> “<hi rend="sc">How</hi> many lie there of my heroes! the
   chiefs of Erin's race! they that were chearful in the hall, when the ſound of the ſhells aroſe !
   No more ſhall I find their ſteps in the heath. No more ſhall I hear their voice in the chace.
   Pale, ſilent, low on bloody beds, are they who were my friends! O ſpirits of the lately dead,
   meet Cuthullin on his heath. Speak to him on the wind, when the ruſtling tree of Tura's cave
   reſounds. There, far remote, I ſhall lie unknown. No bard ſhall hear of me. No grey tone ſhall
   riſe to my renown. Mourn me with the dead, O Bragela ! departed is my fame.” Such were the words
   of Cuthullin, when he ſunk in the woods of Cromla !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi>, tall in his ſhip, ſtretched his bright lance before him. Terrible
   was the gleam of the ſteel : it was like the green meteor of death, ſetting in the heath of
   Malmor, when the traveller is alone, and the broad moon is darkened in heaven.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">The</hi> battle is paſt,” ſaid the king, “I behold the blood of my friends. Sad
   is the heath of Lena! mournful the oaks of Cromla. The hunters have fallen in their ſtrength :
   the ſon of Semo is no more. Ryno and Fillan, my ſons, ſound the horn of Fingal. Aſcend that hill
   on the ſhore; call the children of the foe. <!-- Call -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110272" facs="../img/1773-845.pbm"/>
   <!-- 272 F I N G A L, Book III. --> Call them from the grave of Lamdarg, the chief of other
   times. Be your voice like that of your father, when he enters the battles of his ſtrength. I wait
   for the mighty ſtranger. I wait on Lena's ſhore for Swaran. Let him come with all his race;
   ſtrong in battle are the friends of the dead !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Fair</hi> Ryno as lightning gleamed along : Dark Fillan ruſhed like the ſhade of
   autumn. On Lena's heath their voice is heard. The ſons of ocean heard the horn of Fingal. As the
   roaring eddy of ocean returning from the kingdom of ſnows; ſo ſtrong, ſo dark, ſo ſudden came
   down the ſons of Lochlin. The king in their front appears, in the diſmal pride of his arms !
   Wrath burns on his dark-brown face : his eyes roll in the fire of his valour. Fingal beheld the
   ſon of Starno: he remembered Agandecca. For Swaran with the tears of youth had mourned his
   white-boſomed ſiſter. He ſent Ullin of ſongs to bid him to the feaſt of ſhells : For pleaſant on
   Fingal's ſoul returned the memory of the firſt of his loves !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Ullin</hi> came with aged ſteps, and ſpoke to Starno's ſon. “O thou that dwelleſt
   afar, ſurrounded, like a rock, with thy waves ! come to the feaſt of the King, and paſs the day
   in reſt. To-morrow let us fight, O Swaran, and break <!-- the -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110273" facs="../img/1773-848.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM. 273 --> the ecchoing ſhields.” “To-day,” ſaid Starno's wrathful ſon,
   “we break the ecchoing ſhields: to-morrow my feaſt ſhall be ſpread ; but Fingal ſhall lie on
   earth,” “To-morrow let his feaſt be ſpread,” ſaid Fingal with a ſmile. “To-day, O my ſons, we
   ſhall break the ecchoing ſhields. Oſſian, ſtand thou near my arm. Gaul, lift thy terrible ſword.
   Fergus, bend thy crooked yew. Throw, Fillan, thy lance through heaven. Lift your ſhields, like
   the darkened moon. Be your ſpears the meteors of death. Follow me in the path of my fame. Equal
   my deeds in battle.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> a hundred winds on Morven; as the ſtreams of a hundred hills; as clouds
   fly ſucceſſive over heaven; as the dark ocean aſſails the ſhore of the deſart: ſo roaring, ſo
   vaſt, ſo terrible the armies mixed on Lena's ecchoing heath. The groan of the people ſpread over
   the hills: it was like the thunder of night, when the cloud burſts on Cona ; and a thouſand
   ghoſts ſhriek at once on the hollow wind. Fingal ruſhed on in his ſtrength, terrible as the
   ſpirit of Trenmor; when, in a whirlwind, he comes to Morven, to ſee the children of his pride.
   The oaks reſound on their mountains, and the rocks fall down before him. Dimly ſeen, as
   <!-- Vol. I. T lightens -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110274" facs="../img/1773-851.pbm"/>
   <!-- 274 F I N G A L, Book III. --> lightens the night, he ſtrides largely from hill to hill.
   Bloody was the hand of my father, when he whirled the gleam of his ſword. He remembers the
   battles of his youth. The field is waſted in his courſe !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Ryno</hi> went on like a pillar of fire. Dark is the brow of Gaul. Fergus ruſhed
   forward with feet of wind. Fillan like the miſt of the hill. Oſſian, like a rock, came down. I
   exulted in the ſtrength of the king. Many were the deaths of my arm ! diſmal the gleam of my
   ſword! My locks were not then ſo grey ; nor trembled my hands with age. My eyes were not cloſed
   in darkneſs; my feet failed not in the race !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Who</hi> can relate the deaths of the people ? Who the deeds of mighty heroes ?
   when Fingal, burning in his wrath, conſumed the ſons of Lochlin? groans ſwelled on groans from
   hill to hill, till night had covered all. Pale, ſtaring like a herd of deer, the ſons of Lochlin
   convene on Lena. We ſat and heard the ſprightly harp, at Lubar's gentle ſtream. Fingal himſelf
   was next to the foe. He liſtened to the tales of his bards. His godlike race were in the ſong,
   the chiefs of other times. Attentive, leaning on his ſhield, the king of Morven ſat. The wind
   whiſtled through his locks; his thoughts are of <!-- the -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110275" facs="../img/1773-854.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM. 275 --> the days of other years. Near him on his bending ſpear, my
   young, my valiant Oſcar ſtood. He admired the king of Morven: his deeds were ſwelling in his
   ſoul!</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of my ſon,” begun the king, “O Oſcar, pride of youth ! I ſaw the
   ſhining of thy ſword. I gloried in my race. Purſue the fame of our fathers; be thou what they
   have been, when Trenmor lived, the firſt of men, and Trathal the father of heroes! They fought
   the battle in their youth. They are the ſong of bards. O Oſcar ! bend the ſtrong in arm : but
   ſpare the feeble hand. Be thou a ſtream of many tides againſt the foes of thy people ; but like
   the gale, that moves the graſs, to thoſe who aſk thine aid. So Trenmor lived; ſuch Trathal was ;
   and ſuch has Fingal been. My arm was the ſupport of the injured ; the weak reſted behind the
   lightning of my ſteel.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Oscar</hi>! I was young like thee, when lovely Fainaſóllis came : that ſun-beam!
   that mild light of love! the daughter of Craca's<note>
   <p> What the Craca here mentioned was, is not, at this diſtance of time, eaſy to determine. The
    moſt probable opinion is, that it was one of the Shetland iſles. There is a ſtory concerning a
    daughter of the king of Craca in the ſixth book. </p>
   </note> king! I then returned from Cona's heath, and <!-- T 2 few -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110276" facs="../img/1773-857.pbm"/>
   <!-- 276 F I N G A L, Book III. --> few were in my train: A white-ſailed boat appeared far off;
   we ſaw it like a miſt, that rode on ocean's wind. It ſoon approached. We ſaw the fair. Her white
   breaſt heaved with ſighs, The wind was in her looſe dark hair : her roſy cheek had tears.
   “Daughter of beauty,” calm I ſaid, “what ſigh is in thy breaſt? Can I, young as I am, defend
   thee, daughter of the ſea? My ſword is not unmatched in war, but dauntleſs is my heart.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">To</hi> thee I fly,” with ſighs ſhe ſaid, “O prince of mighty men! To thee I
   fly, chief of the generous ſhells, ſupporter of the feeble hand ! The king of Craca's ecchoing
   iſle owned me the ſunbeam of his race. Cromala's hills have heard the ſighs of love for unhappy
   Fainaſóllis ! Sora's chief beheld me fair; he loved the daughter of Craca. His ſword is a beam of
   light upon the warrior's ſide. But dark is his brow ; and tempeſts are in his ſoul. I ſhun him,
   on the roaring ſea ; but Sora's chief purſues.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Rest</hi> thou,” I ſaid, “behind my ſhield; reſt in peace, thou beam of light!
   The gloomy chief of Sora will fly, if Fingal's arm is like his ſoul. In ſome lone cave I might
   conceal thee, daughter of the ſea! But Fingal never flies. Where the danger threatens, I rejoice
   in the ſtorm of ſpears.” I ſaw the tears upon her <!-- 3 cheek. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110277" facs="../img/1773-860.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III, An EPIC POEM. 277 --> cheek. I pitied Craca's fair. Now, like a dreadful wave
   afar, appeared the ſhip of ſtormy Borbar. His maſts high-bended over the ſea behind their ſheets
   of ſnow. White roll the waters on either ſide. The ſtrength of ocean ſounds. “Come thou,” I ſaid,
   “from the roar of ocean, thou rider of the ſtorm ! Partake the feaſt within my hall. It is the
   houſe of ſtrangers.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> maid ſtood trembling by my ſide. He drew the bow. She fell. “Unerring is
   thy hand,” I ſaid, “but feeble was the foe!” We fought, nor weak the ſtrife of death! He ſank
   beneath my ſword. We laid them in two tombs of ſtone; the hapleſs lovers of youth! Such have I
   been in my youth, O Oſcar; be thou like the age of Fingal. Never ſearch thou for battle ; nor
   ſhun it when it comes.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Fillan</hi> and Oſcar of the dark-brown hair ! ye, that are ſwift in the race !
   fly over the heath in my preſence. View the ſons of Lochlin. Far off I hear the noiſe of their
   fear, like diſtant ſounds in woods. Go: that they may not fly from my ſword, along the waves of
   the north. For many chiefs of Erin's race, lie here on the dark bed of death. The children of war
   are low ; the ſons of ecchoing Cromla.” <!-- T3 THE -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110278" facs="../img/1773-863.pbm"/>
   <!-- 278 FIN G A L, Book III. --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> heroes flew like two dark clouds: two dark clouds that are the chariots
   of ghoſts; when air's dark children come forth to frighten hapleſs men. It was then that Gaul<note>
   <p> Gaul, the ſon of Morni, was chief of a tribe that diſputed long, the pre-eminence, with
    Fingal himſelf. They were reduced at laſt to obedience, and Gaul, from an enemy, turned Fingal's
    beſt friend and greateſt hero, His character is ſomething like that of Ajax in the Iliad ; a
    hero of more ſtrength than conduct in battle. He was very fond of military fame, and here he
    demands the next battle to himſelf. The poet, by an artifice, removes Fingal, that his return
    may be the more magnificent. </p>
   </note>, the ſon of Morni, ſtood like a rock in night. His ſpear is glittering to the ſtars; his
   voice like many ſtreams.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of battle,” cried the chief, “O Fingal, king of ſhells! let the bards
   of many ſongs ſooth Erin's friends to reſt. Fingal, ſheath thou thy ſword of death; and let thy
   people fight, We wither away without our fame ; our king is the only breaker of ſhields! When
   morning riſes on our hills, behold, at a diſtance, our deeds. Let Lochlin feel the ſword of
   Morni's ſon ; that bards may ſing of me. Such was the cuſtom heretofore of Fingal's noble race.
   Such was thine own, thou king of ſwords, in battles of the ſpear.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">O son</hi> of Morni,” Fingal replied, “I glory in thy fame. Fight; but my ſpear
   ſhall <!-- be -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110279" facs="../img/1773-866.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book III. An EPIC POEM. 279 --> be near, to aid thee in the midſt of danger. Raiſe, raiſe
   the voice, ye ſons of ſong, and lull me into reſt. Here will Fingal lie, amidſt the wind of
   night. And if thou, Agandecca, art near, among the children of thy land ; if thou ſitteſt on a
   blaſt of wind, among the high-ſhrowded maſts of Lochlin; come to my dreams<note>
   <p> The poet prepares us for the dream of Fingal in the next book. </p>
   </note>, my fair one. Shew thy bright face to my ſoul.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Many</hi> a voice and many a harp, in tuneful ſounds aroſe. Of Fingal's noble
   deeds they ſung ; of Fingal's noble race: And ſometimes, on the lovely ſound, was heard the name
   of Oſſian. I often fought, and often won, in battles of the ſpear. But blind, and tearful, and
   forlorn I walk with little men! O Fingal, with thy race of war I now behold thee not! The wild
   roes feed on the green tomb of the mighty king of Morven! Bleſt be thy ſoul, thou king of ſwords,
   thou moſt renowned on the hills of Cona ! <!-- T 4 F I N- -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110280" facs="../img/1773-869.pbm"/> </p>
 </div>
</div>
