<front xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73100001" facs="../img/1773-014.pbm"/>

 <titlePage>
  <docTitle>
   <titlePart>THE POEMS OF OSSIAN.</titlePart>
   <titlePart>TRANSLATED By JAMES MACPHERSON, Eſq: </titlePart>
   <titlePart>IN TWO VOLUMES. </titlePart>
   <titlePart>VOL. I.</titlePart>
  </docTitle>
  <docEdition>A NEW EDITION, Carefully corrected, and greatly improved.</docEdition>
  <docImprint>LONDON: Printed for <hi rend="sc">W. Strahan</hi>; and <hi rend="sc">T. Becket</hi>,
   in the Strand, Bookſeller to their Royal Highneſſes the Prince of <hi rend="sc">Wales</hi> and
   Biſhop of <hi rend="sc">Osnabrugh</hi>.</docImprint>
  <docDate>MDCCLXXIII. </docDate>
 </titlePage>

 <pb xml:id="P73100002" facs="../img/1773-017.pbm"/>
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb xml:id="P73100003" facs="../img/1773-020.pbm"/>
 <!--  -->
 <div>
  <head>PREFACE.</head>
  <p> <hi rend="sc">Without</hi> encreaſing his genius, the Author may have improved his language,
   in the eleven years, that the following poems have been in the hands of the public. Errors in
   diction might have been committed at twenty-four, which the experience of a riper age may remove;
   and ſome exuberances in imagery may be reſtrained, with advantage, by a degree of judgment
   acquired in the progreſs of time. Impreſſed with this opinion, he ran over the whole with
   attention and accuracy ; and, he hopes, he has brought the work to a ſtate of correctneſs, which
   will preclude all future improvements.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> eagerneſs, with which theſe Poems have been received abroad, are a
   recompence for the coldneſs with which a few have affected to treat them at home. All the polite
   nations of Europe have transferred them into their <!--  -->
   <!-- Ar ſpective -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100004" facs="../img/1773-023.pbm"/>
   <!-- vi PREFACE. --> reſpective languages; and they ſpeak of him, who brought them to light, in
   terms that might flatter the vanity of one fond of fame. In a convenient indifference for a
   literary reputation, the Author hears praiſe without being elevated, and ribaldry, without being
   depreſſed. He has frequently ſeen the firſt beſtowed too precipitately; and the latter is ſo
   faithleſs to its purpoſe, that it is often the only index to merit in the preſent age.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Though</hi> the taſte, which defines genius, by the points of the compaſs, is a
   ſubject fit for mirth in itſelf, it is often a ſerious matter in the ſale of a work. When rivers
   define the limits of abilities, as well as the boundaries of countries, a Writer may meaſure his
   ſucceſs, by the latitude under which he was born. It was to avoid a part of this inconvenience,
   that the Author is ſaid, by ſome, who ſpeak without any authority, to have aſcribed his own
   productions to another name. If this was the caſe, he was but young in the art of deception. When
   he placed the poet in <!--  -->
   <!-- antiquity, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100005" facs="../img/1773-026.pbm"/>
   <!-- PREFACE. vii --> antiquity, the Tranſlator ſhould have been born on this ſide of the
   Tweed.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">These</hi> obſervations regard only the frivolous in matters of literature;
   theſe, however, form a majority in every age and nation. In this country, men of genuine taſte
   abound ; but their ſtill voice is drowned in the clamours of a multitude, who judge by faſhion of
   poetry, as of dreſs. The truth is, to judge aright requires almoſt as much genius as to write
   well; and good critics are as rare as great poets. Though two hundred thouſand Romans ſtood up,
   when Virgil came into the Theatre, Varius only could correct the Æneid. He that obtains fame muſt
   receive it through mere faſhion; and gratify his vanity with the applauſe of men, of whoſe
   judgment he cannot approve.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> following Poems, it muſt be confeſſed, are more calculated to pleaſe
   perſons of exquiſite feelings of heart, than thoſe who receive all their impreſſions by the ear.
   The novelty of cadence, in what is called a proſe verſion, tho' <!--  -->
   <!-- A 4 not -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100006" facs="../img/1773-029.pbm"/>
   <!-- viii PREFACE --> not deſtitute of harmony, will not to common readers ſupply the abſence of
   the frequent returns of rhime. This was the opinion of the Writer himſelf, tho' he yielded to the
   judgment of others, in a mode, which preſented freedom and dignity of expreſſion, inſtead of
   fetters, which cramp the thought, whilſt the harmony of language is preſerved. His intention was
   to publiſh in verſe. The making of poetry, like any other handicraft, may be learned by induſtry;
   and he had ſerved his apprenticeſhip, though in ſecret, to the muſes,</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is, however, doubtful, whether the harmony which theſe poems might derive
   from rhime, even in much better hands than thoſe of the tranſlator, could atone for the
   ſimplicity and energy, which they would loſe. The determination of this point ſhall be left to
   the readers of this preface. The following is the beginning of a poem, tranſlated from the Norſe
   to the Gaëlic language ; and, from the latter, transferred into Engliſh. The verſe took little
   more time to the writer than the proſe; and even he himſelf is doubtful, (if he <!--  -->
   <!-- 8 has -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100007" facs="../img/1773-032.pbm"/>
   <!-- PREFACE. ix --> has ſucceeded in either) which of them is the moſt literal verſion.</p>
  <quote><label>FRAGMENT of a NORTHERN TALE.</label>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Where</hi> Harold, with golden hair, ſpread o'er Lochlin<note>
   <p>The Gaelic name of Scandinavia, or Scandinia, </p></note> his high commands; where, with
   juſtice, he ruled the tribes, who ſunk, ſubdued, beneath his ſword ; abrupt riſes Gormal<note>
   <p> The mountains of Sevo, </p></note> in ſnow ! The tempeſts roll dark on his ſides, but calm,
   above, his vaſt forehead appears, White-iſſuing from the ſkirt of his ſtorms, the troubled
   torrents pour down his ſides. Joining, as they roar along, they bear the Torno, in foam, to the
   main.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">Grey</hi> on the bank and far from men, halfcovered by ancient pines, from the
   wind, a lonely pile exalts its head, long-ſhaken by the ſtorms of the north. To this fled Sigurd,
   fierce in fight, from Harold the leader of armies, when fate had brightened his ſpear, <!--  -->
   <!-- with -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100008" facs="../img/1773-035.pbm"/>
   <!-- x PREFACE. --> with renown: When he conquered in that rude field, where Lulan's warriors
   fell in blood, or roſe, in terror, on the waves of the main. Darkly ſat the grey-haired chief;
   yet ſorrow dwelt not in his ſoul. But when the warrior thought on the paſt, his proud heart
   heaved again his ſide: Forth-flew his ſword from its place, he wounded Harold in all the
   winds.</p>
   <p><hi rend="sc">One</hi> daughter, and only one, but bright in form and mild of ſoul, the laſt
   beam of the ſetting line, remained to Sigurd of all his race. His ſon, in Lulan's battle ſlain,
   beheld not his father's flight from his foes. Nor finiſhed ſeemed the ancient line ! The ſplendid
   beauty of bright-eyed Fithon, covered ſtill the fallen king with renown. Her arm was white like
   Gormal's ſnow ; her boſom whiter than the foam of the main, when roll the waves beneath the wrath
   of the winds. Like two ſtars were her radiant eyes, like two ſtars that riſe on the deep, when
   dark tumult embroils the night. Pleaſant are their beams aloft, as ſtately they aſcend the
   ſkies.</p>
   <p>
   <!--  -->
   <!-- NOR -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100009" facs="../img/1773-038.pbm"/>
   <!-- PREFACE, xi --> <hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> Odin forgot, in aught, the maid. Her form ſcarce
   equalled her lofty mind. Awe moved around her ſtately ſteps. Heroes loved—but ſhrunk away in
   their fears. Yet midſt the pride of all her charms, her heart was ſoft, and her ſoul was kind.
   She ſaw the mournful with tearful eyes. Tranſient darkneſs aroſe in her breaſt. Her joy was in
   the chace. Fach morning, when doubtful light wandered dimly on Lulan's waves, ſhe rouzed the
   reſounding woods, to Gormal's head of ſnow. Nor moved the maid alone, &amp;c. </p>
   <p> <label><hi>The ſame verſified</hi></label>. </p><lg>
   <l> <hi rend="sc">Where</hi> fair-hair'd Harold, o'er Scandinia reign'd</l>
   <l> And held, with juſtice, what his valour gain'd,</l>
   <l> Sevo, in ſnow, his rugged forehead rears</l>
   <l> And, o'er the warfare of his ſtorms, appears</l>
   <l> Abrupt and vaſt. — White-wandering down his ſide</l>
   <l> A thouſand torrents, gleaming as they glide,</l>
   <l> Unite below ; and pouring through the plain</l>
   <l> Hurry the troubled Torno to the main.</l>
   </lg><lg>
   <l><hi rend="sc">Grey</hi>, on the bank, remote from human kind, </l>
   <l>By aged pines, half ſhelter'd from the wind, </l>
   <l>A homely manſion roſe, of antique form, </l>
   <l>For ages batter'd by the polar ſtorm. </l>
   <l>To this fierce Sigurd fled, from Norway's lord </l>
   <l>When fortune ſettled, on the warrior's ſword, <!--  -->
    <!-- in -->
    <pb xml:id="P73100010" facs="../img/1773-041.pbm"/>
    <!-- xii PREFACE. --> </l>
   <l>In that rude field, where Suecia's chieſs were ſlain, </l>
   <l>Or forced to wander o'er the Bothnic main. </l>
   <l>Dark was his life, yet undiſturb'd with woes, </l>
   <l>But when the memory of defeat aroſe </l>
   <l>His proud heart ſtruck his ſide ; he graſpt the ſpear, </l>
   <l>And wounded Harold in the vacant air.</l>
   </lg><lg>
   <l><hi rend="sc">One</hi> daughter only, but of form divine, </l>
   <l>The laſt fair beam of the departing line, </l>
   <l>Remain'd of Sigurd's race. His warlike ſon </l>
   <l>Fell in the ſhock, which overturn'd the throne. </l>
   <l>Nor deſolate the houſe ! Fionia's charms </l>
   <l>Suſtain'd the glory, which they loſt in arms. </l>
   <l>White was her arm, as Sevo's lofty ſnow, </l>
   <l>Her boſom fairer, than the waves below, </l>
   <l>When heaving to the winds. Her radiant eyes </l>
   <l>Like two bright ſtars, exulting as they riſe, </l>
   <l>O'er the dark tumult of a ſtormy night </l>
   <l>And gladd'ning heav'n, with their majeſtic light,</l>
   </lg><lg>
   <l><hi rend="sc">In</hi> nought is Odin to the maid unkind </l>
   <l>Her form ſcarce equals her exalted mind, </l>
   <l>Awe leads her ſacred ſteps where'er they move, </l>
   <l>And mankind worſhip, where they dare not love. </l>
   <l>But, mix'd with ſoftneſs, was the virgin's pride, </l>
   <l>Her heart had feelings, which her eyes deny'd. </l>
   <l>Her bright tears ſtarted at another's woes, </l>
   <l>While tranſient darkneſs on her ſoul aroſe.</l>
   </lg><lg>
   <l><hi rend="sc">The</hi> chace ſhe lov'd; when morn, with doubtful beam </l>
   <l>Came dimly wandering o'er the Bothnic ſtream, </l>
   <l>On Sevo's ſounding ſides, ſhe bent the bow, </l>
   <l>And rouz'd his foreſts to his head of ſnow. </l>
   <l>Nor mov'd the maid alone; &amp;c. <!--  --></l>
   </lg></quote>
  <!-- ONE -->
  <pb xml:id="P73100011" facs="../img/1773-044.pbm"/>
  <!-- PREFACE. xiii -->
  <p><hi rend="sc">One</hi> of the chief improvements, on this edition, is the care taken, in
   arranging the poems in the order of time; ſo as to form a kind of regular hiſtory of the age to
   which they relate. The writer has now reſigned them for ever to their fate. That they have been
   well received by the public, appears from an extenſive ſale; that they ſhall continue to be well
   received, he may venture to prophecy without the gift of that inſpiration, to which poets lay
   claim. Through the medium of verſion upon verſion, they retain, in foreign languages, their
   native character of ſimplicity and energy. Genuine poetry, like gold, loſes little, when properly
   transfuſed ; but when a compoſition cannot bear the teſt of a literal verſion, it is a
   counterfeit which ought not to paſs current. The operation muſt, however, be performed with
   ſkilful hands. A tranſlator, who cannot equal his original, is incapable of expreſſing its
   beauties.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">London</hi>, Aug. 15, 1773 </p>
 </div>
 <!--  -->
 <pb xml:id="P73100012" facs="../img/1773-048.pbm"/>
 <!--   -->
 <div type="contents">
  <head>CONTENTS OF THE FIRST VOLUME.</head>
  <list>
   <item> CATH-LODA,<list>
    <item>Part Firſt — Page <ref target="#P73110001">1</ref></item>
    <item>Part Second, — <ref target="#P73110015">15</ref>;</item>
    <item>Part Third, <ref target="#P731027">27</ref>310</item>
    </list></item>
   <item>COMALA, — — — <ref target="#P73110037">37</ref></item>
   <item>CARRIC-THURA, — — <ref target="#P73110051">51</ref></item>
   <item>CARTHORN, — — — <ref target="#P73110075">75</ref></item>
   <item>OINA-MORUL, — — <ref target="#P73110097">97</ref></item>
   <item>COLNA-DONA, — — <ref target="#P73110105">105</ref></item>
   <item>OITHONA, — — <ref target="#P73110113">113</ref></item>
   <item>CROMA, — — <ref target="#P73110125">125</ref></item>
   <item>CALTHON and COLMAL, — <ref target="#P73110139">139</ref></item>
   <item>The WAR of CAROS, — <ref target="#P73110153">153</ref></item>
   <item>CATHLIN of CLUTHA, — <ref target="#P73110167">167</ref></item>
   <item>SUL-MALLA of LUMON, — <ref target="#P73110181">181</ref></item>
   <item>WAR of INIS-THONA, — <ref target="#P73110193">193</ref></item>
   <item>The SONGS of SELMA, — <ref target="#P73110203">203</ref> </item>
   <!--  -->
   <!-- FINGAL, -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73100013" facs="../img/1773-051.pbm"/>
   <item>
    <!-- CONTENTS. --> FINGAL,<list>
    <item> Book I. — — <ref target="#P7310217">217</ref></item>
    <item>Book II. — — <ref target="#P73110243">243</ref></item>
    <item>Book III. — — <ref target="#P73110261">261</ref></item>
    <item>Book IV. — — <ref target="#P73110281">281</ref></item>
    <item>Book V. — — <ref target="#P73110299">299</ref></item>
    <item>Book VI. — — <ref target="#P73110315">315</ref></item>
    </list></item>
   <item>LATHMON, — — <ref target="#P73110331">331</ref></item>
   <item>DAR-THULA, — — <ref target="#P73110351">351</ref></item>
   <item>DEATH of CUTHULLIN, <ref target="#P73110375">375</ref></item>
   <item>BATTLE of LORA, — — <ref target="#P73110391">391</ref></item>
   <!--  -->
   <!-- CATH- -->
   <!--  -->
  </list>
 </div>
</front>
