<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb xml:id="P73110181" facs="../img/1773-578.pbm"/><front><titlePage><titlePart><title>SUL-MALLA OF LUMON: A POEM.</title></titlePart></titlePage>
  <!--  -->
<!-- N 3 -->
<pb xml:id="P73110182" facs="../img/1773-579.pbm"/>
<!-- Pp - ” -->
 <div><head>ARGUMENT.</head><p> <hi rend="sc">This</hi> poem, which, properly ſpeaking, is a continuation of the laſt, opens with an addreſs to Sul-malla, the daughter of the king of Inis-huna, whom Oſſian met, at the chace, as he returned from the battle ef Rath-col. Sul-malla invites Oſſian and Oſcar to a feaſt, at the reſidence of her father, who was then abſent in the wars. Upon hearing their name and family, ſhe relates an expedition of Fingal into Inis huna. She caſually mentioning Cathmor, chief of Atha, (who then aſſiſted her father againſt his enemies) Oſſian introduces the epiſode of Culgorm and Surandronlo, two Scandinavian kings, in whoſe wars Oſſian himſelf and Cathmor were engaged on oppoſite ſides. The ſtory is imperſect, a part of the original being loſt. Oſſian, warned, in a dream, by the ghoſt of Trenmor, ſets ſail from Inishuna. </p></div> <!--  -->
 <!--  --></front><body>
  
<pb xml:id="P73110183" facs="../img/1773-582.pbm"/>
<!-- ' 183 = ] -->
 <head>SUL-MALLA OF LUMON: A POEM.</head><p><note>
   <p>The expedition of Oſſian to Inis-huna happened a ſhort time before Fingal paſſed over into
    Ireland, to dethrone Cairbar the ſon of Borbar-duthul. Cathmor, the brother of Cairbar, was
    aiding Conmor, king of Inis-huna, in his wars, at the time that Oſſian defeated Duth-carmor, in
    the valley of Rath-col, The poem is more intereſting, that it contains ſo many particulars
    concerning thoſe perſonages, who make ſo great a figure in Temora.</p>
   <p>The exact correſpondence in the manners and cuſtoms of Inis-huna, as here deſcribed, to thoſe
    of Caledonia, leaves no room to doubt, that the inhabitants of both were originally the ſame
    people. Some may allege, that Oſſian might transfer, in his poetical deſcriptions, the manners
    of his own nation to foreigners. This objection is eaſily anſwered. Why has he not done this
    with regard to the inhabitants of Scandinavia? We find the latter very different in their
    cuſtoms and ſuperſtitions from the nations of Britain and Ireland. The Scandinavian manners are
    remarkably barbarous and fierce, and ſeem to mark out a nation much leſs advanced in a ſtate of
    civilization, than the inhabitants of Britain were in the times of Oſſian. </p>
   </note><hi rend="sc">Who</hi> moves ſo ſtately, on Lumon, at the roar of the foamy waters? Her
   hair falls upon her heaving breaſt. White is her arm behind, as ſlow the bends the bow. Why
   <!--  -->
   <!-- dot -->
   <!--  --><!-- N tra 5tcr, --><!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110184" facs="../img/1773-585.pbm"/>
   <!-- i194 SUL-MALLA or LUMON: --> doſt thou wander in deſarts, like a light thro' a cloudy field
   ? The young roes are panting, by their ſecret rocks. Return, thou daughter of kings! the cloudy
   night is near! It was the young branch of green Inis-huna, Sul-malla of blue eyes. She ſent the
   bard from her rock, to bid us to her feaſt. Amidſt the ſong we ſat down, in Cluba's ecchoing
   hall. White moved the hands of Sul-malla, on the trembling ſtrings. Half-heard amidſt the ſound,
   was the name of Atha's king : he that was abſent in battle for her own green land. Nor abſent
   from her ſoul was he; he came midſt her thoughts by night. Ton-thena looked in, from the ſky, and
   ſaw her toſſing arms.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſound of ſhells had ceaſed. Amidſt long locks, Sul-malla roſe. She ſpoke with bended eyes, and aſked of our courſe thro' ſeas ; “for of the kings of men are ye, tall riders of the <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<!-- wave,” -->
<!--  -->
<pb xml:id="P73110185" facs="../img/1773-588.pbm"/>
<!-- A P O E M. if; -->
 wave<note><p> Sul-malla here diſcovers the quality of Oſſian and Oſcar, from their ſtature and ſtately gait. Among nations, not far advanced in civilization, a ſuperior beauty and ſtatelineſs of perſon were inſeparable from nobility of blood. It was from theſe qualities, that thoſe of family were known by ſtrangers, not from tawdry trappings of ſtate injudiciouſly thrown round them. The cauſe of this diſtinguiſhing property, muſt, in ſome meaſure, be aſcribed to their unmixed blood. They had no inducement to intermarry with the vulgar: and no low notions of intereſt made them deviate from their choice, in their own ſphere. In ſtates, where luxury has been long eſtabliſhed, beauty of perſon is, by no means, the characteriſtic of antiquity of family. This muſt be attributed to thoſe enervating vices, which are inſeparable from luxury and wealth. A great family, (to alter a little the words of the hiſtorian) it is true, like a river, becomes conſiderable from the length of its courſe, but, as it rolls on, hereditary diſtempers, as well as property, flow ſucceſively into it. </p></note>.” “Not unknown,” I ſaid, “at his ſtreams is he, the father of our race. Fingal has been heard of at Cluba, blue-eyed daughter of kings. Nor only, at Cona's ſtream, is Oſſian and Oſcar known. Foes trembled at our voice, and ſhrunk in other lands.”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Not</hi> unmarked,” ſaid the maid, “by Sul-malla, is the ſhield of Morven's king. It hangs high, in my father's hall, in memory of the paſt; when Fingal came to Cluba, in the days of other years. Loud roared the boar of Culdarnu, in the midſt of his rocks and woods. Inis-huna ſent her youths, but they failed ; and <!--  -->
<!-- VIrgins -->
<!--  -->
<pb xml:id="P73110186" facs="../img/1773-591.pbm"/>
<!-- 186 SUL-MALLA or LUMON: -->
 virgins wept over tombs. Careleſs went Fingal to Culdarnu. On his ſpear rolled the ſtrength of the woods. He was bright, they ſaid, in his locks, the firſt of mortal men. Nor at the feaſt were heard his words. His deeds paſſed from his ſoul of fire, like the rolling of vapours from the face of the wandering ſun. Not careleſs looked the blue eyes of Cluba on his ſtately ſteps. In white boſoms roſe the king of Selma, in the midſt of their thoughts by night. But the winds bore the ſtranger to the ecchoing vales of his roes. Nor loſt to other lands was he, like a meteor that ſinks in a cloud. He came forth, at times, in his brightneſs, to the diſtant dwelling of foes. His fame came, like the ſound of winds, to Cluba's woody vale<note><p> Too partial to our own times, we are ready to mark out remote antiquity, as the region of
    ignorance and barbariſm. This, perhaps, is extending our prejudices too far, It has been long
    remarked, that knowlege, in a great meaſure, is ſounded on a free intercourſe between mankind ;
    and that the mind is enlarged in proportion to the obſervations it has made upon the manners of
    different men and nations. If we look, with attention, into the hiſtory of Fingal, as delivered
    by Oſſian, we ſhall find that he was not altogether a poor ignorant hunter, confined to the
    narrow corner of an iſland. His expeditions to all parts of Scandinavia, to the north of
    Germany, and the different ſtates of Great Britain and Ireland, were very numerous, and
    performed under ſuch a character, and at ſuch times, as gave him an opportunity to mark the
    undiſguiſed manners of mankind. War and an active life, as they call forth, by turns, all the
    powers of the ſoul, preſent to us the different characters of men: in times of peace and quiet,
    for want of objects to exert them, the powers of the mind lie concealed, in a great meaſure, and
    we ſee only artificial paſſions and manners. It is from this conſideration I conclude, that a
    traveller of penetration could gather more genuine knowlege from a tour of ancient Gaul, than
    from the minuteſt obſervation of all the artificial manners, and elegant refinements of modern
    France. </p></note>.” <!--  -->
<!-- © DARKNESS -->
<!--  -->
<!-- undiſguiſed -->
<!--  -->
<pb xml:id="P73110187" facs="../img/1773-594.pbm"/>
<!-- A P O E M. 185 -->
 “<hi rend="sc">Darkness</hi> dwells in Cluba of harps : the race of kings is diſtant far ; in battle is my father Conmor: and Lormar<note><p> Lormar was the ſon of Conmor, and the brother of Sulmalla. After the death of Conmor, Lormar ſucceeded him in the throne. </p></note> my brother, king of ſtreams. Nor darkening alone are they; a beam, from other lands, is nigh; the friend of ſtrangers<note><p> Cathmor, the ſon of Barbar-duthul. It would appear, from the partiality with which Sul-malla ſpeaks of that hero, that ſhe had ſeen him, previous to his joining her father's army ; tho' tradition poſitively aſſerts, that it was, after his return, that ſhe fell in love with him. </p></note> in Atha, the troubler of the field. High, from their miſty hills, look forth the blue eyes of Erin; for he is far away, young dweller of their ſouls! Nor, harmleſs, white hands of Erin ! is Cathmor in the ſkirts of war; he rolls ten thouſand before him, in his diſtant field.”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Not</hi> unſeen by Oſſian,” I ſaid, “ruſhed Cathmor from his ſtreams, when he poured his <!--  -->
<!-- ſtrength -->
<!--  -->
<pb xml:id="P73110188" facs="../img/1773-597.pbm"/>
<!-- 1832 SUL-MALLA of LUMON: -->
 ſtrength on I-thorno<note><p> I-thorno, ſays tradition, was an iſland of Scandinavia, In it, at a hunting party, met Culgorm and Suran-dronlo, the kings of two neighbouring iſles. They differed about the honour of killing a boar; and a war was kindled between them. From this epiſode we may learn, that the manners of the Scandinavians were much more ſavage and cruel, than thoſe of Britain, It is remarkable, that the names, introduced in this ſtory, are not of Galic original, which circumſtance affords room to ſuppoſe, that it had its ſoundation in true hiſtory. </p></note>, iſle of many waves! In ſtrife met two kings in I-thorno, Culgorm and Suran-dronlo : each from his ecchoing iſle, ſtern hunters of the boar !”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">They</hi> met a boar, at a foamy ſtream : each pierced him with his ſpear. They ſtrove for the fame of the deed; and gloomy battle roſe. From iſle to iſle they ſent a ſpear, broken and ſtained with blood, to call the friends of their fathers, in their ſounding arms. Cathmor came, from Erin, to Culgorm, red-eyed king : I aided Suran-dronlo, in his land of boars.”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">We</hi> ruſhed on either ſide of a ſtream, which roared thro' a blaſted heath. High broken rocks were round, with all their bending trees. Near were two circles of Loda, with the ſtone of power ; where ſpirits deſcended, by night, in dark-red ſtreams of fire. There, mixed with the murmur of waters, roſe the <!--  -->
<!-- 7 yoice -->
<!--  -->
<pb xml:id="P73110189" facs="../img/1773-600.pbm"/>
<!-- A P O E M. 18 -->
 voice of aged men, they called the forms of night, to aid them in their war.”<note><p> From the circumſtance of Oſſian not being preſent at the rites, deſcribed in the preceding paragraph, we may ſuppoſe that he held them in contempt. This difference of ſentiment, with regard to religion, is a ſort of argument, that the Caledonians were not originally a colony of Scandinavians, as ſome have imagined. Concerning ſo remote a period, mere conjecture muſt ſupply the place of argument and poſitive proofs. </p></note> <hi rend="sc">Heedless</hi> I ſtood, with my people, where fell the foamy ſtream from rocks. The moon moved red from the mountain. My ſong, at times, aroſe. Dark, on the other ſide, young Cathmor heard my voice; for he lay, beneath the oak, in all his gleaming arms. Morning came; we ruſhed to fight: from wing to wing is the rolling of ſtrife. They fell, like the thiſtle's head, beneath autumnal winds.</p><p><hi rend="sc">In</hi> armour came a ſtately form : I mixed my ſtrokes with the chief. By turns
   our ſhields are pierced : loud rung our ſteely mails. His helmet fell to the ground. In
   brightneſs ſhone the foe. His eyes, two pleaſant flames, rolled between his wandering locks. I
   knew Cathmor of Atha, and threw my ſpear on earth. Dark, we turned, and ſilent paſſed to mix with
   other foes.” <!--  -->
   <!-- c NOT -->
   <!--  --></p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73110190" facs="../img/1773-603.pbm"/>
   <!-- 190 SUL-MALLA or LUMON: --> “<hi rend="sc">Not</hi> ſo paſſed the ſtriving kings<note>
   <p> Culporm and Suran dronlo. The combat of the kings and their attitude in death are hiphly
    pictureſque, and expreſſive of that ferocity of manners, which diſtinguiſhed the northern
    nations. </p>
   </note>. They, mixed in ecchoing fray ; like the meeting of ghoſts, in the dark wing of winds.
   Thro' either breaſt ruſhed the ſpears ; nor yet lay the foes on earth ! A rock received their
   fall ; half-reclined they lay in death. Each held the lock of his foe; each grimly ſeemed to roll
   his eyes. The ſtream of the rock leapt on their ſhields, and mixed below with blood.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> battle ceaſed in I-thorno. The ſtrangers met in peace: Cathmor from Atha of ſtreams, and Oſſian, king of harps. We placed the dead in earth. Our ſteps were by Runar's bay. With the bounding boat, afar, advanced a ridgy wave. Dark was the rider of ſeas, but a beam of light was there, like the ray of the ſun, in Stromlo's rolling ſmoak. It was the daughter<note><p> Tradition has handed down the name of this princeſs. The bards call her Runo-forlo, which has no
    other ſort of title for being genuine, but its not being of Galic original ; a diſtinction,
    which the bards had not the art to preſerve, when they feigned names for foreigners. The
    highland ſenachies, who very often endeavoured to ſupply the deficiency, they thought they ſound
    in the tales of Oſſian, have given us the continuation of the ſtory of the daughter of
    Suran-dronlo. The cataſtrophe is ſo unnatural, and the circumſtances of it fo ridiculouſly
    pompous, that, for the ſake of the inventors, I ſhall conceal them.</p><p>The wildly beautiful appearance of Runo-forlo, made a deep impreſſion on a chief, ſome ages ago, who was himſelf no contemptible poet. The ſtory is romantic, but not incredible, if we make allowances for the lively imagination of a man of genius. Our chief ſailing, in a ſtorm, along one of the iſlands of Orkney, ſaw a woman, in a boat, near the ſhore, whom he thought, as he expreſſes it himſelf, <hi>as beautiful as a ſudden ray of the ſun, on the dark-heaving deep</hi>. The verſes of Oſſian, on the attitude of Runo-forlo, which was ſo ſimilar to that of the woman in the boat, wrought ſo much on his fancy, that he fell deſperately in love. The winds, however, drove him from the coaſt, and, aſter a few days, he arrived at his reſidence in Scotland. There his paſſion increaſed to ſuch a degree, that two of his friends, fearing the conſequence, ſailed to the Orkneys, to carry to him the objet of his deſire. Upon enquiry they ſoon ſound the nymph, and carried her to the enamoured chief; but mark his ſurprize, when, inſtead <hi>of a ray of the fun</hi>, he ſaw a ſkinny fiſherwoman, more than middle aged, appearing before him. Tradition here ends the ſtory : but it may be eaſily ſuppoſed that the paſſion of the chief ſoon ſubſided. </p></note> of Suran-dronlo, wild in brightened looks. <!--  -->
<!-- Her -->
<!--  -->
<!-- 8 thought -->
<!--  -->
<pb xml:id="P73110191" facs="../img/1773-606.pbm"/>
<!-- A P O E M. 11 -->
 Her eyes were wandering flames, amidſt diſordered locks. Forward is her white arm, with the ſpear ; her high-heaving breaſt is ſeen, white as foamy waves that rife, by turns, amidſt rocks. They are beautiful, but terrible, and mariners call the winds !”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Come</hi>, ye dwellers of Loda!” ſhe ſaid, “come, Carchar, pale in the midſt of
   clouds ! <!--  -->
   <!-- Sluthmor -->
   <!--  -->
   <!-- 3 -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110192" facs="../img/1773-609.pbm"/>
   <!-- 192 SUL-MALLA or LUMON: --> Sluthmor, that ſtrideſt in airy halls ! Corchtur, terrible in
   winds ! Receive, from his daughter's ſpear, the foes of Suran-dronlo. No ſhadow, at his roaring
   ſtreams; no mildly-looking form was he ! When he took up his ſpear, the hawks ſhook their
   ſounding wings: for blood was poured around the ſteps of dark-eyed Suran-dronlo. He lighted me,
   no harmleſs beam, to glitter on his ſtreams. Like meteors, I was bright, but I blaſted the foes
   of Suran-dronlo.”</p><p> * * * *</p><p><hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> unconcerned heard Sul-malla, the praiſe of Cathmor of ſhields. He was within her ſoul, like a fire in ſecret heath, which awakes at the voice of the blaſt, and ſends its beam abroad. Amidſt the ſong removed the daughter of kings, like the voice of a ſummer-breeze; when it lifts the heads of flowers, and curls the lakes and ſtreams. The ruſtling ſound gently ſpreads o'er the vale, foſtly-pleaſing as it ſaddens the ſoul.</p><p>By night came a dream to Oſſian; formleſs ſtood the ſhadow of Trenmor. He ſeemed to ſtrike the dim ſhield, on Selma's ſtreamy rock. I roſe, in my rattling ſteel ; I knew that war was near, before the winds our ſails were ſpread ; when Lumon ſhewed its ſtreams to the morn.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Come</hi> from the watching of night, Malvina, lonely beam ! <!--  -->
<!-- THE -->
<!--  -->
</p>
</body></text>