<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73110193" facs="../img/1773-612.pbm"/>
 <front>
  <titlePage source="NYPL">
   <titlePart><title>THE WAR of INIS-THONA: A POEM. </title></titlePart>
  </titlePage>
   <pb xml:id="P73110194" facs="../img/1773-615.pbm"/>
  <div>
   <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p> Reflections on the poet's youth. An apoſtrophe to Selma. Oſcar obtains leave to go to
    Inis-thona, an iſland of Scandinavia. The mournful ſtory of Argon and Kuro, the two ſons of the
    king of Inis-thona. Oſcar revenges their death, and returns in triumph to Selma. A ſoliloquy by
    the poet himſelf. </p>
  </div>
  <!--  -->
  <!--  -->
 </front>
 <body>
  <pb xml:id="P73110195" facs="../img/1773-618.pbm"/>
  <!-- [195] -->
  <head>THE WAR of INIS-THONA: A POEM.</head>
  <p> <hi rend="sc">Our</hi> youth is like the dream of the hunter on the hill of heath. He ſleeps
   in the mild beams of the ſun ; he awakes amidſt a ſtorm; the red lightning flies around : trees
   ſhake their heads to the wind ! He looks back with joy, on the day of the ſun; and the pleaſant
   dreams of his reſt! When ſhall Oſſian's youth return ? When his ear delight in the ſound of arms
   ? When ſhall I, like Oſcar, travel in the light of my ſteel? Come, with your ſtreams, ye hills of
   Cona ! liſten to the voice of Oſſian. The ſong riſes, like the ſun, in my ſoul. I feel the joys
   of other times !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">I behold</hi> thy towers, O Selma ! the oaks of thy ſhaded wall: thy ſtreams
   ſound in my ear thy heroes gather around. Fingal ſits in the <!--  -->
   <!-- O 2 midſt, -->
   <!--  -->
   <!-- 4 -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110196" facs="../img/1773-621.pbm"/>
   <!-- 196 The WAR of INIS-THONA: --> midſt. He leans on the ſhield of Trenmor: his ſpear ſtands
   againſt the wall ; he liſtens to the ſong of his bards. The deeds of his arm are heard; the
   actions of the king in his youth ! Oſcar had returned from the chace, and heard the hero's
   praiſe. He took the ſhield of Branno<note>
   <p> This is Branno, the father of Everallin, and grandfather to Oſcar; he was of Iriſh
   extraction, and lord of the country round the lake of Lego. His great actions are handed down by
   tradition, and his hoſpitality has paſſed into a proverb. </p></note> from the wall; his eyes
   were filled with tears. Red was the cheek of youth. His voice was trembling, low. My ſpear ſhook
   its bright head in his hand : he ſpoke to Morven's king.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi>! thou king of heroes! Oſſian, next to him in war! ye have fought in
   your youth; your names are renowned in ſong. Oſcar is like the miſt of Cona ; I appear and I
   vaniſh away. The bard will not know my name. The hunter will not ſearch in the heath for my tomb.
   Let me fight, O heroes, in the battles of Inis-Thona. Diſtant is the land of my war! ye ſhall not
   hear of Oſcar's fall ! Some bard may find me there ; ſome bard may give my name to ſong. The
   daughter of the ſtranger ſhall ſee my tomb, and weep over the youth, that came from afar. The
   bard ſhall ſay, at the feaſt, “hear the ſong of Oſcar from the diſtant land !” <!--  -->
   <!-- OscaR,” -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110197" facs="../img/1773-624.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. I 97 --> </p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Oscar</hi>,” replied the king of Morven ; “thou ſhalt fight, ſon of my fame !
   Prepare my dark-boſomed ſhip to carry my hero to Inisthona. Son of my ſon, regard our fame ; thou
   art of the race of renown ! Let not the children of ſtrangers ſay, feeble are the ſons of Morven
   ! Be thou, in battle, a roaring ſtorm : mild as the evening ſun in peace ! Tell, Oſcar, to
   Inisthona's king, that Fingal remembers his youth; when we ſtrove in the combat together, in the
   days of Agandecca.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">They</hi> lifted up the ſounding ſail; the wind whiſtled through the thongs<note>
   <p> Leather thongs were uſed among the Celtic nations, inſtead of ropes. </p></note> of their
   maſts. Waves laſh the oozy rocks: the ſtrength of ocean roars. My ſon beheld, from the wave, the
   land of groves, He ruſhed into Runa's ſounding bay, and ſent his ſword to Annir of ſpears. The
   grey-haired hero roſe, when he ſaw the ſword of Fingal. His eyes were full of tears; he
   remembered his battles in youth. Twice had they lifted the ſpear, before the lovely Agandecca :
   heroes ſtood far diſtant, as if two ſpirits were ſtriving in winds.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">But</hi> now,” began the king, “I am old; the ſword lies uſeleſs in my hall.
   Thou, who <!--  -->
   <!-- O 3 art -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110198" facs="../img/1773-627.pbm"/>
   <!-- 193 The WAR of INIS-THONA: --> art of Morven's race! Annir has ſeen the battle of ſpears ;
   but now he is pale and withered, like the oak of Lano. I have no ſon to meet thee with joy, to
   bring thee to the halls of his fathers. Argon is pale in the tomb, and Ruro is no more. My
   daughter is in the hall of ſtrangers : ſhe longs to behold my tomb. Her ſpouſe ſhakes ten
   thouſand ſpears; he comes<note>
   <p> Cormalo had reſolved on a war againſt his father in law Annir king of Inis-thona, in order to
   deprive him of his kingdom : the injuſtice of his deſigns was ſo much reſented by Fingal, that he
   ſent his grandſon, Oſcar, to the aſſiſtance of Annir. Both armies came ſoon to a battle, in which
   the conduct and valour of Oſcar obtained a compleat victory. An end was put to the war by the
   death of Cormalo, who fell in a ſingle combat, by Oſcar's hand. Thus is the ſtory delivered down
   by tradition ; though the poet, to raiſe the character of his ſon, makes Oſcar himſelf propoſe
   the expedition. </p></note> a cloud of death from Lano. Come, to ſhare the feaſt of Annir, ſon of
   ecchoing Morven !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Three</hi> days they feaſted together; on the fourth, Annir heard the name of
   Oſcar. They rejoiced in the ſhell<note>
   <p> <hi>To rejoice in the ſhell</hi> is a phraſe for feaſting ſumptuouſly and drinking freely.
   </p>
   </note>. They purſued the boars of Runa. Beſide the fount of moſſy ſtones, the weary heroes reſt.
   The tear ſteals in ſecret from Annir: he broke the riſing ſigh. “Here darkly reſt,” the hero
   ſaid, “the children of my youth. This ſtone is the tomb of Ruro; that tree ſounds <!--  -->
   <!-- over -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110199" facs="../img/1773-630.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 199 --> over the grave of Argon. Do ye hear my voice, O my ſons, within your
   narrow houſe ? Or do ye ſpeak in theſe ruſtling leaves, when the winds of the deſart riſe ?”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">King</hi> of Inis-thona,” ſaid Oſcar, “how fell the children of youth? The wild
   boar ruſhes over their tombs, but he does not diſturb their repoſe. They purſue deer<note>
   <p> The notion of Oſſian concerning the ſtate of the deceaſed, was the ſame with that of the
    ancient Greeks and Romans. They imagined that the ſouls purſued, in their ſeparate ſtate, the
    employments and pleaſures of their former life. </p>
   </note> formed of clouds, and bend their airy bow. They ſtill love the ſport of their youth ; and
   mount the wind with joy.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Cormalo</hi>,” replicd the king, “is a chief of ten thouſand ſpears. He dwells
   at the waters of Lano<note>
   <p> Lano was a lake of Scandinavia, remarkable, in the days of Oſſian, for emitting a
    peſtilential vapour in autumn. <quote><hi>And thou, O valiant Duchomar, like the miſt of marſhy
    Lano ; when it ſails ever the plains of autumn, and brings death to the hoſt.</hi> </quote><hi
    rend="sc">Fingal</hi>, B. I. </p>
   </note>, which ſends forth the vapour of death. He came to Runa's ecchoing halls, and ſought the
   honour of the ſpear<note>
   <p> By <hi>the honour of the ſpear</hi> is meant the tournament practiſed among the ancient
    northern nations. </p>
   </note>. The youth was lovely as the firſt beam of the ſun ; few were they who could meet him in
   fight ! My heroes yielded to Cormalo : my daughter was ſeized in his love. <!--  -->
   <!--  -->
   <!-- O 4 Argon -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110200" facs="../img/1773-633.pbm"/>
   <!-- 300 The WAR of INIS-THONA: -->  Argon and Ruro returned from the chace; the tears of their
   pride deſcend : they roll their ſilent eyes on Runa's heroes, who had yielded to a ſtranger.
   Three days they feaſted with Cormalo : on the fourth young Argon fought. But who could fight with
   Argon ! Cormalo is overcome. His heart ſwelled with the grief of pride; he reſolved, in ſecret,
   to behold the death of my ſons? They went to the hills of Runa : they purſued the dark-brown
   hinds. The arrow of Cormalo flew in ſecret ; my children fell in blood. He came to the maid of
   his love ; to Inis-thona's long-haired maid. They fled over the deſart. Annir remained alone.
   Night came on and day appeared; nor Argon's voice, nor Ruro's came. At length their much-loved
   dog was ſeen ; the fleet and bounding Runar. He came into the hall and howled ; and ſeemed to
   look towards the place of their fall. We followed him : we ſound them here : we laid them by this
   moſſy ſtream. This is the haunt of Annir, when the chace of the hinds is paſt. I bend like the
   trunk of an aged oak; my tears for ever flow !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">O Ronnan</hi> !” ſaid the riſing Oſcar, “Ogar king of ſpears! call my heroes to
   my ſide, the ſons of ſtreamy Morven. To-day we go to Lano's water, that ſends forth the vapour of
   <!--  -->
   <!-- death. -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110201" facs="../img/1773-636.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O BE M. 251 --> death. Cormalo will not long rejoice: death is often at the point of our
   ſwords !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">They</hi> came over the deſart like ſtormy clouds, when the winds roll them along
   the heath : their edges are tinged with lightning ; the ecchoing groves foreſee the form! The
   horn of Oſcar's battle is heard ; Lano ſhook over all its waves. The children of the lake
   convened around the ſounding ſhield of Cormalo. Oſcar fought, as he was wont in war. Cormalo fell
   beneath his ſword : the ſons of diſmal Lano fled to their ſecret vales! Oſcar brought the
   daughter of Inis-thona to Annir's ecchoing halls. The face of age is bright with joy ; he bleſt
   the king of ſwords !</p>
  <p>How great was the joy of Oſſian, when he beheld the diſtant fail of his ſon! it was like a
   cloud of light that riſes in the eaſt, when the traveller is ſad in a land unknown; and diſmal
   night, with her ghoſts, is fitting around in ſhades! We brought him, with ſongs, to Selma's
   halls. Fingal ſpread the feaſt of ſhells. A thouſand bards raiſed the name of Oſcar : Morven
   anſwered to the ſound. The daughter of Toſcar was there; her voice was like the harp; when the
   diſtant ſound comes, in the evening, on the foſt-ruſtling breeze of the vale! <!--  -->
   <!-- O LAY -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73110202" facs="../img/1773-639.pbm"/>
   <!-- 202 The WAR of INIS-THONA. --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">O Lay</hi> me, ye that ſee the light, near ſome rock of my hills ! let the thick
   hazels be around, let the ruſtling oak be near. Green be the place of my reſt; let the ſound of
   the diſtant torrent be heard. Daughter of Toſcar, take the harp, and raiſe the lovely ſong of
   Selma ; that ſleep may overtake my ſoul in the midſt of joy ; that the dreams of my youth may
   return, and the days of the mighty Fingal. Selma! I behold thy towers, thy trees, thy ſhaded wall
   ! I ſee the heroes of Morven ; I hear the ſong of bards ! Oſcar lifts the ſword of Cormalo; a
   thouſand youths admire its ſtudded thongs. They look with wonder on my ſon: They admire the
   ſtrength of his arm. They mark the joy of his father's eyes; they long for an equal fame. And ye
   ſhall have your fame, O ſons of ſtreamy Morven! My ſoul is often brightened with ſong; I remember
   the friends of my youth. But ſleep deſcends, in the ſound of the harp! pleaſant dreams begin to
   riſe! Ye ſons of the chace ſtand far diſtant, nor diſturb my reſt. The bard of other times holds
   diſcourſe with his fathers, the chief of the days of old ! Sons of the chace, ſtand far diſtant !
   diſturb not the dreams of Oſſian ! <!--  -->
   <!-- THE -->
   <!--  -->
   <!--  --> </p>
 </body>
</text>