<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73210191" facs="../img/1773-614.pbm"/>

 <front>
  <titlePage source="NYPL">
   <titlePart>BERRATHON: A POEM.</titlePart>
  </titlePage>
  <pb xml:id="P73210192" facs="../img/1773-617.pbm"/>
  <div type="argument">
   <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p> Fingal in his voyage to Lochlin, whither he had been invited by Starno the father of
    Agandecca, touched at Berrathon, an iſland of Scandinavia, where he was kindly entertained by
    Larthmor the petty king of the place, who was a vaſſal of the ſupreme kings of Lochlin. The
    hoſpitality of Larthmor gained him Fingal's friendſhip, which that hero manifeſted, after the
    impriſonment of Larthmor by his own ſon, by ſending Oſſian and Toſcar, the father of Malvina ſo
    often mentioned, to reſcue Larthmor, and to puniſh the unnatural behaviour of Uthal. Uthal was
    handſome, and, by the ladies, much admired. Nina-thoma, the beautiful daughter of Torthoma, a
    neighbouring prince, fell in love and fled with him. He proved unconſtant; for another lady,
    whoſe name is not mentioned, gaining his affections, he confined Nina-thoma to a deſart iſland
    near the coaſt of Berrathon. She was relieved by Oſſian, who, in company with Toſcar, landing on
    Berrathon, defeated the forces of Uthal, and killed him in a ſingle combat. Nina-thoma, whoſe
    love not all the bad behaviour of Uthal could eraſe, hearing of his death, died of grief. In the
    mean time Larthmor is reſtored, and Oſſian and Toſcar return in triumph to Fingal,</p>
   <p>The poem opens with an elegy on the death of Malvina the daughter of Toſcar, and cloſes with
    preſages of Oſſian's death. </p>
  </div>

 </front>
 <body>
  <pb xml:id="P73210193" facs="../img/1773-620.pbm"/>
  <!-- [193] -->
  <head>BERRATHON: A P O E M.</head>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Bend</hi> thy blue courſe, O ſtream, round the narrow plain of<note>
   <p> Lutha, <hi>ſwift ſtream</hi>. </p>
   </note> Lutha. Let the green woods hang over it, from their hills: the ſun look on it at noon.
   The thiſtle is there on its rock, and ſhakes its beard to the wind. The flower hangs its heavy
   head, waving, at times, to the gale. “Why doſt thou awake me, O gale,” it ſeems to ſay, “I am
   covered with the drops of heaven? The time of my fading is near, the blaſt that ſhall ſcatter my
   leaves. Tomorrow ſhall the traveller come ; he that ſaw me in my beauty ſhall come. His eyes will
   ſearch the field, but they will not find me?” So ſhall they ſearch in vain, for the voice of
   Cona, after it has failed in the field. The hunter ſhall come forth in the morning, and the voice
   of my harp <!-- Vol. II. O şhall -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210194" facs="../img/1773-623.pbm"/>
   <!-- 194. BERRATHON: --> ſhall not be heard. “Where is the ſon of car-borne Fingal ?” The tear
   will be on his cheek ! Then come thou, O Malvina, with all thy muſic, come. Lay Oſſian in the
   plain of Lutha : let his tomb riſe in the lovely field.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Malvina</hi>! where art thou, with thy ſongs, with the ſoft ſound of thy ſteps? Son<note>
   <p> His father was one of Fingal's principal bards, and he had a poetical genius. </p>
   </note> of Alpin art thou near ? where is the daughter of Toſcar? “I paſſed, O ſon of Fingal, by
   Tor-lutha's moſſy walls. The ſmoke of the hall was ceaſed. Silence was among the trees of the
   hill. The voice of the chace was over. I ſaw the daughters of the bow. I aſked about Malvina, but
   they anſwered not. They turned their faces away : thin darkneſs covered their beauty. They were
   like ſtars, on a rainy hill, by night, each looking faintly thro' her miſt.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Pleasant</hi><note>
   <p> Oſſian ſpeaks. He calls Malvina a beam of light, and continues the metaphor throughout the
    paragraph. </p>
   </note> be thy reſt, O lovely beam! ſoon haſt thou ſet on our hills ! The ſteps of thy departure
   were ſtately, like the moon on the blue, trembling wave. But thou haſt left us in darkneſs, firſt
   of the maids of Lutha ! We ſit, at the rock, and there is no voice; no light but <!-- A th -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210195" facs="../img/1773-626.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 195 --> the meteor of fire ! Soon haſt thou ſet, O Malvina, daughter of generous
   Toſcar ! But thou riſeſt like the beam of the eaſt, among the ſpirits of thy friends, where they
   ſit, in their ſtormy halls, the chambers of the thunder ! A cloud hovers over Cona. Its blue
   curling ſides are high. The winds are beneath it, with their wings. Within it is the dwelling<note>
   <p> The deſcription of this ideal palace of Fingal is agreeable to the notions of thoſe times,
    concerning the ſtate of the deceaſed, who were ſuppoſed to purſue, after death, the pleaſures
    and employments of their former life. The ſituation of the Celtic heroes, in their ſeparate
    ſtate, if not entirely happy, is more agreeable, than the notions of the antient Greeks
    concerning their departed heroes. </p>
   </note> of Fingal. There the hero ſits in darkneſs. His airy ſpear is in his hand. His ſhield
   half covered with clouds, is like the darkened moon ; when one half ſtill remains in the wave,
   and the other looks ſickly on the field !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">His</hi> friends ſit around the King, on miſt ! They hear the ſongs of Ullin : he
   ſtrikes the half-viewleſs harp. He raiſes the feeble voice. The leſſer heroes, with a thouſand
   meteors, light the airy hall. Malvina riſes, in the midſt; a bluſh is on her cheek. She beholds
   the unknown faces of her fathers. She turns aſide her humid eyes. “Art thou come ſo ſoon ?” ſaid
   Fingal, “daughter of generous Toſcar. <!-- O2 neşs -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210196" facs="../img/1773-629.pbm"/>
   <!-- 196 BERRATHON: --> Sadneſs dwells in the halls of Lutha. My aged ſon<note>
   <p> Oſſian who had a great friendſhip for Malvina, both on account of her love for his ſon Oſcar,
    and her attention to himſelf. </p>
   </note> is ſad ! I hear the breeze of Cona, that was wont to lift thy heavy locks. It comes to
   the hall, but thou art not there. Its voice is mournful among the arms of thy fathers ! Go, with
   thy ruſtling wing, O breeze! ſigh on Malvina's tomb. It riſes yonder beneath the rock, at the
   blue ſtream of Lutha. The maids<note>
   <p> That is, the young virgins who ſung the funeral elegy over her tomb. </p>
   </note> are departed to their place. Thou alone, O breeze, mourneſt there!”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> who comes from the duſky weſt, ſupported on a cloud? A ſmile is on his
   grey, watry face. His locks of miſt fly on wind. He bends forward on his airy ſpear. It is thy
   father, Malvina ! “Why ſhineft thou, ſo ſoon, on our clouds,” he ſays, “O lovely light of Lutha!
   But thou wert ſad, my daughter. Thy friends had paſſed away. The ſons of little men<note>
   <p> Tradition is entirely ſilent concerning what paſſed in the north, immediately after the death
    of Fingal and all his heroes ; by which it would ſeem that the actions of their ſucceſſors were
    not to be compared to thoſe of the renowned Fingalians. </p>
   </note> were in the hall. None remained of the heroes, but Oſſian king of ſpears !” <!-- AND -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210197" facs="../img/1773-632.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 197 --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">And</hi> doſt thou remember Oſſian, car-borne Toſcar<note>
   <p>Toſcar was the ſon of that Conloch, who was alſo father to the lady, whoſe unfortunate death
    is related in the laſt epiſode of the ſecond book of Fingal. </p>
   </note>, ſon of Conloch ? The battles of our youth were many. Our ſwords went together to the
   field. They ſaw us coming like two falling rocks. The ſons of the ſtranger fled. “There come the
   warriors of Cona !” they ſaid. “Their ſteps are in the paths of the flying!” Draw near, ſon of
   Alpin, to the ſong of the aged. The deeds of other times are in my ſoul. My memory beams on the
   days that are paſt. On the days of mighty Toſcar, when our path was in the deep. Draw near, ſon
   of Alpin, to the laſt ſound of the voice of Cona !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> king of Morven commanded. I raiſed my ſails to the wind. Toſcar chief of
   Lutha ſtood at my ſide. I roſe on the dark-blue wave, Our courſe was to ſea-ſurrounded Berrathon<note>
   <p> Barrathón, <hi>a promontory in the midſt of waves</hi>, </p>
   </note>, the iſle of many ſtorms. There dwelt, with his locks of age, the ſtately ſtrength of
   Larthmor. Larthmor, who ſpread the feaſt of ſhells to Fingal, when he went to Starno's halls, in
   the days of Agandecca. But when the chief was old, the pride of his ſon aroſe ; the pride of
   fair-haired Uthal, the love of a thouſand maids. He bound <!-- Og © re -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210198" facs="../img/1773-635.pbm"/>
   <!-- 198 BERRATHON: --> the aged Larthmor, and dwelt in his ſounding halls !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Long</hi> pined the king in his cave, beſide his rolling ſea. Day did not come to
   his dwelling ; nor the burning oak by night. But the wind of ocean was there, and the parting
   beam of the moon. The red ſtar looked on the king, when it trembled on the weſtern wave. Snitho
   came to Selma's hall : Snitho the friend of Larthmor's youth. He told of the king of Berrathon :
   the wrath of Fingal aroſe. Thrice he aſſumed the ſpear, reſolved to ſtretch his hand to Uthal.
   But the memory<note>
   <p> The meaning is, that Fingal remembered his own great actions, and conſequently would not
    ſully them by engaging in a petty war againſt Uthal, who was ſo far his inferior in valour and
    power. </p>
   </note> of his deeds roſe before the king. He ſent his ſon and Tofcar. Our joy was great on the
   rolling ſea. We often half-unſheathed our ſwords. For never before had we fought alone, in
   battles of the ſpear.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Night</hi> came down on the ocean. The winds departed on their wings. Cold and
   pale is the moon. The red ſtars lift their heads on high. Our courſe is ſlow along the coaſt of
   Berrathon. The white waves tumble on the rocks. “What voice is that,” ſaid Toſcar, “which comes
   between the ſounds of the waves? It is ſoft but <!-- mournful, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210199" facs="../img/1773-638.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 199 --> mournful, like the voice of departed bards. But I behold a maid<note>
   <p> Nina-thoma, the daughter of Torth'ma, who had been confined to a deſart iſland by her lover
    Uthal. </p>
   </note>. She ſits on the rock alone. Her head bends on her arm of ſnow. Her dark hair is in the
   wind. Hear, ſon of Fingal, her ſong, it is ſmooth as the gliding ſtream.” We came to the ſilent
   bay, and heard the maid of night.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">How</hi> long will ye roll around me, blue-tumbling waters of ocean ? My
   dwelling was not always in caves, nor beneath the whiſtling tree. The feaſt was ſpread in
   Torthóma's hall. My father delighted in my voice. The youths beheld me in the ſteps of my
   lovelineſs. They bleſſed the dark-haired Nina-thoma. It was then thou didſt come, O Uthal ! like
   the ſun of heaven ! The ſouls of the virgins are thine, ſon of generous Larthmor ! But why doſt
   thou leave me alone, in the midſt of roaring waters? Was my ſoul dark with thy death? Did my
   white hand lift the ſword ? Why then haſt thou left me alone, king of high Finthormo<note>
   <p> Finthormo, the palace of Uthal. The names in this epiſode are not of a Celtic original. </p>
   </note> !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> tear ſtarted from my eye, when I heard the voice of the maid. I ſtood
   before her in my arms. I ſpoke the words of peace ! “Lovely <!-- O4 dweller -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210200" facs="../img/1773-641.pbm"/>
   <!-- 200 BERRATHON: --> dweller of the cave! what ſigh is in thy breaſt ? Shall Oſſian lift his
   ſword in thy preſence, the deſtruction of thy foes? Daughter of Torthoma, riſe. I have heard the
   words of thy grief. The race of Morven are around thee, who never injured the weak. Come to our
   dark-boſomed ſhip! thou brighter than that ſetting moon ! Our courſe is to the rocky Berrathon,
   to the ecchoing walls of Finthormo.” She came in her beauty ; ſhe came with all her lovely ſteps.
   Silent joy brightened in her face; as when the ſhadows fly from the field of ſpring ; the
   blue-ſtream is rolling in brightneſs, and the green buſh bends over its courſe !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> morning roſe with its beams. We came to Rothma's bay. A boar ruſhed from
   the wood : my ſpear pierced his ſide, and he fell. I rejoiced over the blood<note>
   <p> Oſſian might have thought that his killing a boar on his firſt landing in Berrathon, was a
    good omen of his future ſucceſs in that iſland. The preſent Highlanders look, with a degree of
    ſuperſtition, upon the ſucceſs of their firſt action, after they have engaged in any deſperate
    undertaking. </p>
   </note>. I foreſaw my growing fame. But now the ſound of Uthal's train came, from the high
   Finthormo. They ſpread over the heath to the chace of the boar. Himſelf comes ſlowly on, in the
   pride of his ſtrength. He lifts two pointed ſpears. On his ſide is the hero's <!-- şword. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210201" facs="../img/1773-644.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M, 201 --> ſword. Three youths carry his poliſhed bows. The bounding of five dogs is
   before him. His heroes move on, at a diſtance, admiring the ſteps of the king. Stately was the
   ſon of Larthmor ! but his ſoul was dark! Dark as the troubled face of the moon, when it foretels
   the ſtorms !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">We</hi> roſe on the heath before the king. He ſtopt in the midſt of his courſe.
   His heroes gathered around. A gray-haired bard advanced. “Whence are the ſons of the ſtrangers !”
   began the bard of ſong. “The children of the unhappy come to Berrathon; to the ſword of car-borne
   Uthal. He ſpreads no feaſt in his hall. The blood of ſtrangers is on his ſtreams. If from Selma's
   walls ye come, from the moſſy walls of Fingal, chuſe three youths to go to your king to tell of
   the fall of his people. Perhaps the hero may come and pour his blood on Uthal's ſword. So ſhall
   the fame of Finthormo ariſe, like the growing tree of the vale!”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Never</hi> will it riſe, O bard,” I ſaid in the pride of my wrath. “He would
   ſhrink from the preſence of Fingal, whofe eyes are the flames of death. The ſon of Comhal comes,
   and kings vaniſh before him. They are rolled together, like miſt, by the breath of his rage.
   Shall three tell to Fingal, that his people fell? <!-- Yes! -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210202" facs="../img/1773-647.pbm"/>
   <!-- 202 BERRATHON: --> Yes ! they may tell it, bard ! but his people ſhall fall with fame !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">I stood</hi> in the darkneſs of my ſtrength. Toſcar drew his ſword at my ſide.
   The foe came on like a ſtream. The mingled ſound of death aroſe. Man took man, ſhield met ſhield
   ; ſteel mixed its beams with ſteel. Darts hiſs thro' air. Spears ring on mails. Swords on broken
   bucklers bound. As the noiſe of an aged grove beneath the roaring wind, when a thouſand ghoſts
   break the trees by night, ſuch was the din of arms! But Uthal fell beneath my ſword. The ſons of
   Berrathon fled. It was then I ſaw him in his beauty, and the tear hung in my eye! “Thou art fallen<note>
   <p> To mourn over the fall of their enemies, was a practice univerſal among the Celtic heroes
    This is more agreeable to humanity, than the ſhameful inſulting of the dead, ſo common in Homer,
    and after him, ſervilely copied by all his imitators, the humane Virgil not excepted, who have
    been more ſucceſsful in borrowing the imperfections of that great poet, than in their imitations
    of his beauties. </p>
   </note>, young tree,” I ſaid, “with all thy beauty round thee. Thou art fallen on thy plains, and
   the field is bare. The winds come from the deſart! there is no ſound in thy leaves ! Lovely art
   thou in death, ſon of car-borne Larthmor.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Nina-thoma</hi> ſat on the ſhore. She heard the ſound of battle. She turned her
   red eyes on <!-- Lethmal, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210203" facs="../img/1773-650.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 203 --> Lethmal, the gray-haired bard of Selma. He alone had remained on the
   coaſt, with the daughter of Torthoma, “Son of the times of old !” ſhe ſaid, “I hear the noiſe of
   death. Thy friends have met with Uthal and the chief is low ! O that I had remained on the rock,
   incloſed with the tumbling waves! Then would my ſoul be ſad, but his death would not reach my
   ear. Art thou fallen on thy heath, O ſon of high Finthormo ! Thou didſt leave me on a rock, but
   my ſoul was full of thee. Son of high Finthormo ! art thou fallen on thy heath ?”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">She</hi> roſe pale in her tears. She ſaw the bloody ſhield of Uthal. She ſaw it
   in Oſſian's hand. Her ſteps were diſtracted on the heath. She flew. She found him. She fell. Her
   ſoul came forth in a ſigh. Her hair is ſpread on his face. My burſting tears deſcend. A tomb
   aroſe on the unhappy. My ſong of woe was heard. “Reſt, hapleſs children of youth! Reſt at the
   noiſe of that moſſy ſtream! The virgins will ſee your tomb, at the chace, and turn away their
   weeping eyes. Your fame will be in ſong. The voice of the harp will be heard in your praiſe. The
   daughters of Selma ſhall hear it: your renown ſhall be in other lands. Reſt, children of youth,
   at the noiſe of the moſſy ſtream.” <!-- Two -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210204" facs="../img/1773-653.pbm"/>
   <!-- 204 BERRATHON: --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Two</hi> days we remained on the coaſt. The heroes of Berrathon convened. We
   brought Larthmor to his halls. The feaſt of ſhells is ſpread. The joy of the aged was great. He
   looked to the arms of his fathers. The arms which he left in his hall, when the pride of Uthal
   roſe. We were renowned before Larthmor. He bleſſed the chiefs of Morven. He knew not that his ſon
   was low, the ſtately ſtrength of Uthal ! They had told, that he had retired to the woods, with
   the tears of grief. They had told it, but he was ſilent in the tomb of Rothma's heath.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the fourth day we raiſed our ſails, to the roar of the northern wind.
   Larthmor came to the coaſt. His bards exalted the ſong. The joy of the king was great, he looked
   to Rothma's gloomy heath. He ſaw the tomb of his ſon. The memory of Uthal roſe. “Who of my
   heroes,” he ſaid, “lies there? he ſeems to have been of the Kings of men. Was he renowned in my
   halls, before the pride of Uthal roſe ?” Ye are ſilent, ſons of Berrathon! is the king of heroes
   low ? My heart melts for thee, O Uthal ! though thy hand was againſt thy father. O that I had
   remained in the cave! that my ſon had dwelt in Finthormo! I might have heard the <!-- tread -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210205" facs="../img/1773-656.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 205 --> tread of his feet, when he went to the chace of the boar. I might have
   heard his voice on the blaſt of my cave. Then would my ſoul be glad : but now darkneſs dwells in
   my halls.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were my deeds, ſon of Alpin, when the arm of my youth was ſtrong. Such<note>
   <p> Oſſian ſpeaks. </p>
   </note> the actions of Toſcar, the car-borne ſon of Conloch. But Toſcar is on his flying cloud. I
   am alone at Lutha. My voice is like the laſt ſound of the wind, when it forfakes the woods. But
   Oſſian ſhall not be long alone. He fees the miſt that ſhall receive his ghoſt. He beholds the
   miſt that ſhall form his robe, when he appears on his hills. The ſons of feeble men ſhall behold
   me, and admire the ſtature of the chiefs of old. They ſhall creep to their caves. They ſhall look
   to the ſky with fear: for my ſteps ſhall be in the clouds. Darkneſs ſhall roll on my ſide.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Lead</hi>, ſon of Alpin, lead the aged to his woods. The winds begin to riſe. The
   dark wave of the lake reſounds. Bends there not a tree from Mora with its branches bare? It
   bends, ſon of Alpin, in the ruſtling blaſt. My harp hangs on a blaſted branch. The ſound of its
   ſtrings is mournful. Does the wind touch thee, O harp, or is it ſome paſſing ghoſt! It is the
   hand of Malvina! Bring me the harp, <!-- şn -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210206" facs="../img/1773-659.pbm"/>
   <!-- 206 BERRATHON: --> ſon of Alpin. Another ſong ſhall riſe. My ſoul ſhall depart in the ſound.
   My fathers ſhall hear it in their airy hall. Their dim faces ſhall hang, with joy, from their
   clouds; and their hands receive their ſon. The aged oak bends over the ſtream. It ſighs with all
   its moſs. The withered fern whiſtles near, and mixes, as it waves, with Oſſian's hair.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Strike</hi> the harp and raiſe the ſong: be near, with all your wings, ye winds.
   Bear the mournful ſound away to Fingal's airy hall. Bear it to Fingal's hall, that he may hear
   the voice of his ſon. The voice of him that praiſed the mighty !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">The</hi> blaſt of north opens thy gates, O king. I behold thee ſitting on miſt,
   dimly gleaming in all thine arms. Thy form now is not the terror of the valiant. It is like a
   watery cloud ; when we ſee the ſtars behind it, with their weeping eyes. Thy ſhield is the aged
   moon : thy ſword a vapour half-kindled with fire. Dim and feeble is the chief, who travelled in
   brightneſs before ! But thy ſteps<note>
   <p> This deſcription of the power of Fingal over the winds and ſtorms, and the image of his
    taking the ſun, and hiding him in the clouds, do not correſpond with the preceding paragraph,
    where he is repreſented as a feeble ghoſt, and no more the <hi rend="sc">terror of the
    valiant</hi> ; but it agrees with the notion of the times concerning the ſouls of the deceaſed,
    who, it was ſuppoſed, had the command of the winds and ſtorms, but took no concern in the
    affairs of men. </p>
   </note> are on the winds of the <!-- deşart. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210207" facs="../img/1773-662.pbm"/>
   <!-- A PO E M. 207 --> deſart, The ſtorms are darkening in thy hand. Thou takeſt the ſun in thy
   wrath, and hideſt him in thy clouds. The ſons of little men are afraid. A thouſand ſhowers
   deſcend. But when thou comeſt forth in thy mildneſs ; the gale of the morning is near thy courſe.
   The ſun laughs in his blue fields. The grey ſtream winds in its vale, The buſhes ſhake their
   green heads in the wind. The roes bound towards the deſart.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">There</hi> is a murmur in the heath ! the ſtormy winds abate! ] hear the voice
   of Fingal. Long has it been abſent from mine ear ! “Come, Oſſian, come away,” he ſays. “Fingal
   has received his fame. We paſſed away, like flames that had ſhone for a ſeaſon. Our departure was
   in renown. Though the plains of our battles are dark and ſilent ; our fame is in the ſour grey
   ſtones. The voice of Oſſian has been heard. The harp has been ſtrung in Selma. “Come Oſſian, come
   away,” he ſays, “come, fly with thy fathers on clouds.” I come, I come, thou king of men ! The
   life of Oſſian fails. I begin to vaniſh on Cona. My ſteps are not ſeen in Selma. Beſide the ſtone
   of Mora I ſhall fall aſleep. The winds whiſtling in my grey hair, ſhall not awaken me. Depart on
   thy wings, O wind : thou canſt not diſturb the reſt of the bard. <!-- I be -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210208" facs="../img/1773-665.pbm"/>
   <!-- 208 BERRATHON: --> The night is long, but his eyes are heavy, Depart, thou ruſtling
   blaſt.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">But</hi> why art thou ſad, ſon of Fingal ? Why grows the cloud of thy ſoul ? The
   chiefs of other times are departed. They have gone without their fame. The ſons of future years
   ſhall paſs away. Another race ſhall ariſe. The people are like the waves of ocean : like the
   leaves of woody Morven, they paſs away in the ruſtling blaſt, and other leaves lift their green
   heads on high.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Did</hi> thy beauty laſt, O Ryno<note>
   <p> Ryno, the ſon of Fingal, who was killed in Ireland, in the war againſt Swaran, was remarkable
    for the beauty of his perſon, his ſwiftneſs and great exploits. Minvâne, the daughter of Morni,
    and ſiſter to Gaul, was in love with Ryno. Her lamentation over her lover follows.</p>
   <quote>
    <p><hi rend="sc">She</hi> bluſhing ſad, from Morven's rocks, bends over the darkly-rolling ſea.
     She ſees the youth in all their arms,. Where, Kyno, where art thou? </p>
    <p>Our dark looks told that he was low ! That pale the hero flew on clouds! That in the graſs of
     Morven's hills, his feeble voice was heard in wind!</p>
    <p>And is the ſon of Fingal fallen on Ullin's moſſy plains? Strong was the arm that vanquiſhed
     him! Ah me! I am alone !</p>
    <p>Alone I ſhall not be, ye winds! that lift my dark-brown hair. My ſighs ſhall not long mix
     with your ſtream; for I muſt ſleep with Ryno.</p>
    <p>I ſee thee not, with beauty's ſteps, returning from the chace. The night is round Minvâne's
     love. Dark ſilence dwells with Ryno.</p>
    <p>Where are thy dogs, and where thy bow ? Thy ſhield that was ſo ſtrong ? Thy ſword like
     heaven's deſcending fire ? The bloody ſpear of Ryno ?</p>
    <p>I ſee them mixed in thy deep ſhip; I ſee them ſtained with blood. No arms are in thy narrow
     hall, O darkly-dwelling Ryno!</p>
    <p>When will the morning come, and ſay, “ariſe, thou king of ſpears! ariſe, the hunters are
     abroad. The hinds are near thee, Ryno!”</p>
    <p>Away, thou fair-haired morning, away! the ſlumbering king hears thee not! The hinds bound
     over his narrow tomb ; for death dwells round young Ryno.</p>
    <p>But I will tread ſoftly, my king! and ſteal to the bed of thy repoſe. Minvâne will lie in
     ſilence; nor diſturb the ſlumbering Ryno.</p>
    <p>The maids ſhall ſeek me; but they ſhall not find me : they ſhall follow my departure with
     ſongs. But I ſhall not hear you, O maids: I ſleep with fair-haired Ryno. </p>
   </quote>
   </note>? Stood the ſtrength of car-borne Oſcar? Fingal himſelf <!-- departed. -->
   <!-- I şee -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210209" facs="../img/1773-668.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 209 --> departed. The halls of his fathers forgot his ſteps. Shalt thou then
   remain, thou aged bard! when the mighty have failed ? But my fame ſhall remain, and grow like the
   oak of Morven ; which lifts its broad head to the ſtorm, and rejoices in the courſe of the wind ! </p>
  <!-- Vol. II. P -->
  <pb xml:id="P73210210" facs="../img/1773-671.pbm"/>

 </body>
</text>
