<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73210191" facs="../img/1773-614.pbm"/>

 <front>
  <titlePage source="NYPL">
   <titlePart>BERRATHON: A POEM.</titlePart>
  </titlePage>
  <pb xml:id="P73210192" facs="../img/1773-617.pbm"/>
  <div>
   <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p> Fingal in his voyage to Lochlin, whither he had been invited by Starno the father of
    Agandecca, touched at Berrathon, an işland of Scandinavia, where he was kindly entertained by
    Larthmor the petty king of the place, who was a vaşşal of the şupreme kings of Lochlin. The
    hoşpitality of Larthmor gained him Fingal's friendşhip, which that hero manifeşted, after the
    imprişonment of Larthmor by his own şon, by şending Oşşian and Toşcar, the father of Malvina şo
    often mentioned, to reşcue Larthmor, and to punişh the unnatural behaviour of Uthal. Uthal was
    handşome, and, by the ladies, much admired. Nina-thoma, the beautiful daughter of Torthoma, a
    neighbouring prince, fell in love and fled with him. He proved unconştant; for another lady,
    whoşe name is not mentioned, gaining his affections, he confined Nina-thoma to a deşart işland
    near the coaşt of Berrathon. She was relieved by Oşşian, who, in company with Toşcar, landing on
    Berrathon, defeated the forces of Uthal, and killed him in a şingle combat. Nina-thoma, whoşe
    love not all the bad behaviour of Uthal could eraşe, hearing of his death, died of grief. In the
    mean time Larthmor is reştored, and Oşşian and Toşcar return in triumph to Fingal,</p>
   <p>The poem opens with an elegy on the death of Malvina the daughter of Toşcar, and cloşes with
    preşages of Oşşian's death. </p>
  </div>

 </front>
 <body>
  <pb xml:id="P73210193" facs="../img/1773-620.pbm"/>
  <!-- [193] -->
  <head>BERRATHON: A P O E M.</head>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Bend</hi> thy blue courşe, O ştream, round the narrow plain of<note>
   <p> Lutha, <hi>şwift ştream</hi>. </p>
   </note> Lutha. Let the green woods hang over it, from their hills: the şun look on it at noon.
   The thiştle is there on its rock, and şhakes its beard to the wind. The flower hangs its heavy
   head, waving, at times, to the gale. “Why doşt thou awake me, O gale,” it şeems to şay, “I am
   covered with the drops of heaven? The time of my fading is near, the blaşt that şhall şcatter my
   leaves. Tomorrow şhall the traveller come ; he that şaw me in my beauty şhall come. His eyes will
   şearch the field, but they will not find me?” So şhall they şearch in vain, for the voice of
   Cona, after it has failed in the field. The hunter şhall come forth in the morning, and the voice
   of my harp <!-- Vol. II. O şhall -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210194" facs="../img/1773-623.pbm"/>
   <!-- 194. BERRATHON: --> şhall not be heard. “Where is the şon of car-borne Fingal ?” The tear
   will be on his cheek ! Then come thou, O Malvina, with all thy muşic, come. Lay Oşşian in the
   plain of Lutha : let his tomb rişe in the lovely field.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Malvina</hi>! where art thou, with thy şongs, with the şoft şound of thy şteps?
   Son<note>
   <p> His father was one of Fingal's principal bards, and he had a poetical genius. </p> </note> of
   Alpin art thou near ? where is the daughter of Toşcar? “I paşşed, O şon of Fingal, by Tor-lutha's
   moşşy walls. The şmoke of the hall was ceaşed. Silence was among the trees of the hill. The voice
   of the chace was over. I şaw the daughters of the bow. I aşked about Malvina, but they anşwered
   not. They turned their faces away : thin darkneşs covered their beauty. They were like ştars, on
   a rainy hill, by night, each looking faintly thro' her mişt.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Pleasant</hi><note>
   <p> Oşşian şpeaks. He calls Malvina a beam of light, and continues the metaphor throughout the
   paragraph. </p> </note> be thy reşt, O lovely beam! şoon haşt thou şet on our hills ! The şteps
   of thy departure were ştately, like the moon on the blue, trembling wave. But thou haşt left us
   in darkneşs, firşt of the maids of Lutha ! We şit, at the rock, and there is no voice; no light
   but <!-- A th -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210195" facs="../img/1773-626.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 195 --> the meteor of fire ! Soon haşt thou şet, O Malvina, daughter of generous
   Toşcar ! But thou rişeşt like the beam of the eaşt, among the şpirits of thy friends, where they
   şit, in their ştormy halls, the chambers of the thunder ! A cloud hovers over Cona. Its blue
   curling şides are high. The winds are beneath it, with their wings. Within it is the
   dwelling<note>
   <p> The deşcription of this ideal palace of Fingal is agreeable to the notions of thoşe times,
   concerning the ştate of the deceaşed, who were şuppoşed to purşue, after death, the pleaşures and
   employments of their former life. The şituation of the Celtic heroes, in their şeparate ştate, if
   not entirely happy, is more agreeable, than the notions of the antient Greeks concerning their
   departed heroes. </p> </note> of Fingal. There the hero şits in darkneşs. His airy şpear is in
   his hand. His şhield half covered with clouds, is like the darkened moon ; when one half ştill
   remains in the wave, and the other looks şickly on the field !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">His</hi> friends şit around the King, on mişt ! They hear the şongs of Ullin : he
   ştrikes the half-viewleşs harp. He raişes the feeble voice. The leşşer heroes, with a thouşand
   meteors, light the airy hall. Malvina rişes, in the midşt; a bluşh is on her cheek. She beholds
   the unknown faces of her fathers. She turns aşide her humid eyes. “Art thou come şo şoon ?” şaid
   Fingal, “daughter of generous Toşcar. <!-- O2 neşs -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210196" facs="../img/1773-629.pbm"/>
   <!-- 196 BERRATHON: --> Sadneşs dwells in the halls of Lutha. My aged şon<note>
   <p> Oşşian who had a great friendşhip for Malvina, both on account of her love for his şon Oşcar,
    and her attention to himşelf. </p>
   </note> is şad ! I hear the breeze of Cona, that was wont to lift thy heavy locks. It comes to
   the hall, but thou art not there. Its voice is mournful among the arms of thy fathers ! Go, with
   thy ruştling wing, O breeze! şigh on Malvina's tomb. It rişes yonder beneath the rock, at the
   blue ştream of Lutha. The maids<note>
   <p> That is, the young virgins who şung the funeral elegy over her tomb. </p>
   </note> are departed to their place. Thou alone, O breeze, mourneşt there!”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">But</hi> who comes from the duşky weşt, şupported on a cloud? A şmile is on his
   grey, watry face. His locks of mişt fly on wind. He bends forward on his airy şpear. It is thy
   father, Malvina ! “Why şhineft thou, şo şoon, on our clouds,” he şays, “O lovely light of Lutha!
   But thou wert şad, my daughter. Thy friends had paşşed away. The şons of little men<note>
   <p> Tradition is entirely şilent concerning what paşşed in the north, immediately after the death
   of Fingal and all his heroes ; by which it would şeem that the actions of their şucceşşors were
   not to be compared to thoşe of the renowned Fingalians. </p> </note> were in the hall. None
   remained of the heroes, but Oşşian king of şpears !” <!-- AND -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210197" facs="../img/1773-632.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 197 --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">And</hi> doşt thou remember Oşşian, car-borne Toşcar<note>
   <p>Toşcar was the şon of that Conloch, who was alşo father to the lady, whoşe unfortunate death
   is related in the laşt epişode of the şecond book of Fingal. </p> </note>, şon of Conloch ? The
   battles of our youth were many. Our şwords went together to the field. They şaw us coming like
   two falling rocks. The şons of the ştranger fled. “There come the warriors of Cona !” they şaid.
   “Their şteps are in the paths of the flying!” Draw near, şon of Alpin, to the şong of the aged.
   The deeds of other times are in my şoul. My memory beams on the days that are paşt. On the days
   of mighty Toşcar, when our path was in the deep. Draw near, şon of Alpin, to the laşt şound of
   the voice of Cona !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> king of Morven commanded. I raişed my şails to the wind. Toşcar chief of
   Lutha ştood at my şide. I roşe on the dark-blue wave, Our courşe was to şea-şurrounded
   Berrathon<note>
   <p> Barrathón, <hi>a promontory in the midşt of waves</hi>, </p> </note>, the işle of many
   ştorms. There dwelt, with his locks of age, the ştately ştrength of Larthmor. Larthmor, who
   şpread the feaşt of şhells to Fingal, when he went to Starno's halls, in the days of Agandecca.
   But when the chief was old, the pride of his şon aroşe ; the pride of fair-haired Uthal, the love
   of a thouşand maids. He bound <!-- Og © re -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210198" facs="../img/1773-635.pbm"/>
   <!-- 198 BERRATHON: --> the aged Larthmor, and dwelt in his şounding halls !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Long</hi> pined the king in his cave, beşide his rolling şea. Day did not come to
   his dwelling ; nor the burning oak by night. But the wind of ocean was there, and the parting
   beam of the moon. The red ştar looked on the king, when it trembled on the weştern wave. Snitho
   came to Selma's hall : Snitho the friend of Larthmor's youth. He told of the king of Berrathon :
   the wrath of Fingal aroşe. Thrice he aşşumed the şpear, reşolved to ştretch his hand to Uthal.
   But the memory<note>
   <p> The meaning is, that Fingal remembered his own great actions, and conşequently would not
    şully them by engaging in a petty war againşt Uthal, who was şo far his inferior in valour and
    power. </p>
   </note> of his deeds roşe before the king. He şent his şon and Tofcar. Our joy was great on the
   rolling şea. We often half-unşheathed our şwords. For never before had we fought alone, in
   battles of the şpear.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Night</hi> came down on the ocean. The winds departed on their wings. Cold and
   pale is the moon. The red ştars lift their heads on high. Our courşe is şlow along the coaşt of
   Berrathon. The white waves tumble on the rocks. “What voice is that,” şaid Toşcar, “which comes
   between the şounds of the waves? It is şoft but <!-- mournful, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210199" facs="../img/1773-638.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 199 --> mournful, like the voice of departed bards. But I behold a maid<note>
   <p> Nina-thoma, the daughter of Torth'ma, who had been confined to a deşart işland by her lover
    Uthal. </p>
   </note>. She şits on the rock alone. Her head bends on her arm of şnow. Her dark hair is in the
   wind. Hear, şon of Fingal, her şong, it is şmooth as the gliding ştream.” We came to the şilent
   bay, and heard the maid of night.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">How</hi> long will ye roll around me, blue-tumbling waters of ocean ? My
   dwelling was not always in caves, nor beneath the whiştling tree. The feaşt was şpread in
   Torthóma's hall. My father delighted in my voice. The youths beheld me in the şteps of my
   lovelineşs. They bleşşed the dark-haired Nina-thoma. It was then thou didşt come, O Uthal ! like
   the şun of heaven ! The şouls of the virgins are thine, şon of generous Larthmor ! But why doşt
   thou leave me alone, in the midşt of roaring waters? Was my şoul dark with thy death? Did my
   white hand lift the şword ? Why then haşt thou left me alone, king of high Finthormo<note>
   <p> Finthormo, the palace of Uthal. The names in this epişode are not of a Celtic original. </p>
   </note> !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> tear ştarted from my eye, when I heard the voice of the maid. I ştood
   before her in my arms. I şpoke the words of peace ! “Lovely <!-- O4 dweller -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210200" facs="../img/1773-641.pbm"/>
   <!-- 200 BERRATHON: --> dweller of the cave! what şigh is in thy breaşt ? Shall Oşşian lift his
   şword in thy preşence, the deştruction of thy foes? Daughter of Torthoma, rişe. I have heard the
   words of thy grief. The race of Morven are around thee, who never injured the weak. Come to our
   dark-boşomed şhip! thou brighter than that şetting moon ! Our courşe is to the rocky Berrathon,
   to the ecchoing walls of Finthormo.” She came in her beauty ; şhe came with all her lovely şteps.
   Silent joy brightened in her face; as when the şhadows fly from the field of şpring ; the
   blue-ştream is rolling in brightneşs, and the green buşh bends over its courşe !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> morning roşe with its beams. We came to Rothma's bay. A boar ruşhed from
   the wood : my şpear pierced his şide, and he fell. I rejoiced over the blood<note>
   <p> Oşşian might have thought that his killing a boar on his firşt landing in Berrathon, was a
   good omen of his future şucceşs in that işland. The preşent Highlanders look, with a degree of
   şuperştition, upon the şucceşs of their firşt action, after they have engaged in any deşperate
   undertaking. </p> </note>. I foreşaw my growing fame. But now the şound of Uthal's train came,
   from the high Finthormo. They şpread over the heath to the chace of the boar. Himşelf comes
   şlowly on, in the pride of his ştrength. He lifts two pointed şpears. On his şide is the hero's
   <!-- şword. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210201" facs="../img/1773-644.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M, 201 --> şword. Three youths carry his polişhed bows. The bounding of five dogs is
   before him. His heroes move on, at a diştance, admiring the şteps of the king. Stately was the
   şon of Larthmor ! but his şoul was dark! Dark as the troubled face of the moon, when it foretels
   the ştorms !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">We</hi> roşe on the heath before the king. He ştopt in the midşt of his courşe.
   His heroes gathered around. A gray-haired bard advanced. “Whence are the şons of the ştrangers !”
   began the bard of şong. “The children of the unhappy come to Berrathon; to the şword of car-borne
   Uthal. He şpreads no feaşt in his hall. The blood of ştrangers is on his ştreams. If from Selma's
   walls ye come, from the moşşy walls of Fingal, chuşe three youths to go to your king to tell of
   the fall of his people. Perhaps the hero may come and pour his blood on Uthal's şword. So şhall
   the fame of Finthormo arişe, like the growing tree of the vale!”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Never</hi> will it rişe, O bard,” I şaid in the pride of my wrath. “He would
   şhrink from the preşence of Fingal, whofe eyes are the flames of death. The şon of Comhal comes,
   and kings vanişh before him. They are rolled together, like mişt, by the breath of his rage.
   Shall three tell to Fingal, that his people fell? <!-- Yes! -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210202" facs="../img/1773-647.pbm"/>
   <!-- 202 BERRATHON: --> Yes ! they may tell it, bard ! but his people şhall fall with fame !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">I stood</hi> in the darkneşs of my ştrength. Toşcar drew his şword at my şide.
   The foe came on like a ştream. The mingled şound of death aroşe. Man took man, şhield met şhield
   ; şteel mixed its beams with şteel. Darts hişs thro' air. Spears ring on mails. Swords on broken
   bucklers bound. As the noişe of an aged grove beneath the roaring wind, when a thouşand ghoşts
   break the trees by night, şuch was the din of arms! But Uthal fell beneath my şword. The şons of
   Berrathon fled. It was then I şaw him in his beauty, and the tear hung in my eye! “Thou art
   fallen<note>
   <p> To mourn over the fall of their enemies, was a practice univerşal among the Celtic heroes
   This is more agreeable to humanity, than the şhameful inşulting of the dead, şo common in Homer,
   and after him, şervilely copied by all his imitators, the humane Virgil not excepted, who have
   been more şucceşsful in borrowing the imperfections of that great poet, than in their imitations
   of his beauties. </p> </note>, young tree,” I şaid, “with all thy beauty round thee. Thou art
   fallen on thy plains, and the field is bare. The winds come from the deşart! there is no şound in
   thy leaves ! Lovely art thou in death, şon of car-borne Larthmor.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Nina-thoma</hi> şat on the şhore. She heard the şound of battle. She turned her
   red eyes on <!-- Lethmal, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210203" facs="../img/1773-650.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 203 --> Lethmal, the gray-haired bard of Selma. He alone had remained on the
   coaşt, with the daughter of Torthoma, “Son of the times of old !” şhe şaid, “I hear the noişe of
   death. Thy friends have met with Uthal and the chief is low ! O that I had remained on the rock,
   incloşed with the tumbling waves! Then would my şoul be şad, but his death would not reach my
   ear. Art thou fallen on thy heath, O şon of high Finthormo ! Thou didşt leave me on a rock, but
   my şoul was full of thee. Son of high Finthormo ! art thou fallen on thy heath ?”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">She</hi> roşe pale in her tears. She şaw the bloody şhield of Uthal. She şaw it
   in Oşşian's hand. Her şteps were diştracted on the heath. She flew. She found him. She fell. Her
   şoul came forth in a şigh. Her hair is şpread on his face. My burşting tears deşcend. A tomb
   aroşe on the unhappy. My şong of woe was heard. “Reşt, hapleşs children of youth! Reşt at the
   noişe of that moşşy ştream! The virgins will şee your tomb, at the chace, and turn away their
   weeping eyes. Your fame will be in şong. The voice of the harp will be heard in your praişe. The
   daughters of Selma şhall hear it: your renown şhall be in other lands. Reşt, children of youth,
   at the noişe of the moşşy ştream.” <!-- Two -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210204" facs="../img/1773-653.pbm"/>
   <!-- 204 BERRATHON: --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Two</hi> days we remained on the coaşt. The heroes of Berrathon convened. We
   brought Larthmor to his halls. The feaşt of şhells is şpread. The joy of the aged was great. He
   looked to the arms of his fathers. The arms which he left in his hall, when the pride of Uthal
   roşe. We were renowned before Larthmor. He bleşşed the chiefs of Morven. He knew not that his şon
   was low, the ştately ştrength of Uthal ! They had told, that he had retired to the woods, with
   the tears of grief. They had told it, but he was şilent in the tomb of Rothma's heath.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the fourth day we raişed our şails, to the roar of the northern wind.
   Larthmor came to the coaşt. His bards exalted the şong. The joy of the king was great, he looked
   to Rothma's gloomy heath. He şaw the tomb of his şon. The memory of Uthal roşe. “Who of my
   heroes,” he şaid, “lies there? he şeems to have been of the Kings of men. Was he renowned in my
   halls, before the pride of Uthal roşe ?” Ye are şilent, şons of Berrathon! is the king of heroes
   low ? My heart melts for thee, O Uthal ! though thy hand was againşt thy father. O that I had
   remained in the cave! that my şon had dwelt in Finthormo! I might have heard the <!-- tread -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210205" facs="../img/1773-656.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 205 --> tread of his feet, when he went to the chace of the boar. I might have
   heard his voice on the blaşt of my cave. Then would my şoul be glad : but now darkneşs dwells in
   my halls.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were my deeds, şon of Alpin, when the arm of my youth was ştrong.
   Such<note>
   <p> Oşşian şpeaks. </p> </note> the actions of Toşcar, the car-borne şon of Conloch. But Toşcar
   is on his flying cloud. I am alone at Lutha. My voice is like the laşt şound of the wind, when it
   forfakes the woods. But Oşşian şhall not be long alone. He fees the mişt that şhall receive his
   ghoşt. He beholds the mişt that şhall form his robe, when he appears on his hills. The şons of
   feeble men şhall behold me, and admire the ştature of the chiefs of old. They şhall creep to
   their caves. They şhall look to the şky with fear: for my şteps şhall be in the clouds. Darkneşs
   şhall roll on my şide.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Lead</hi>, şon of Alpin, lead the aged to his woods. The winds begin to rişe. The
   dark wave of the lake reşounds. Bends there not a tree from Mora with its branches bare? It
   bends, şon of Alpin, in the ruştling blaşt. My harp hangs on a blaşted branch. The şound of its
   ştrings is mournful. Does the wind touch thee, O harp, or is it şome paşşing ghoşt! It is the
   hand of Malvina! Bring me the harp, <!-- şn -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210206" facs="../img/1773-659.pbm"/>
   <!-- 206 BERRATHON: --> şon of Alpin. Another şong şhall rişe. My şoul şhall depart in the şound.
   My fathers şhall hear it in their airy hall. Their dim faces şhall hang, with joy, from their
   clouds; and their hands receive their şon. The aged oak bends over the ştream. It şighs with all
   its moşs. The withered fern whiştles near, and mixes, as it waves, with Oşşian's hair.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Strike</hi> the harp and raişe the şong: be near, with all your wings, ye winds.
   Bear the mournful şound away to Fingal's airy hall. Bear it to Fingal's hall, that he may hear
   the voice of his şon. The voice of him that praişed the mighty !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">The</hi> blaşt of north opens thy gates, O king. I behold thee şitting on mişt,
   dimly gleaming in all thine arms. Thy form now is not the terror of the valiant. It is like a
   watery cloud ; when we şee the ştars behind it, with their weeping eyes. Thy şhield is the aged
   moon : thy şword a vapour half-kindled with fire. Dim and feeble is the chief, who travelled in
   brightneşs before ! But thy şteps<note>
   <p> This deşcription of the power of Fingal over the winds and ştorms, and the image of his
   taking the şun, and hiding him in the clouds, do not correşpond with the preceding paragraph,
   where he is repreşented as a feeble ghoşt, and no more the <hi rend="sc">terror of the
   valiant</hi> ; but it agrees with the notion of the times concerning the şouls of the deceaşed,
   who, it was şuppoşed, had the command of the winds and ştorms, but took no concern in the affairs
   of men. </p> </note> are on the winds of the <!-- deşart. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210207" facs="../img/1773-662.pbm"/>
   <!-- A PO E M. 207 --> deşart, The ştorms are darkening in thy hand. Thou takeşt the şun in thy
   wrath, and hideşt him in thy clouds. The şons of little men are afraid. A thouşand şhowers
   deşcend. But when thou comeşt forth in thy mildneşs ; the gale of the morning is near thy courşe.
   The şun laughs in his blue fields. The grey ştream winds in its vale, The buşhes şhake their
   green heads in the wind. The roes bound towards the deşart.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">There</hi> is a murmur in the heath ! the ştormy winds abate! ] hear the voice
   of Fingal. Long has it been abşent from mine ear ! “Come, Oşşian, come away,” he şays. “Fingal
   has received his fame. We paşşed away, like flames that had şhone for a şeaşon. Our departure was
   in renown. Though the plains of our battles are dark and şilent ; our fame is in the şour grey
   ştones. The voice of Oşşian has been heard. The harp has been ştrung in Selma. “Come Oşşian, come
   away,” he şays, “come, fly with thy fathers on clouds.” I come, I come, thou king of men ! The
   life of Oşşian fails. I begin to vanişh on Cona. My şteps are not şeen in Selma. Beşide the ştone
   of Mora I şhall fall aşleep. The winds whiştling in my grey hair, şhall not awaken me. Depart on
   thy wings, O wind : thou canşt not dişturb the reşt of the bard. <!-- I be -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210208" facs="../img/1773-665.pbm"/>
   <!-- 208 BERRATHON: --> The night is long, but his eyes are heavy, Depart, thou ruştling
   blaşt.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">But</hi> why art thou şad, şon of Fingal ? Why grows the cloud of thy şoul ? The
   chiefs of other times are departed. They have gone without their fame. The şons of future years
   şhall paşs away. Another race şhall arişe. The people are like the waves of ocean : like the
   leaves of woody Morven, they paşs away in the ruştling blaşt, and other leaves lift their green
   heads on high.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Did</hi> thy beauty laşt, O Ryno<note>
   <p> Ryno, the şon of Fingal, who was killed in Ireland, in the war againşt Swaran, was remarkable
   for the beauty of his perşon, his şwiftneşs and great exploits. Minvâne, the daughter of Morni,
   and şişter to Gaul, was in love with Ryno. Her lamentation over her lover follows.</p> <quote>
   <p><hi rend="sc">She</hi> bluşhing şad, from Morven's rocks, bends over the darkly-rolling şea.
   She şees the youth in all their arms,. Where, Kyno, where art thou? </p>
   <p>Our dark looks told that he was low ! That pale the hero flew on clouds! That in the graşs of
   Morven's hills, his feeble voice was heard in wind!</p>
   <p>And is the şon of Fingal fallen on Ullin's moşşy plains? Strong was the arm that vanquişhed
   him! Ah me! I am alone !</p>
   <p>Alone I şhall not be, ye winds! that lift my dark-brown hair. My şighs şhall not long mix with
   your ştream; for I muşt şleep with Ryno.</p>
   <p>I şee thee not, with beauty's şteps, returning from the chace. The night is round Minvâne's
   love. Dark şilence dwells with Ryno.</p>
   <p>Where are thy dogs, and where thy bow ? Thy şhield that was şo ştrong ? Thy şword like
   heaven's deşcending fire ? The bloody şpear of Ryno ?</p>
   <p>I şee them mixed in thy deep şhip; I şee them ştained with blood. No arms are in thy narrow
     hall, O darkly-dwelling Ryno!</p>
   <p>When will the morning come, and şay, “arişe, thou king of şpears! arişe, the hunters are
   abroad. The hinds are near thee, Ryno!”</p>
   <p>Away, thou fair-haired morning, away! the şlumbering king hears thee not! The hinds bound over
   his narrow tomb ; for death dwells round young Ryno.</p>
   <p>But I will tread şoftly, my king! and şteal to the bed of thy repoşe. Minvâne will lie in
   şilence; nor dişturb the şlumbering Ryno.</p>
   <p>The maids şhall şeek me; but they şhall not find me : they şhall follow my departure with
   şongs. But I şhall not hear you, O maids: I şleep with fair-haired Ryno. </p> </quote> </note>?
   Stood the ştrength of car-borne Oşcar? Fingal himşelf <!-- departed. -->
   <!-- I şee -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210209" facs="../img/1773-668.pbm"/>
   <!-- A P O E M. 209 --> departed. The halls of his fathers forgot his şteps. Shalt thou then
   remain, thou aged bard! when the mighty have failed ? But my fame şhall remain, and grow like the
   oak of Morven ; which lifts its broad head to the ştorm, and rejoices in the courşe of the wind ! </p>
  <!-- Vol. II. P -->
  <pb xml:id="P73210210" facs="../img/1773-671.pbm"/>

 </body>
</text>
