<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <front>
  <pb xml:id="P73210181" facs="../img/1773-584.pbm"/>
  <titlePage source="NYPL"><titlePart>CONLATH and CUTHONA; A P O E M.</titlePart></titlePage>
  <pb xml:id="P73210182" facs="../img/1773-587.pbm"/>
  <div>
   <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p> Conlath was the youngeſt of Morni's ſons, and brother to the celebrated Gaul. He was in love
    with Cuthóna the daughter of Rumar, when Toſcar the ſon of Kinfena, accompanied by Fercuth his
    friend, arrived, from Ireland, at Mora, where Conlath dwelt. He was hoſpitably received, and
    according to the cuſtom of the times, feaſted, three days, with Conlath. On the fourth he ſet
    ſail, and coaſting the <hi>iſland of waves</hi>, one of the Hebrides, he ſaw Cuthona hunting,
    fell in love with her, and carried her away, by force, in his ſhip. He was forced, by ſtreſs of
    weather, into I-thona a deſart iſle. In the mean-time Conlath, hearing of the rape, ſailed after
    him, and ſound him on the point of ſailing for the coaſt of Ireland. They fought; and they and
    their followers fell by mutual wounds. Cuthona did not long ſurvive: for ſhe died of grief the
    third day after. Fingal, hearing of their unfortunate death, ſent Stormal the ſon of Moran to
    bury them, but forgot to ſend a bard to ſing the funeral ſong over their tombs. The ghoſt of
    Conlath comes, long after, to Oſſian, to intreat him to tranſmit, to poſterity, his and
    Cuthona's fame. For it was the opinion of the times, that the ſouls of the deceaſed were not
    happy, till their elegies were compoſed by a bard. </p>
  </div>
  <!--  -->
  <!--  -->
 </front>
 <body>
  <pb xml:id="P73210183" facs="../img/1773-590.pbm"/>
  <!-- [183] -->
   <head>CONLATH and CUTHONA; A P O E M.</head>
   <p> <hi rend="sc">Did</hi> not Oſſian hear a voice? or is it the ſound of days that are no more?
    Often does the memory of former times come, like the evening ſun, on my ſoul. The noiſe of the
    chace is renewed. In thought, I lift the ſpear. But Oſſian did hear a voice ! Who art thou, ſon
    of night ? The children of the feeble are aſleep. The midnight wind is in my hall. Perhaps it is
    the ſhield of Fingal that ecchoes to the blaſt. It hangs in Oſſian's hall. He feels it ſometimes
    with his hands. Yes! I hear thee, my friend ! Long has thy voice been abſent from mine ear !
    What brings thee, on thy cloud, to Oſſian, ſon of generous Morni? Are the friends of the aged
    near thee? Where is Oſcar, ſon of fame? He was often near thee, O Conlath, when the ſound of
    battle aroſe.</p>
   <!--  -->
   <!-- N 4 GHOST -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210184" facs="../img/1773-593.pbm"/>
   <!-- 134 CONLATH and CUTHONA: -->
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Ghost</hi> of <hi rend="sc">Conlath</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">Sleeps</hi> the ſweet voice of Cona, in the midſt of his ruſtling hall ?
     Sleeps Oſſian in his hall, and his friends without their fame? The ſea rolls round dark I-thona. <note>
     <p> I-thonn, <hi>iſland of waves</hi>, one of the uninhabited weſtern iſles. </p></note> Our
     tombs are not ſeen in our iſle. How long ſhall our fame be unheard, ſon of reſounding Selma
     ?</p>
    
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Ossian</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">O that</hi> mine eyes could behold thee ! Thou ſitteſt, dim, on thy cloud! Art
     thou like the miſt of Lano? An half-extinguiſhed meteor of fire? Of what are the ſkirts of thy
     robe? Of what is thine airy bow? He is gone on his blaſt like the ſhade of a wandering cloud.
     Come from thy wall, O harp! Let me hear thy ſound. Let the light of memory riſe on I-thona. Let
     me behold again my friends ! And Oſſian does behold his friends, on the dark-blue iſle. The
     cave of Thona appears, with its moſſy rocks and bending trees. A ſtream roars at its mouth.
     Toſcar bends over its courſe, Fercuth is ſad by his ſide. Cuthóna<note>
     <p> Cuthona the daughter of Rumar, whom Toſcar had carried away by force. </p></note> ſits at a
     diſtance, and weeps. Does the wind of <!--  -->
     <!-- 7 the -->
     <!--  -->
     <pb xml:id="P73210185" facs="../img/1773-596.pbm"/>
     <!-- A P O E M. 185 --> the waves deceive me? Or do I hear them ſpeak ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Toscar</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">The</hi> night was ſtormy. From their hills the groaning oaks came down, The
     ſea darkly-tumbled beneath the blaſt. The roaring waves climbed againſt our rocks. The
     lightning came often and ſhewed the blaſted fern. Fercuth ! I ſaw the ghoſt who embroiled the night<note>
     <p> It was long thought, in the north of Scotland, that ſtorms were raiſed by the ghoſts of the
     deceaſed. This notion is ſtill entertained by the vulgar; for they think that whirlwinds, and
     ſudden ſqualls of wind are occaſioned by ſpirits, who tranſport themſelves, in that manner,
     from one place to another. </p></note>. Silent he ſtood, on that bank. His robe of miſt flew on
     the wind. I could behold his tears. An aged man he ſeemed, and full of thought !</p>
    
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Fercuth</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> It was thy father, O Toſcar. He foreſees ſome death among his race. Such was his appearance
     on Cromla, before the great Maronnan<note>
     <p> Ma-ronnan was the brother of Toſcar, </p></note> fell. Erin of hills of graſs! how pleaſant
     are thy vales? Silence is near thy blue ſtreams. The ſun is on thy fields. Soft is the
     <!--  -->
     <!-- ſound -->
     <!--  -->
     <pb xml:id="P73210186" facs="../img/1773-599.pbm"/>
     <!-- 126 CONLATH and CUTHONA: --> ſound of the harp in Selama<note>
     <p> Selámath, <hi>beautiful to behold</hi>, the name of Toſcar's reſidence, on the coaſt of
     Ulſter, near the mountain Cromla. </p></note>. Lovely the cry of the hunter on Crómla. But we
     are in dark I-thona, ſurrounded by the ſtorm. The billows lift their white heads above our
     rocks. We tremble amidſt the night.</p>
    </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Toscar</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">Whither</hi> is the ſoul of battle fled, Fercuth with locks of age? I have
     ſeen thee undaunted in danger: thine eyes burning with joy in the fight. Whither is the ſoul of
     battle fled? Our fathers never feared. Go: view the ſettling ſea : the ſtormy wind is laid. The
     billows ſtill tremble on the deep. They ſeem to fear the blaſt. Go view the ſettling ſea.
     Morning is grey on our rocks. The ſun will look ſoon from his eaſt; in all his pride of light!
     I lifted up my ſails, with joy, before the halls of generous Conlath. My courſe was by a deſart
     iſle : where Cuthona purſued the deer. I ſaw her, like that beam of the ſun that iſſues from
     the cloud. Her hair was on her heaving breaſt. She, bending forward, drew the bow. Her white
     arm ſeemed, behind her, like the ſnow of Cromla. Come to my ſoul, I ſaid, huntreſs <!--  -->
     <!-- of -->
     <!--  -->
     <pb xml:id="P73210187" facs="../img/1773-602.pbm"/>
     <!-- A P O E M. 187 --> of the deſart iſle! But ſhe waſtes her time in tears, She thinks of the
     generous Conlath. Where can I find thy peace, Cuthona, lovely maid !</p>
    
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Cu-thona</hi><note>
     <p> Cu-thona, <hi>the mournful ſound of the waves</hi>; a poetical name given her on account of
     her mourning to the ſound of the waves; her name in tradition is Gorm-huil, <hi>the blue-eyed
     maid</hi>. </p></note>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">A distant</hi> ſteep bends over the ſea, with aged trees and moſſy rocks. The
     billow rolls at its feet. On its ſide is the dwelling of roes. The people call it Mora. There
     the towers of my love ariſe. There Conlath looks over the ſea for his only love. The daughters
     of the chace returned. He beheld their downcaft eyes. “Where is the daughter of Rumar ?” But
     they anſwered not. My peace dwells on Mora, ſon of the diſtant land !</p>
    
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Toscar</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">Cuthona</hi> ſhall return to her peace : to the towers of generous Conlath. He
     is the friend of Toſcar ! I have feaſted in his halls! Riſe, ye gentle breezes of Erin. Stretch
     my ſails toward Mora's ſhores. Cuthona ſhall reſt on Mora : but the days of Toſcar muſt be ſad.
     I ſhall fit in my cave in the field of the ſun. The <!--  -->
     <!-- blaſt -->
     <!--  -->
     <pb xml:id="P73210188" facs="../img/1773-605.pbm"/>
     <!-- 282 CONLATH and CUTHONA: --> blaſt will ruſtle in my trees. I ſhall think it is Cuthona's
     voice. But ſhe is diſtant far, in the halls of the mighty Conlath !</p>
    
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Cuthona</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">Ha</hi> ! what cloud is that ? It carries the ghoſts of my fathers. I ſee the
     ſkirts of their robes, like grey and watry miſt. When ſhall I fall, O Rumar ? Sad Cuthona
     foreſees her death. Will not Conlath behold me, before I enter the narrow houſe<note>
     <p> The grave. </p></note> ?</p>
    
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Ossian</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> <hi rend="sc">He</hi> ſhall behold thee, O maid. He comes along the heaving ſea. The death
     of Toſcar is dark on his ſpear. A wound is in his ſide ! He is pale at the cave of Thona. He
     ſhews his ghaſtly wound. Where art thou with thy tears, Cuthona ? The chief of Mora dies. The
     viſion grows dim, on my mind. I behold the chiefs no more ! But, O ye bards of future times,
     remember the fall of Conlath with tears. He fell before his day. Sadneſs darkened in his hall.
     His mother looked to his ſhield on the wall, and it was bloody<note>
     <p> It was the opinion of the times, that the arms left by the heroes at home, became bloody
     the very inſtant their owners were killed, though at ever ſo great a diſtance. </p></note>. She
     knew that her hero fell. <!--  -->
     <!--  Her -->
     <!--  -->
     <pb xml:id="P73210189" facs="../img/1773-608.pbm"/>
     <!-- A P O E M. 189 --> Her ſorrow was heard on Mora. Art thou pale on thy rock, Cuthona,
     beſide the fallen chiefs ? Night comes, and day returns, but none appears to raiſe their tomb.
     Thou frighteneſt the ſcreaming fowls away. Thy tears for ever flow. Thou art pale as a watry
     cloud, that riſes from a lake !</p>
    <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſons of green Selma came. They ſound Cuthona cold. They raiſed a tomb
     over the heroes. She reſts at the ſide of Conlath. Come not to my dreams, O Conlath ! Thou haſt
     received thy fame. Be thy voice far diſtant from my hall; that ſleep may deſcend at night. O
     that I could forget my friends : till my footſteps ſhould ceaſe to be ſeen! till I come among
     them with joy! and lay my aged limbs in the narrow houſe ! </p>
   </sp>
   <!--  -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210190" facs="../img/1773-611.pbm"/>
   <!--  -->
   <!--  -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210191" facs="../img/1773-614.pbm"/>
   <!--  -->
   <!--  -->
  
 </body>
</text>