<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><front>
 <pb xml:id="P73210233" facs="../img/1773-740.pbm"/>
 <titlePage source="NYPL"><titlePart>A DISSERTATION CONCERNING THE POEMS of OSSIAN.</titlePart></titlePage>

 <pb xml:id="P73210234" facs="../img/1773-743.pbm"/>
</front><body>
<pb xml:id="P73210235" facs="../img/1773-746.pbm"/>
<!--   -->
<head>A DISSERTATION CONCERNING THE POEMS of OSSIAN.</head>
 <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> hiſtory of thoſe nations, who originally poſſeſſed the north of Europe, is leſs known than their manners. Deſtitute of the uſe of letters, they themſelves had not the means of tranſmitting their great actions to remote poſterity. Foreign writers ſaw them only at a diſtance, and deſcribed them as they found them. The vanity of the Romans induced them to conſider the nations beyond the pale of their empire as barbarians; and conſequently their hiſtory unworthy of being inveſtigated. Their manners and fingular character were matters of curioſity, as they committed them to record. Some men, otherwiſe of great merit among ourſelves, give into confined ideas on 
<!-- this -->

<pb xml:id="P73210236" facs="../img/1773-749.pbm"/>
<!-- 236 ADISSERTATION concerning the -->
 this ſubject. Having early imbibed their idea of exalted manners from the Greek and Roman writers, they ſcarcely ever afterwards have the fortitude to allow any dignity of character to any nation deſtitute of the uſe of letters.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Without</hi> derogating from the fame of Greece and Rome, we may conſider antiquity beyond the pale of their empire worthy of ſome attention. The nobler paſſions of the mind never ſhoot forth more free and unreſtrained than in the times we call barbarous. That irregular manner of life, and thoſe manly purſuits from which barbarity takes its name, are highly favorable to a ſtrength of mind unknown in poliſhed times. In advanced ſociety the characters of men are more uniform and diſguiſed. The human paſſions lie in ſome degree concealed behind forms, and artificial manners; and the powers of the ſoul, without an opportunity of exerting them, loſe their vigor. The times of regular government, and poliſhed manners, are therefore to be wiſhed ſor by the feeble and weak in mind. An unſettled ſtate, and thoſe convulſions which attend it, is the proper field for an exalted character, and the exertion of great parts. Merit there riſes always ſuperior ; no fortuitous event can raiſe the timid and mean into power. To thoſe who look upon antiquity in this light, 
<!-- it -->

<pb xml:id="P73210237" facs="../img/1773-752.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 237 -->
 it is an agreeable proſpect ; and they alone can have real pleaſure in tracing nations to their ſource.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> eſtabliſhment of the Celtic ſtates, in the north of Europe, is beyond the reach of written annals. The traditions and ſongs to which they truſted their hiſtory, were loſt, or altogether corrupted in their revolutions and migrations, which were ſo frequent and univerſal, that no kingdom in Europe is now poſſefed by its original inhabitants. Societies were ſormed, and kingdoms erected, from a mixture of nations, who, in proceſs of time, loſt all knowlege of their own origin. If tradition could be depended upon, it is only among a people, from all time, free from intermixture with foreigners. We are to look for theſe among the mountains and inacceſfible parts of a country : places, on account of their barrenneſs, uninviting to an enemy, or whoſe natural ſtrength enabled the natives to repel invaſions. Such are the inhabitants of the mountains of Scotland. We, accordingly, find, that they differ materially from thoſe who poſſeſs the low and more fertile part of the kingdom. Their language is pure and original, and their manners are thoſe of an ancient and unmixed race of men. Conſcious of their own antiquity, they long deſpiſed others, as a new and mixed 
<!-- people, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210238" facs="../img/1773-755.pbm"/>
<!-- 233 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 people. As they lived in a country only fit for paſture, they were free from that toil and buſineſs, which engroſs the attention of a commercial people, Their amuſement conſiſted in hearing or repeating their ſongs and traditions, and theſe intirely turned on the antiquity of their nation, and the exploits of their forefathers. It is no wonder, therefore, that there are more remains of antiquity among them, than among any other people in Europe. Traditions, however, concerning remote periods, are only to be regarded, in ſo far as they co-incide with cotemporary writers of undoubted credit and veracity.</p><p><hi rend="sc">No</hi> writers began their accounts from a more early period, than the hiſtorians of the Scots nation. Without records, or even tradition itſelf, they give a long liſt of ancient kings, and a detail of their tranſactions, with a ſcrupulous exactneſs. One might naturally ſuppoſe, that, when they had no authentic annals, they ſhould, at leaſt, have recourſe to the traditions of their country, and have reduced them into a regular ſyſtem of hiſtory. Of both they ſeem to have been equally deſtitute. Born in the low country, and ſtrangers to the ancient language of their nation, they contented themſelves with copying from one another, and retailing the ſame fictions, in a new colour and dreſs.</p>
 <!-- <p>2 JonN</p>-->
<pb xml:id="P73210239" facs="../img/1773-758.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 239 -->
<p><hi rend="sc">John Fordunn</hi> was the firſt who collected thoſe fragments of the Scots hiſtory, which had eſcaped the brutal policy of Edward I. and reduced them into order. His accounts, in ſo far as they concerned recent tranſactions, deſerved credit : beyond a certain period, they were fabulous and unſatisfactory. Some time before Fordun wrote, the king of England, in a letter to the pope, had run up the antiquity of his nation to a very remote æra. Fordun, poſſeſſed of all the national prejudice of the age, was unwilling that his country ſhould yield, in point of antiquity, to a people, then its rivals and enemies. Deſtitute of annals in Scotland, he had recourſe to Ireland, which, according to the vulgar errors of the times, was reckoned the firſt habitation of the Scots. He found, there, that the Iriſh bards had carried their pretenſions to antiquity as high, if not beyond any nation in Europe. It was from them he took thoſe improbable fictions, which form the firſt part of his hiſtory.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> writers that ſucceeded Fordun implicitly followed his ſyſtem, though they ſometimes varied from him in their relations of particular tranſactions, and the order of ſucceſſion of their kings. As they had no new lights, and were, equally with him, unacquainted with the 
<!-- tions -->

<pb xml:id="P73210240" facs="../img/1773-761.pbm"/>
<!-- 240 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 traditions of their country, their hiſtories contain little information concerning the origin of the Scots. Even Buchanan himſelf, except the elegance and vigour of his ſtile, has very little to recommend him. Blinded with political prejudices, he ſeemed more anxious to turn the fictions of his predeceſſors to his own purpoſes, than to detect their miſrepreſentations, or inveſtigate truth amidſt the darkneſs which they had thrown round it. It therefore appears, that little can be collected from their own hiſtorians, concerning the firſt migration of the Scots into Britain. </p><p><hi rend="sc">That</hi> this iſland was peopled from Gaul admits of no doubt. Whether colonies came afterwards from the north of Europe is a matter of meer ſpeculation. When South-Britain yielded to the power of the Romans, the unconquered nations to the north of the province were diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>Caledonians</hi>. From their very name, it appears, that they were of thoſe Gauls, who poſſeſſed themſelves originally of Britain. It is compounded of two <hi>Celtic</hi> words, <hi>Cal</hi> ſignifying <hi>Celts</hi>, or <hi>Gauls</hi>, and <hi>Dun</hi> or <hi>Don</hi>, a hill; ſo that <hi>Cal-don</hi>, or Caledonians, is as much as to ſay, the <hi>Celts of the hill country</hi>. The Highlanders, to this day, call themſelves <hi>Cal</hi>, their language <hi>Calic</hi>, or <hi>Galic</hi>, and their country 
<!-- 9 Catldoch, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210241" facs="../img/1773-764.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 241 -->
 <hi>Caldoch</hi>, which the Romans ſoftened into <hi>Caledonia</hi>. This, of itſelf, is ſufficient to demonſtrate, they are the genuine deſcendents of the ancient Caledonians, and not a pretended colony of <hi>Scots</hi>, who ſettled firſt in the north, in the third or fourth century.</p><p><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the double meaning of the word <hi>Cal</hi>, which ſignifies <hi>ſtrangers</hi>, as well as <hi>Gauls</hi>,or <hi>Celts</hi>, ſome have imagined, that the anceſtors of the Caledonians were of a different race from the reſt of the Britons, and that they received their name upon that account. This opinion, ſay they, is ſupported by Tacitus, who, from ſeveral circumſtances, concludes, that the Caledonians were of German extraction. A diſcuſſion of a point ſo intricate, at this diſtance of time, could neither be fatisfaſtory nor important.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Towards</hi> the latter end of the third, and beginning of the fourth century, we meet with the Scots in the north. Porphyrius<note><p> St. Hierom, ad Cteſiphon, </p></note> makes the firſt mention of them about that time. As the Scots were not heard of before that period, moſt writers ſuppoſed them to have been a colony, newly come to Britain, and that the <hi>Picts</hi> were the only genuine deſcendents of the ancient Caledonians. This miſtake is eaſily removed. The 
<!-- Vor. Il, R Cale- -->

<pb xml:id="P73210242" facs="../img/1773-767.pbm"/>
<!-- 242 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 Caledonians, in proceſs of time, became naturally divided into two diſtinct nations, as poſfefſing parts of the country, intirely different in their nature and ſoil. The weſtern coaſt of Scotland is hilly and barren ; towards the eaſt the country is plain, and fit for tillage. The inhabitants of the mountains, a roving and uncontrouled race of men, lived by feeding of cattle, and what they killed in hunting. Their employment did not fix them to one place. They removed from one heath to another, as ſuited beſt with their convenience or inclination. They were not, therefore, improperly called, by their neighbours, <hi rend="sc">Scuite</hi>, or <hi>the wandering nation</hi> ; wiuch is evidently the origin of the Roman name of <hi>Scoti</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the other hand, the Caledonians, who poſſefſed the eaſt coaſt of Scotland, as the diviſion of the country was plain and fertile, applied themſelves to agriculture, and raiſing of corn. It was from this, that the Galic name of the <hi>Picts</hi> proceeded; for they are called, in that language, <hi>Cruithnich</hi>, i. e. <hi>the wheat or corn-eaters</hi>. As the Picts lived in a country ſo different in its nature from that poſſeſſed by the Scots, ſo their national characterr ſuffered a material change. Unobſtructed by mountains, or lakes, their communication with one another was free and frequent. 
<!-- SOCICTY, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210243" facs="../img/1773-770.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSTIAN. 243 -->
 Society, therefore, became ſooner eſtabliſhed among them, than among the Scots, and, conſequently, they were much ſooner governed by civil magiſtrates and laws. This, at laſt, produced ſo great a difference in the manners of the two nations, that they began to forget their common origin, and almoſt continual quarrels and animoſities ſubſiſted between them. Theſe animoſities, after ſome ages, ended in the fubverſion of the Pictiſh kingdom, but not in the total extirpation of the nation, according to moſt of the Scots writers, who ſeemed to think it more for the honour of their countrymen to annihilate, than reduce a rival people under their obedience. It is certain, however, that the very name of the Picts was loſt, and thoſe that remained were ſo completely incorporated with their conquerors, that they ſoon loſt all memory of their own origin.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> end of the Pictiſh government is placed ſo near that period, to which authentic annals reach, that it is matter of wonder, that we have no monuments of their language or hiſtory remaining. This favours the ſyſtem I have laid down. Had they originally been of a different race from the Scots, their language of courſe would be different. The contrary is the caſe. The names of places in the Pictiſh dominions, 
<!-- R 2 and -->

<pb xml:id="P73210244" facs="../img/1773-773.pbm"/>
<!-- 244 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 and the very names of their kings, which are handed down to us, are of Galic original, which is a convincing proof, that the two nations were, of old, one and the ſame, and only divided into two governments, by the effect which their ſituation had upon the genius of the people.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> name of <hi>Picts</hi> is ſaid to have been given by the Romans to the Caledonians, who poſſefſed the eaſt coaſt of Scotland, from their painting their bodies. The ſtory is ſilly and the argument abſurd. But let us revere antiquity in her very follies. This circumſtance made ſome imagine, that the Picts were of Britiſh extract, and a different race of men from the Scots. That more of the Britons, who fled northward from the tyranny of the Romans, ſettled in the low country of Scotland, than among the Scots of the mountains, may be eaſily imagined, from the very nature of the country. It was they who introduced painting among the Picts. From this circumſtance, affirm ſome antiquaries, proceeded the name of the latter, to diſtinguiſh them from the Scots, who never had that art among them, and from the Britons, who diſcontinued it after the Roman conqueſt.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Caledonians, moſt certainly, acquired a conſiderable knowlege in navigation, by their living on a coaſt interſected with many arms of 
<!-- the -->

<pb xml:id="P73210245" facs="../img/1773-776.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 245 -->
 the ſea, and, in iſlands, divided, one from another, by wide and dangerous firths. It is, therefore, highly probable, that they, very early, ſound their way to the north of Ireland, which: is within ſight of their own country. That Ireland was firſt peopled from Britain is, at length, a matter that admits of no doubt. The vicinity of the two iſlands; the exact correſpondence of the ancient inhabitants of both, in point of manners and language, are ſufficient proofs, even if we had not the teſtimony of<note><p> Dio. Sic, 1. 5. </p></note> authors of undoubted veracity to confirm it. The abettors of the moſt romantic ſyſtems of Iriſh antiquities allow it; but they place the colony from Britain in an improbable and remote æra. I ſhall eaſily  admit, that the colony of the <hi>Firbolg</hi>, confeſſedly the Belgæ of Britain, ſettled in the ſouth of Ireland, before the Cal, or Caledonians, diſcovered the north; but it is not at all likely, that the migration of the Firbolg to Ireland happened many centuries before the chriſtian æra.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> poem of Temora throws conſiderable light on this ſubject. The accounts given in it agree ſo well with what the ancients have delivered, concerning the firſt population and
<!-- R 3 habitan's -->

<pb xml:id="P73210246" facs="../img/1773-779.pbm"/>
<!-- 246 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
inhabitants of Ireland, that eyery unbiaſſed perſon will confeſs them more probable, than the legends handed down, by tradition, in that country. It appears, that, in the days of Trathal, grandfather to Fingal, Ireland was poſſeſſed by two nations; the <hi>Firbolg</hi> or <hi>Belgæ</hi> of Britain, who inhabited the ſouth, and the Cal, who paſſed over from Caledonia and the Hebrides to Ulfter. The two nations, as is uſual among an unpoliſhed and lately ſettled people, were divided into ſmall dynaſties, ſubject to petty kings, or chiefs, independent of one another. In this ſituation, it is probable, they continued long, without any material revolution in the ſtate of the iſland, until Crothar, Lord of Atha, a country in Connaught, the moſt potent chief of the <hi>Firbolg</hi>, carried away Conlama, the daughter of Cathmin, a chief of the Cal, who poſſeſſed Ulſter.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Conlama</hi> had been betrothed ſome time before to Turloch, a chief of their own nation. Turloch reſented the affront offered him by Crothar, made an irruption into Connaught, and killed Cormul, the brother of Crothar, who came to oppoſe his progreſs. Crothar himſelf then took arms, and either killed or expelled Turloch. The war, upon this, became general, between the two nations: and the Cal were 
<!-- reduced -->

<pb xml:id="P73210247" facs="../img/1773-782.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 247 -->
 reduced to the laſt extremity. In this ſituation, they applied, for aid, to Trathal king of Morven, who ſent his brother Conar, already famous for his great exploits, to their relief. Conar, upon his arrival in Ulfter, was choſen king, by the unanimous conſent of the Caledonian tribes, who poſſeſſed that country. The war was renewed with vigour and ſucceſs; but the Firbolg appear to have been rather repelled than ſubdued. In ſucceeding reigns, we learn from epiſodes in the ſame poem, that the chiefs of Atha made ſeveral efforts to become monarchs of Ireland, and to expel the race of Conar.</p><p><hi rend="sc">To</hi> Conar ſucceeded his ſon Cormac, who appears to have reigned long. In his latter days he ſeems to have been driven to the laſt extremity, by an inſurrection of the <hi>Firbolg</hi>, who ſupported the pretenſions of the chiefs of Atha to the Iriſh throne. Fingal, who then was very young, came to the aid of Cormac, totally defeated Colc-ulla, chief of Atha, and re-eſtabliſhed CorMac in the ſole poſſeſſion of all Ireland. It was then he fell in love with, and took to wife, Roscrana, the daughter of Cormac, who was the mother of Oſſian.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Cormac</hi> was ſucceeded in the Iriſh throne by his ſon, Cairbre; Cairbre by Artho, his ſon, who was the father of that Cormac, in whoſe 
<!-- 1 R 4 minority -->

<pb xml:id="P73210248" facs="../img/1773-785.pbm"/>
<!-- 248 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 minority the invaſion of Swaran happened, which is the ſubject of the poem of <hi>Fingal</hi>. The family of Atha, who had not relinquiſhed their pretenflons to the Iriſh throne, rebelled in the minority of Cormac, defeated his adherents, and murdered him in the palace of Temora. Cairbar, lord of Atha, upon this, mounted the throne. His uſurpation ſoon ended with his life; for Fingal made an expedition into Ireland, and reſtored, after various viciſſitudes of fortune, the family of Conar to the poſſeſſion of the kingdom. This war is the ſubject of Temora; the events, though certainly heightened and embelliſhed by poetry, ſeem, notwithſtanding, to have their ſoundation in true hiſtory.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Temora</hi> contains not only the hiſtory of the firſt migration of the Caledonians into Ireland, it alſo preſerves ſome important facts, concerning the firſt ſettlement of the <hi>Firbolg</hi>, or <hi>Belgæ of Britain</hi>, in that kingdom, under their leader Larthon, who was anceſtor to Cairbar and Cathmor, who ſucceſſively mounted the Iriſh throne, after the death of Cormac, the ſon of Artho. I forbear to tranſcribe the paſſage, on account of its length. It is the ſong of Fonar, the bard; towards the latter end of the ſeventh book of Temora. As the generations from Larthon to Cathmor, to whom the epiſode 
<!-- þ -->

<!-- — —<div><head>——</head><p> -->

<pb xml:id="P73210249" facs="../img/1773-788.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 249 -->
 is addreſſed, are not marked, as are thoſe of the family of Conar, the firſt king of Ireland, we can form no judgment of the time of the ſettlement of the Firbolg. It is, however, probable, it was ſome time before the Cal, or Caledonians, ſettled in Ulfter. One important fact may be gathered from this hiſtory, that the Iriſh had no king before the latter end of the firſt century. Fingal lived, it is ſuppoſed, in the third century ; ſo Conar, the firſt monarch of the Iriſh, who was his grand-uncle, cannot be placed farther back than the cloſe of the firſt. To eſtabliſh this fact, is to lay, at once, aſide the pretended antiquities of the Scots and Iriſh, and to get quit of the long lift of kings which the latter give us for a millennium before.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Of</hi> the affairs of Scotiand, it is certain, nothing can be depended upon, prior to the reign of Fergus, the ſon of Erc, who lived in the fifth century. The true hiſtory of Ireland begins ſomewhat later than that period, Sir James Ware<note><p> War. de antiq. Hybern. præ p. 1. </p></note>, who was indeſatigable in his reſearches after the antiquities of his country, rejects, as mere fiction and idle romance, all that is related of the ancient Iriſh, before the time of St. Patrick, and the reign of Leogaire. It is from 
<!-- this -->

<pb xml:id="P73210250" facs="../img/1773-791.pbm"/>
<!-- 2:0 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 this conſideration, that he begins his hiſtory at the introduction of Chriſtianity, remarking, that all that is delivered down, concerning the times of paganiſm, were tales of late invention, ſtrangely mixed with anachroniſms and inconſiſtencies. Such being the opinion of Ware, who had collected with uncommon induſtry and zeal, all the real and pretendedly antient manuſcripts, concerning the hiſtory of his country, we may, on his authority, reject the improbable and ſelfcondemned tales of Keating and O'Flaherty. Credulous and puerile to the laſt degree, they have diſgraced the antiquities they meant to eſtabliſh. It is to be wiſhed, that ſome able Iriſhman, who underſtands the language and records of his country, may redeem, ere it is too late, the genuine antiquities of Ireland, from the hands of theſe idle fabuliſts.</p><p><hi rend="sc">By</hi> comparing the hiſtory in theſe poems with the legends of the Scots and Iriſh writers, and, by afterwards examining both by the teſt of the Roman authors, it is eaſy to diſcover which is the moſt probable. Probability is all that can be eſtabliſhed on the authority of tradition, ever dubious and uncertain. But when it favours the hypotheſis laid down by cotemporary writers of undoubted veracity, and, as it were, finiſhes the figure of which they only drew the out-lines, it 
<!-- ought, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210251" facs="../img/1773-794.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSI1IAN. 2gr -->
 ought, in the judgment of ſober reaſon, to be preferred to accounts framed in dark and diſtant periods, with little judgment, and upon no authority.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Concerning</hi> the period of more than a century, which intervenes between Fingal and the reign of Fergus, the ſon of Erc or Arcath, tradition is dark and contradictory. Some trace up the family of Fergus to a ſon of Fingal of that name, who makes a conſiderable figure in Oſſian's poems. The three elder ſons of Fingal, Oſſian, Fillan, and Ryno, dying without iſſue, the ſucceſſion, of courſe, devolved upon Fergus, the fourth ſon and his poſterity. This Fergus, ſay ſome traditions, was the father of Congal, whote ſon was Arcath, the father of Fergus, properly called the firſt king of Scots, as it was in his time the <hi>Cal</hi>, who poſſeſſed the weſtern coaft of Scotland, began to be diſtinguiſhed, by foreigners, by the name of <hi>Scots</hi> From thenceforward, the Scots and Picts, as diftinct nations, became objects of attention to the hiſtorians of other countries. The internal ſtate of the two Caledonian kingdoms has always continued, and ever muſt remain, in obſcurity and fable.</p><p><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is in this epoch we muſt ſix the beginning of the decay of that ſpecies of heroiſm, which ſubſiſted in the days of Fingal. There are three 
<!-- ſtages -->

<pb xml:id="P73210252" facs="../img/1773-797.pbm"/>
<!-- 2:2 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 ſtages in human ſociety. The firſt is the reſult of conſanguinity, and the natural affection of the members of a family to one another. The ſecond begins when property is eſtabliſhed, and men enter into aſſociations for mutual defence, againſt the invaſions and injuſtice of neighbours. Mankind ſubmit, in the third, to certain laws and ſubordinations of government, to which they truſt the ſafety of their perſons and property. As the firft is formed on nature, ſo, of courſe, it is the moſt diſintereſted and noble. Men, in the laſt, have leiſure to cultivate the mind, and to reſtore it, with reflection, to a primæval dignity of ſentiment. The middle ſtate is the region of complete barbariſm and ignorance. About the beginning of the fifth century, the Scots and Picts were advanced into the ſecond ſtage, and, conſequently, into thoſe circumſcribed ſentiments, which always diſtinguiſh barbarity. The events which ſoon after happened did not at all contribute to enlarge their ideas, or mend their national character.</p><p><hi rend="sc">About</hi> the year 425, the Romans, on account of domeſtic commotions, entirely forſook Britain, finding it impoſſible to defend ſo diſtant a frontier, The Picts and Scots, ſeizing this favourable opportunity, made incurſions into the deſerted province. The Britons, enervated by 
<!-- the -->

<pb xml:id="P73210253" facs="../img/1773-800.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 257 -->
 the ſlavery of ſeveral centuries, and thoſe vices, which are inſeparable from an advanced ſtate of civility, were not able to withſtand the impetuous, though irregular attacks of a barbarous enemy. In the utmoſt diſtreſs, they applied to their old maſters, the Romans, and (after the unfortunate ſtate of the Empire could not ſpare aid) to the Saxons, a nation equally barbarous and brave, with the enemies of whom they were ſo much afraid. Though the bravery of the Saxons repelled the Caledonian nations for a time, yet the latter found means to extend themſelves, conſiderably, towards the ſouth. It is, in this period, we muſt place the origin of the arts of Civil life among the Scots. The ſeat of government was removed from the mountains to the plain and more fertile provinces of the South, to be near the common enemy, in caſe of ſudden incurſions. Inſtead of roving through unfrequented wilds, in ſearch of ſubſiſtance, by means of hunting, men applied to agriculture, and raiſing of corn. This manner of life was the firſt means of changing the national character. The next thing which contributed to it was their mixture with ſtrangers.</p><p><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the countries which the Scots had conquered from the Britons, it is probable the moſt of the old inhabitants remained. Theſe 
<!-- porating -->

<pb xml:id="P73210254" facs="../img/1773-803.pbm"/>
<!-- 234 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
  incorporating with the conquerors, taught them agriculture, and other arts, which they themſelves had received from the Romans. The Scots, however, in number as well as power, being the moſt predominant, retained ſtill their language, and as many of the cuſtoms of their anceſtors, as ſuited with the nature of the country they poſſeſſed. Even the union of the two Caledonian kingdoms did not much affect the national character. Being originally deſcended from the ſame ſtock, the manners of the Picts and Scots were as ſimilar as the different natures of the countries they poſſefſed permitted.</p><p><hi rend="sc">What</hi> brought about a total change in the genius of the Scots nation, was their wars, and other tranſactions with the Saxons. Several counties in the ſouth of Scotland were alternately poſſeſſed by the two nations. They were ceded, in the ninth age, to the Scots, and, it is probable, that moſt of the Saxon inhabitants remained in poſſeſſion of their lands. During the ſeveral conqueſts and revolutions in England, many fled, for refuge, into Scotland, to avoid the oppreſſion of foreigners, or the tyranny of domeſtic uſurpers ; in ſo much, that the Saxon race formed perhaps near one half of the Scottiſh kingdom. The Saxon manners and language daily gained ground, on the tongue and 
<!-- toms -->

<pb xml:id="P73210255" facs="../img/1773-806.pbm"/>
<!-- POEM'S of OSSIAN. 2z5 -->
   cuſtoms of the antient Caledonians, till, at laſt, the latter were entirely relegated to inhabitants of the mountains, who were ſtill unmixed with ſtrangers.</p><p><hi rend="sc">It</hi> was after the acceſſion of territory which the Scots received, upon the retreat of the Romans from Britain, that the inhabitants of the Highlands were divided into clans. The king, when he kept his court in the mountains, was conſidered, by the whole nation, as the chief of their blood. Their ſmall number, as well as the preſence of their prince, prevented thoſe diviſions, which, afterwards, ſprung forth into ſo many ſeparate tribes. When the ſeat of government was removed to the ſouth, thoſe who remained in the Highlands were, of courſe, neglected. They naturally formed themſelves into ſmall focieties, independent of one another. Each ſociety had it's own <hi>regulus</hi>, who either was, or in the ſucceſſion of a few generations, was regarded as chief of their blood. The nature of the country favoured an inſtitution of this ſort. A few valleys, divided from one another by extenſive heaths and impaſſible mountains, form the face of the Highlands. In theſe valleys the chiefs fixed their reſidence. Round them, and almoſt within ſight of their dwellings, were  the habitations of their relations and dependents.</p><p>
<!-- THz -->

<pb xml:id="P73210256" facs="../img/1773-809.pbm"/>
<!-- 266 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 <hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſeats of the Highland chiefs were neither diſagreeable nor inconvenient. Surrounded with mountains and hanging woods, they were covered from the inclemency of the weather. Near them generally ran a pretty large river, which, diſcharging itſelf not far off, into an arm of the ſea, or extenſive lake, ſwarmed with variety of fiſh. The woods were ſtocked with wild-fowl ; and the heaths and mountains behind them were the natural ſeat of the red-deer and roe. If we make allowance for the backward ſtate of agriculture, the valleys were not unfertile ; affording, if not all the conveniencies, at leaſt the neceſſaries of life. Here the chief lived, the ſupreme judge and law-giver of his own people ; but his ſway was neither ſevere nor unjuſt. As the populace regarded him as the chief of their blood, ſo he, in return, conſidered them as members of his family. His commands therefore, though abſolute and decifive, partook more of the authority of a father, than of the rigor of a judge. Though the whole territory of the tribe was conſidered as the property of the chief, yet his vaſſals made him no other conſideration for their lands than ſervices, neither burdenſome nor frequent. As he ſeldom went from home, he was at no expense. His table 
<!-- Was -->

<pb xml:id="P73210257" facs="../img/1773-812.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 2 -->
 was ſupplied by his own herds, and what his numerous attendants killed in hunting.</p><p><hi rend="sc">In</hi> this rural kind of magnificence, the Highland chiefs lived, for many ages. At a diſtance from the ſeat of government, and ſecured, by the inacceſſibleneſs of their country, they were free and independent. As they had little communication with ſtrangers, the cuſtoms of their anceſtors remained among them, and their language retained its original purity. Naturally fond of military fame, and remarkably attached to the memory of their anceſtors, they delighted in traditions and ſongs, concerning the exploits of their nation, and eſpecially of their own particular families. A ſucceſſion of bards was retained in every clan, to hand down the memorable actions of their foreſathers. As Fingal and his chiefs were the moſt renowned names in tradition, the bards took care to place them in the genealogy of every great family. They became famous among the people, and an object of fiction and poetry to the bards.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> bards erected their immediate patrons into heroes, and celebrated them in their ſongs. As the circle of their knowledge was narrow, their ideas were confined in proportion. A few happy expreſſions, and the manners they repreſent, may pleaſe thoſe who underſtand the 
<!-- Vor. Il, 5 gUIZC -->

<pb xml:id="P73210258" facs="../img/1773-815.pbm"/>
<!-- 253 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
  language; their obſcurity and inaccuracy would diſguſt in a tranſlation. It was chiefly for this reaſon, that I have rejected wholly the works of the bards in my publications. Oſſian acted in a more extenſive ſphere, and his ideas ought to be more noble and univerſal ; neither gives he, I preſume, ſo many of thoſe peculiarities, which are only underſtood in a certain period or country. The other bards have their beauties, but not in this ſpecies of compoſition. Their rhimes, only calculated to kindle a martial ſpirit among the vulgar, afford very little pleaſure to genuine taſte. This obſervation only regards their poems of the heroic kind; in every inferior ſpecies of poetry they are more ſucceſsful. They expreſs the tender melancholy of deſponding love, with ſimplicity and nature. So well adapted are the ſounds of the words to the ſentiments, that, even without any knowledge of the language they pierce and diſſolve the heart. Succeſsful love is expreſſed with peculiar tenderneſs and elegance. In all their compoſitions, except the heroic, which was ſolely calculated to animate the vulgar, they give us the genuine language of the heart, without any of thoſe affected ornaments of phraſeology, which, tho' intended to beautify ſentiments, diveſt them of their natural force. The ideas, it is confeſſed, 
<!-- are -->

<pb xml:id="P73210259" facs="../img/1773-818.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 2x9 -->
 are too local, to be admired, in another language ; to thoſe who are acquainted with the manners they repreſent, and the ſcenes they deſcribe, they muſt afford pleaſure and ſatiffaction.</p><p><hi rend="sc">It</hi> was the locality of their deſcription and ſentiment, that, probably, has kept them hitherto in the obſcurity of an almoſt loſt language. The ideas of an unpoliſhed period are ſo contrary to the preſent advanced ſtate of ſociety, that more than a common mediocrity of taſte is required, to reliſh them as they deſerve. Thoſe who alone are capable of transferring ancient poetry into a modern language, might be better employed in giving originals of their own, were it not for that wretched envy and meanneſs which affects to deſpiſe cotemporary genius. My firſt publication was merely accidental. Had I then met with leſs approbation, my after-purſuits would have been more profitable ; at leaft I might have continued to be ſtupid, without being branded with dulneſs.</p><p><hi rend="sc">These</hi> poems may furniſh light to antiquaries, as well as ſome pleaſure to the lovers of poetry. The firſt population of Ireland, its firſt kings, and ſeveral circumſtances, which regards its connection of old with the ſouth and north of Britain, are preſented in ſeveral epiſodes. The 
<!-- S 2 ſubject -->

<pb xml:id="P73210260" facs="../img/1773-821.pbm"/>
<!-- 260 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 ſubject and cataſtrophe of the poem are ſounded upon facts, which regarded the firſt peopling of that country, and the conteſts between the two Britiſh nations, who originally inhabited that iſland. In a preceding part of this Diſſertation, I have ſhewn how ſuperior the probability of this ſyſtem is to the undigeſted fictions of the Iriſh bards, and the more recent and regular legends of both Iriſh and Scottiſh hiſtorians. I mean not to give offence to the abettors of the high antiquities of the two nations, though I have all along expreſſed my doubts, concerning the veracity and abilities of thoſe who deliver down their antient hiſtory. For my own part, I prefer the national fame, ariſing from a few certain facts, to the legendary and uncertain annals of ages of remote and obſcure antiquity. No kingdom now eſtablithed in Europe can pretend to equal antiquity with that of the Scots, inconſiderable as it may appear in other reſpects, even according to my ſyſtem, ſo that it is altogether needleſs to fix its origin a fictitious millennium before.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Since</hi> the firſt publication of theſe poems, many inſinuations have been made, and doubts ariſen, concerning their authenticity. Whether theſe ſuſpicions are ſuggeſted by prejudice, or are only the effects of malice, I neither know nor 
<!-- Care -->

<pb xml:id="P73210261" facs="../img/1773-824.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 261 -->
 care. Thoſe who have doubted my veracity have paid a compliment to my genius ; and were even the allegation true, my ſelf-denial might have atoned for my fault. Without vanity I ſay it, I think I could write tolerable poetry ; and I aſſure my antagoniſts, that I ſhould not tranſlate what I could not imitate.</p><p>As prejudice is the effect of ignorance, I am not ſurprized at its being general. An age that produces few marks of genius ought to be ſparing of admiration. The truth is, the bulk of mankind have ever been led, by reputation more than taſte, in articles of literature. If all the Romans, who admired Virgil, underſtood his beauties, he would have ſcarce deſerved to have come down to us, through ſo many centuries. Unleſs genius were in faſhion, Homer himſelf might have written in vain. He that wiſhes to come with weight, on the ſuperficial, muſt ſkim the ſurface, in their own ſhallow way. Were my aim to gain the many, I wou'd write a madrigal ſooner than an heroic poem. Laberius himſelf would be always ſure of more followers than Sophocles.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Some</hi> who doubt the authenticity of this work, with peculiar acuteneſs appropriate them to the Iriſh nation. Tho' it is not eaſy to conceive how theſe poems can belong to Ireland and to me, at 
<!-- SD 3 once, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210262" facs="../img/1773-827.pbm"/>
<!-- 262 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 once, [ ſhall examine the ſubject, without further animadverſion on the blunder.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Of</hi> all the nations deſcended from the antient <hi>Celtæ</hi>, the Scots and Iriſh are the moſt ſimilar in language, cuſtoms, and manners. This argues a more intimate connection between them, than a remote deſcent from the great Celtic ſtock. It is evident, in ſhort, that at ſome one period or other, they formed one ſociety, were ſubject to the ſame government, and were, in all reſpects, one and the ſame people. How they became divided, which the colony, or which the mother nation, I have in another work amply diſcuſſed. The firft circumſtance that induced me to diſregard the vulgarly-received opinion of the Hibernian extraction of the Scottiſh nation, was my obſervations on their antient language. That dialect of the Celtic tongue, ſpoken in the north of Scotland, is much more pure, more agreeable to its mother language, and more abounding with primitives, than that now ſpoken, or even that which has been written for ſome centuries back, amongſt the moſt unmixed part of the Iriſh nation. A Scotchman, tolerably converſant in his own language, underſtands an Iriſh compoſition, from that derivative analogy which it has to the <hi>Galic</hi> of North Britain. An Iriſhman, on the other hand, withoat the aid of fiudy, can never underſtand 
<!-- 7 A com- -->

<pb xml:id="P73210263" facs="../img/1773-830.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 263 -->
 a compoſition in the Galic tongue. This affords a proof, that the Scotch Galic is the moſt origipal, and, conſequently, the language of a more ancient and unmixed people. The Iriſh, however backward they may be to allow any thing to the prejudice of their antiquity, ſeem inadvertently to acknowledge it, by the very appellation they give to the dialect they ſpeak. They call their own language <hi>Calic, Eirinach</hi>, i. e. <hi>Caledonian Iriſh</hi>, when, on the contrary, they call the dialctt of North-Britain <hi>a Chalic</hi>, or the <hi>Caledoman tongue</hi>, emphatically. A circumftance of this nature tends more to decide which is the moſt antient nation, than the united teſtimonies of a whole legion of ignorant bards and ſenachies, who, perhaps, never dreamed of bringing the Scots from Spain to Ireland, till ſome one of them, more learned than the reſt, diſcovered, that the Romans called the firſt <hi>Iberia</hi>, and the latter <hi>Hibernia</hi>. On ſuch a ſlight foundation were probably built the romantic fictions, concerning the Mileſians of Ircland.</p><p><hi rend="sc">From</hi> internal proofs it ſufficiently appears, that the poems publiſhed under the name of Oſſian, are not of Iriſh compoſition. The favourite chimæra, that Ireland is the mother-country of the Scots, is totally ſubverted and ruined. The fictions concerning the antiquities 
<!-- S of -->

<pb xml:id="P73210264" facs="../img/1773-833.pbm"/>
<!-- 264 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 of that country, which were forming for ages, and growing as they came down, on the hands of ſucceſſive <hi>ſenachies</hi> and <hi>fileas</hi>, are found, at laſt, to be the ſpurious brood of modern and ignorant ages. To thoſe who know how tenacious the Iriſh are, of their pretended <hi>Iberian</hi> deſcent, this alone is proof ſufficient, that poems, ſo ſubverſive of their ſyſtem, could never be produced by an Hibernian bard. But when we look to the language, it is ſo different from the Iriſh dialect, that it would be as ridiculous to think, that Milton's Paradiſe Loſt could be wrote by a Scottiſh peaſant, as to ſuppoſe, that the poems aſcribed to Oſſian were writ in Ireland.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> pretenſions of Ireland to Oſſian proceed from another quarter. There are handed down, in that country, traditional poems, concerning the <hi>Fiona</hi>, or the heroes of <hi>Fion Mac Comnal</hi>. This <hi>Fion</hi>, ſay the Iriſh annaliſts, was general of the militia of Ireland, in the reign of Cormac, in the third century. Where Keating and O'Flaherty learned, that Ireland had an <hi>embodied</hi> militia ſo early, is not eaſy for me to determine. Their information certainly did not come from the Iriſh poems,concerning Fion. I have juſt now, in my hands, all that remain, of thoſe 
<!-- 8 fitions ; -->

<pb xml:id="P73210265" facs="../img/1773-836.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 26s -->
  compoſitions; but, unluckily for the antiquities of Ireland, they appear to be the work of a very modern period. Every ſtanza, nay almoſt every line, affords ſtriking proofs, that they cannot be three centuries old. Their alluſions to the manners and cuſtoms of the fifteenth century, are ſo many, that it is matter of wonder to me, how any one could dream of their antiquity. They are entirely writ in that romantic taſte, which prevailed two ages ago. Giants, enchanted caſtles, dwarfs, palfreys, witches and magicians form the whole circle of the poet's invention. The celebrated <hi>Fion</hi> could ſcarcely move from one hillock to another, without encountering a giant, or being entangled in the circles of a magician. Witches, on broomſticks, were continually hovering round him, like crows; and he had freed enchanted virgins in every valley in Ireland. In ſhort, <hi>Fion</hi>, great as he was, paſſed a diſagreeable life. Not only had he to engage all the miſchiefs in his own country, foreign armies invaded him, aſſiſted by magicians and witches, and headed by Kings, as tall as the main-maſt of a firſt rate. It muſt be owned, however, that <hi>Fion</hi> was not inferior to them in height. 
<!-- ? A chos -->

<pb xml:id="P73210266" facs="../img/1773-839.pbm"/>
<!-- 266 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
</p><p>A chos air <hi>Cromleach</hi>, druim-ard,\ Chos eile air Crom-meal dubh,\ Thoga <hi>Fion</hi> le lamh mhoir\ An d'uiſge o <hi>Lubhair</hi> na fruth.\</p><p>With one foot on <hi>Cromleach</hi> his brow,\ The other on <hi>Crommal</hi> the dark,\ <hi>Fion</hi> took up with his large hand\ The water from <hi>Lubar</hi> of the ſtreams.\</p><p><hi>Cromleach</hi> and <hi>Crommal</hi> were two mountains in the neighbourhood of one another, in Ulſter, and the river <hi>Lubar</hi> ran through the intermediate valley. The property of ſuch a monſter as this <hi>Fion</hi>, I ſhould never have diſputed with any nation. But the bard himſelf, in the poem, from which the above quotation is taken, cedes him to Scotland.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Fion o Albin</hi>, fiol nan laoich !\ <hi rend="sc">Fion</hi> <hi>from</hi> <hi rend="sc">Albion</hi>, <hi>race of heroes</hi> !\</p><p>Were it allowable to contradict the authority of a bard, at this diſtance of time, I ſhould have given as my opinion, that this enormous <hi>Fion</hi> was of the race of the Hibernian giants, of Ruanus, or ſome other celebrated name, rather than 
<!-- a native -->

<pb xml:id="P73210267" facs="../img/1773-842.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 267 -->

a native of Caledonia, whoſe inhabitants, now at 
leaſt, are not remarkable for their ſtature. As 
for the poetry, I leave it to the reader. 
 
<hi rend="sc">If</hi> <hi>Fion</hi> was ſo remarkable for his ſtature, his 
heroes had alſo other extraordinary properties. 
<hi>In weight all the ſons of ſtrangers</hi> yielded to the 
celebrated Ton-iofal ; and for hardneſs of ſkull, 
and, perhaps, for thickneſs too, the valiant 
Oſcar ſtood <hi>unrivalled and alone</hi>. Oſſian himſelf 
 had many ſingular and leſs delicate qualifications, 
than playing on the harp; and the brave Cuthullin 
was of ſo diminutive a ſize, as to be taken for 
a child of two years of age, by the gigantic 
Swaran. To illuſtrate this ſubject, 1 ſhall here 
lay before the reader, the hiſtory of ſome of the 
Iriſh poems, concerning Fion Mac Comnal. A 
tranflation of theſe pieces, if well executed, 
might afford ſatisfaction, in an uncommon way, 
to the Public. But this ought to be the work 
of a native of Ireland. To draw forth, from 
obſcurity, the poems of my own country, 
has waſted all the time I had allotted for the 
muſes ; beſides, I am too diffident of my own 
abilities, to undertake ſuch a work. A gentleman 
in Dublin accuſed me to the public, of 
committing blunders and abſurdities, in tranflating 
the language of my own country, and 

<!-- that -->

<pb xml:id="P73210268" facs="../img/1773-845.pbm"/>
<!-- 268 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 that before any tranſlation of mine appeared<note><p> In Faulkner's Dublin Journal, of the 1ſt December, 1761, appeared the following Advertiſement : two weeks before my firſt publication appeared in London.</p><p>Speedily will be publiſhed, by a gentleman of this kingdom, who hath been, for ſome time paft, employed in tranſlating and writing hiſtorical Notes to FINGAL, 
<hi rend="sc">A poem</hi>, Originally wrote in the Iriſh or Erſe language. In the preface to which, the tranſlator, who is a perfect maſter of the Iriſh tongue, will give an account of the manners and cuſtoms of the antient Iriſh or Scotch ; and, therefore, moſt humbly intreats the public, to wait for his edition, which will appear in a ſhort time, as he will ſet forth all the blunders and abſurdities in the edition now printing in London, and ſhew the ignorance of the Engliſh tranſlator, in his knowlege of Iriſh grammar, not underſtanding any part of that accidence. </p></note>. How the gentleman came to ſee my blunders before I committed them, is not eaſy to determine; if he did not conclude, that, as a Scotſman, and, of courſe deſcended of the Mileſian race, I might have committed ſome of thoſe overſights, which, perhaps very unjuſtly, are ſaid to be peculiar to them.</p><p><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the whole tenor of the Iriſh poems, concerning the <hi>Fiona</hi>, it appears, that <hi>Fion Mac Comnal</hi> flouriſhed inthe reign of Cormac, which is placed, by the univerſal conſent of the ſenachies, in the third century. They even fix the death 
<!-- of -->

<pb xml:id="P73210269" facs="../img/1773-848.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 269 -->
 of Fingal in the year 286, yet his ſon Oſſian is made cotemporary with St. Patrick, who preached the goſpel in Ireland about the middle of the fifth age. Oſſian, though, at that time, he muſt have been two hundred and fifty years of age, had a daughter young enough to become wife to the faint. On account of this family connection, <hi>Patrick of the Pſalms</hi>, for ſo the apoſtle of Ireland is emphatically called in the poems, took great delight in the company of Oſſian, and in hearing the great actions of his family. The ſaint ſometimes threw off the aufterity of his profeſſion, drunk freely, and had his ſoul properly warmed with wine, to receive with becoming enthuſiaſm, the poems of his father-in-law. One of the poems begins with this piece of uſeful information,</p><p>Lo don rabh <hi rend="sc">Padric</hi> na mhúr,\ Gun <hi>Sailm</hi> air uidh, ach a gól,\ Ghluais é thigh <hi>Oſſian</hi> mhic <hi>Fhion</hi>,\ O fan leis bu bhinn a ghloir.\</p><p>The title of this poem is <hi>Teantach mor na Fiona</hi>. It appears to have been founded on the ſame ſtory with the <hi>battle of Lora</hi>. The circumſtances and cataſtrophe in both are much the ſame; but 
<!-- the -->

<pb xml:id="P73210270" facs="../img/1773-851.pbm"/>
<!-- 2750 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 the <hi>Iriſh Oſſian</hi> diſcovers the age in which he lived, by an unlucky anachroniſm. After deſcribing the total route of Erragon, he very gravely concludes with this remarkable anecdote, that none of the foe eſcaped, but a few, who were permitted to go on a pilgrimage to the <hi>Holy Land</hi>. This circumſtance fixes the date of the compofition of the piece ſome centuries after the famous croiſade; for, it is evident, that the poet thought the time of the croiſade ſo ancient, that he conſounds it with the age of Fingal. Erragon, in the courſe of this poem, is often called,</p><p>Riogh <hi>Lochlin</hi> an do ſhloigh,\ <hi>King of Denmark of two nations</hi>\</p><p>which alludes to the union of the kingdoms of Norway and Denmark, a circumſtance which happened under Margaret de Waldemar, in the cloſe of the fourteenth age. Modern, however, as this pretended Oſſian was, it is certain, he lived before the Iriſh had dreamed of appropriating <hi>Fion</hi>, or <hi>Fingal</hi>, to themſelves. He concludes the poem, with this reflection.</p><p>Na fagha fe comhthróm nan n' arm,\ Erragon Mac Annir nan lánn glas\ 
<!-- 'San -->

<pb xml:id="P73210271" facs="../img/1773-854.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 2y1 -->
 'San n' <hi rend="sc">Albin</hi> ni n' abairtair Triath\ Agus ghlaoite an n' <hi>Fhiona</hi> as.\</p><p>“Had Erragon, ſon of Annir of gleaming ſwords, avoided the equal conteſt of arms, (ſingle combat) no chief ſhould have afterwards been numbered in <hi rend="sc">Albion</hi>, and the heroes of Fion ſhould no more be named.”</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> next poem that falls under our obſervation is <hi>Cath-cabhra</hi>, or, <hi>The death of Oſcar</hi>. This piece is ſounded on the ſame ſtory which we have in the firft book of Temora. So little thought the author of Cath-cabhra of making Oſcar his countryman, that, in the courſe of two hundred lines, of which the poems conſifts, he puts the following expreſſion thrice in the mouth of the hero :</p><p><hi rend="sc">Albin</hi> an fa d' roina m' arach.\ <hi rend="sc">Albion</hi> <hi>where I was born and bred</hi>.</p><p>The poem contains almoſt all the incidents in the firſt book of Temora. In one circumſtance the bard differs materially from Oſſian. Oſcar, after he was mortally wounded by Cairbar, was carried by his people to a neighbouring hill, which commanded a proſpect of the ſea. A fleet appeared at a diſtance, and the hero exclaims with joy, 
<!-- Loingeas -->

<pb xml:id="P73210272" facs="../img/1773-857.pbm"/>
<!-- 273 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 Loingeas mo ſhean-athair at' án\ 'S iad a tiächd le cabhair chugain,\ <hi rend="sc">O Albin</hi> na n' ioma ſtuagh.\</p><p>“It is the fleet of my grandfather, coming with aid to our field, from <hi rend="sc">Albion</hi> of many waves !” —The teſtimony of this bard is ſufficient to confute the idle fictions of Keating and O'Flaherty ; for, though he is far from being ancient, it is probable, he flouriſhed a full century before theſe hiſtorians. He appears, however, to have been a much better chriſtian than chronologer; for <hi>Fion</hi>, though he is placed two centuries before St. Patrick, very devoutly recommends the ſoul of his grandſon to his Redeemer.</p><p><hi>Duan a Gharibh Mac-Starn</hi> is another Iriſh poem in high repute. The grandeur of its images, and its propriety of ſentiment, might have induced me to give a tranſlation of it, had not I ſome expectations, which are now over, of ſeeing it in the collection of the Iriſh Oſſian's poems, promiſed twelve years ſince, to the public. The author deſcends ſometimes from the region of the ſublime to low and indecent deſcription; the laſt of which, the Iriſh tranſlator, no doubt, will chooſe to leave in the obſcurity of the original. In this piece Cuthullin is uſed with very little ceremony, for he is oft called, the <hi>dog of 
<!-- Tara, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210273" facs="../img/1773-860.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN: 213 -->
 Tara</hi>, in the county of Meath. This ſevere title of the <hi>redoubtable Cuthullin</hi>, the moſt renowned of  Iriſh champions, proceeded from the poet's ignorance of etymology. <hi rend="sc">Cu</hi>, <hi>voice</hi>, or commander, ſignifies alſo a <hi>dog</hi>. The poet choſe the laſt, as the moſt noble appellation for his hero.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſubject of the poem is the ſame with that of the epic poem of Fingal. <hi>Caribh Mac-Starn</hi> is the ſame with Oſſian's Swaran, the ſon of Starno. His ſingle combats with, and his victory over all the heroes of Ireland, excepting the <hi>celebrated dog of Tara</hi>, i. e. Cuthullin, afford matter for two hundred lines of tolerable poetry. <hi>Caribh</hi>'s progreſs in ſearch of Cuthullin, and his intrigue with the gigantic Emir-bragal, that hero's wife, enables the poet to extend his piece to four hundred lines. This author, it is true, makes Cuthullin a native of Ireland ; the gigantic Emir-bragal he calls the <hi>guiding ſtar of the women of Ireland</hi>. The property of this enormous lady I ſhall not diſpute with him, or any other. But, as he ſpeaks with great tenderneſs of the <hi>daughters of the convent</hi>, and throws out ſome hints againſt the Englith nation, it is probable he lived in too modern a period to be intimately acquainted with the genealogy of Cuthullin. 
<!-- Vol. II. T ANOTHER -->

<pb xml:id="P73210274" facs="../img/1773-863.pbm"/>
<!-- 274 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
</p><p><hi rend="sc">Another</hi> Iriſh Oſſian, for there were many, as appears from their difference in language and ſentiment, ſpeaks very dogmatically of <hi>Fion Mac Comnal</hi>, as an Iriſhman. Little can be ſaid for the judgment of this poet, and leſs for his delicacy of ſentiment. The hiſtory of one of his epiſodes may, at once, ſtand as a ſpecimen of his want of both. Ireland, in the days of <hi>Fion</hi>, happened to be threatened with an invaſion, by three great potentates, the kings of Lochlin, Sweden, and France. lt is needleſs to inſiſt upon the impropriety of a French invaſion of Ireland ; it is ſufficient for me to be faithful to the language of my author. <hi>Fion</hi>, upon receiving intelligence of the intended invaſion, ſent Ca-olt, Oſſian, and Oſcar, to watch the bay, in which, it was apprehended, the enemy was to land. Oſcar was the worſt choice of a ſcout that could be made, for, brave as he was, he had the bad property of falling very often aſleep on his poſt, nor was it poſſible to awake him, without cutting off one of his fingers, or daſhing a large ſtone againſt his head. When the enemy appeared, Oſcar, very unfortunately, was aſleep. Oſſian and Ca-olt conſulted about the method of wakening him, and they, at laſt, fixed on the ſtone, as the leſs dangerous expedient. 
<!-- Gun -->

<pb xml:id="P73210275" facs="../img/1773-866.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN, 275 -->
</p><p>Gun thog Caoilte a chlach, nach gán,\ Agus a n' aigha' chican gun bhuail ;\ Tri mil an tulloch gun chri', &amp;c.\</p><p>“Ca-olt took up a heavy ſtone, and ſtruck it againſt the hero's head. The hill ſhook for three miles, as the ſtone rebounded and rolled away.” Oſcar roſe in wrath, and his father gravely defired him to ſpend his rage on his enemies, which he did to ſo good purpoſe, that he ſingly routed a whole wing of their army. The confederate kings advanced, notwithſtanding, till they came to a narrow paſs, poſſeſſed by the celebrated Ton-iofal. This name is very ſignificant of the ſingular property of the hero who bore it. Ton-iofal, though brave, was ſo heavy and unwieldy, that when he ſat down, it took the whole force of an hundred men to ſet him upright on his feet again. Luckily for the preſervation of Ireland, the hero happened to be ſtanding when the enemy appeared, and he gave ſo good an account of them, that <hi>Fion</hi>, upon his arrival, ſound little to do, but to divide the ſpoil among his ſoldiers,</p><p><hi rend="sc">All</hi> theſe extraordinary heroes, Fion, Oſſian, Oſcar and Ca-olt, ſays the poet, were 
<!-- T2 Liol -->

<pb xml:id="P73210276" facs="../img/1773-869.pbm"/>
<!-- 2356 A DISSERTATION concerning 'the -->
</p><p>Siol <hi rend="sc">Erin</hi> na gorm lánn,\ <hi>The ſons of</hi> <hi rend="sc">Erin</hi> <hi>of blue ſteel</hi>.\</p><p>Neither ſhall I much diſpute the matter with him : He has my conſent alſo to appropriate to Ireland the celebrated Ton-iofal. I ſhall only ſay, that they are different perſons from thoſe of the ſame name, in the Scotch poems ; and that, though the ſtupendous valour of the firſt is ſo remarkable, they have not been equally lucky with the latter, in their poet. It is ſomewhat extraordinary, that <hi>Fion</hi>, who lived ſome ages before St. Patrick, ſwears like a very good chriſtian :</p><p>Air an Dia do chum gach <hi>caſe</hi>.\ <hi>By God, who ſhaped every caſe</hi>.\</p><p>It is worthy of being remarked, that, in the line quoted, Oſſian, who lived in St. Patrick's days, ſeems to have underſtood ſomething of the Engliſh, a language not then ſubſiſting. A perſon, more ſanguine for the honour of his country than I am, might argue, from this circumſtance, that this pretendedly Iriſh Ofſian was a native of Scotland ; for my countrymen are univerſally allowed to have an excluſive right to the ſecond-ſight. 
<!-- FROM -->

<pb xml:id="P73210277" facs="../img/1773-872.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 277 -->
</p><p>From the inſtances given, the reader may form a complete idea of the Iriſh compoſitions concerning the <hi>Fiona</hi>, The greateſt part of them make the heroes of <hi>Fion</hi>,</p><p>Siol <hi rend="sc">Albin</hi> a n'nioma caoile.\ <hi>The race of</hi> <hi rend="sc">Albion</hi> <hi>of many firths</hi>.\</p><p>The reſt make them natives of Ireland. But, the truth is, that their authority is of little conſequence on either ſide. From the inſtances I have given, they appear to have been the work of a very modern period. The pious ejaculations they contain, their alluſions to the manners of the times, fix them to the fifteenth century. Had even the authors of theſe pieces avoided all alluſions to their own times, it is 1mpoſſible that the poems could paſs for ancient, in the eyes of any perſon tolerably converſant with the Iriſh tongue. The idiom is ſo corrupted and ſo many words borrowed from the Engliſh, that the language muſt have made conſiderable progreſs in Ireland before the poems were written.</p><p><hi rend="sc">It</hi> remains now to ſhew, how the Iriſh bards begun to appropriate the Scottiſh Oſſian and his he- . roes to their own country. After the Engliſh conqueſt, many of the natives of Ireland, averſe to a foreign yoke, either actually were in a ſtate of hoſtility with the conquerors, or at leaſt, paid 
<!-- T 3 little -->

<pb xml:id="P73210278" facs="../img/1773-875.pbm"/>

<!-- 278 A DISSERTATION concerning the -->
 little regard to their government. The Scots, in thoſe ages, were often in open war, and never in cordial friendſhip with the Engliſh. The ſimilarity of manners and language, the traditions concerning their common origin, and above all, their having to do with the ſame enemy, created a free and friendly intercourſe between the Scottiſh and Iriſh nations. As the cuſtom of retaining bards and ſenachies was common to both ; ſo each, no doubt, had formed a ſyſtem of hiſtory, it matters not how much ſoever fabulous, concerning their reſpectve origin. It was the natural policy of the times, to reconcile the traditions of both nations together, and, if poſſible, to reduce them from the ſame original ſtock.</p><p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Saxon manners and language had, at that time, made great progreſs in the ſouth of Scotland. The ancient language, and the traditional hiſtory of the nation, became confined entirely to the inhabitants of the Highlands, then fallen, from ſeveral concurring circumſtances, into the laſt degree of ignorance and barbariſm. The Iriſh, who, for ſome ages before the conqueſt, had poſſeſſed a competent ſhare of that kind of learning, which then prevailed in Europe, ſound it no difficult matter to impoſe their own fictions on the ignorant Highland ſenachies. By flattering the vanity of the Highlanders, with 
<!-- 6 their -->

<pb xml:id="P73210279" facs="../img/1773-878.pbm"/>
<!-- POEMS of OSSIAN. 279 -->
 their long liſt of Heremonian kings and heroes, they, without contradiction, aſſumed to themſelves the character of being the mother-nation of the Scots of Britain. At this time, certainly, was eſtabliſhed that Hibernian ſyſtem of the original of the Scots, which afterwards, for want of any other, was univerſally received. The Scots of the low-country, who, by lofing the language of their anceſtors, loſt, together with it, their national traditions, received, implicitly, the hiſtory of their country, from Iriſh refugees, or from Highland ſenachies, perſuaded over into the Hibernian ſyſtem.</p><p><hi rend="sc">These</hi> circumſtances are far from being ideal. We have remaining many particular traditions, which bear teſtimony to a fact, of itſelf abundantly probable. What makes the matter inconteſtible is, that the antient traditional accounts of the genuine origin of the Scots, have been handed down without interruption. Tho' a few ignorant ſenachies might be perſuaded out of their own opinion, by the ſmoothneſs of an Iriſh tale, it was impoſſible to eradicate, from among the bulk of the people, their own national traditions. Thefe traditions afterwards ſo much prevailed, that the Highlanders continue totally unacquainted with the pretended Hibernian extract of the Scots nation. Ignorant chronicle 
<!-- T 4 writers, -->

<pb xml:id="P73210280" facs="../img/1773-881.pbm"/>
<!-- 20 A DISSERTATION, &amp;c. -->
 writers, ſtrangers to the antient language of their country, preſerved only from falling to the ground, ſo improbable a ſtory.</p><p><hi rend="sc">This</hi> ſubject, perhaps, is purſued further than it deſerves; but a diſcuſſion of the pretenſions of Ireland, was become in ſome meaſure neceſſary. If the Iriſh poems, concerning the <hi>Fiona</hi>, ſhould appear ridiculous, it is but juſtice to obferve, that they are ſcarcely more ſo than the poems of other nations, at that period. On other ſubjects, the bards of Ireland have diſplayed a genius for poetry. It was, alone, in matters of antiquity, that they were monſtrous in their fables. Their love-ſonnets, and their elegies on the death of perſons worthy or renowned, abound with ſimplicity, and a wild harmony of numbers. They become more than an atonement for their errors, in every other ſpecies of poetry. But the beauty of theſe pieces, depends ſo much on a certain <hi>curioſa felicitas</hi> of expreſſion in the original, that they muſt appear much to diſadvantage in another language. 

</p>
</body></text>