<front xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb n="73200001" facs="1773-020.pbm"/>
 <div type="advertisements">
  <head><hi>This Day is Publiſhed</hi>, </head>
  <p> By T. BECKET, Corner of the Adelphi Buildings in the STRAND,</p>
  <p>Bookſeller to their Royal Highneſſes the Prince of <hi rend="sc">Wales</hi> and Biſhop of <hi
   rend="sc">Osnaburgh</hi>,</p>
  <p>FABLES de La FONTAINE,</p>
  <p>Printed at Paris, in Four Volumes Folio.</p>
  <p>This very magnificent Work is propoſed to the Publick at only <hi>Eight</hi> Guineas in Sheets,
   being but Half the original Price.</p>
  <p>This Edition, which coſt the Artiſts near twenty Years Labour, and the Proprietors upwards of
   <hi>Fourteen thouſand Pounds Sterling</hi>, is undoubtedly one of the moſt ſuperb Monuments ever
   erected to the Memory of an Author.</p>
  <p>It is printed with a new Letter, on a fine Paper, manufactured expreſsly for the Work ; every
   Fable being ornamented by a Head and Tail-piece, deſigned in a new Taſte, by M. <hi rend="sc"
   >Bachelier</hi>, and executed by M. <hi rend="sc">T. Papillon</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Le
   Sueur</hi>,</p>
  <p>To the Beauty this Work derives from the Printing-preſs, is alſo added the capital
   Embelliſhment of no leſs than <hi rend="sc">Two Hundred</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Seventy-six</hi>
   Copper-plates; the Deſigns applicable to the Subjects, drawn after Nature, by <hi rend="sc"
   >Oudry</hi>, one of the moſt celebrated Painters France ever produced for delineating the Animal
   Creation. The Engravings by the moſt expert Artiſts in their ſeveral Departments, under the
   Direction of the celebrated M. <hi rend="sc">Cochin</hi> ; who reviſed and ſuperintended the
   Whole.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">La Fontaine</hi>'s Life is prefixed, containing many Anecdotes of that exquiſite
   Fabuliſt, not to be met with elſewhere.</p>
  <p> * * Such Ladies and Gentlemen who are deſirous of being poſſeſſed of this magnificent Work,
   are requeſted to ſavour the Proprietors with their Commands. <!--  -->
   <!-- Vol. II, A The --></p>
  <p>
   <!--  -->
   <pb n="73200002" facs="1773-023.pbm"/> The following <hi rend="sc">books</hi> are publiſhed by
   <hi rend="sc">t. becket</hi>:</p>
  <list>
   <item>
    <p>1. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> Iliad of Homer. Tranſlated by James Macpherſon, Eſq; in 2 Vols.
    Royal Paper. 4to. Second Edition, reviſed throughout, and carefully corrected. Price One Guinea
    and a Half in Boards.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>2. An Introduction to the Hiſtory of Great Britain and Ireland. The Third Edition, reviſed
    and greatly enlarged. In one Volume 4to. Price 15 s. in Boards.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>3. Memoirs of Ruſſia, from the Year 1727 to the Year 1944. Tranſlated from the Original
    Manuſcript of the Baron de <hi rend="sc">Manstein</hi>. Illuſtrated with Maps and Plans, and
    with the Life of the Author. The Second Edition, carefully corrected throughout, and greatly
    improved. In one Volume 4to. Price 18s. in Boards.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>4. The Hiſtory of the Britiſh Dominions in North America; from the firſt Diſcovery of that
    vaſt Continent by Sebaſtian Cabot, in 1497, to its glorious Eſtabliſhment, as confirmed by the
    late Treaty of Peace in 1763. In 14 Books. Illuſtrated with a new and accurate Map, coloured. In
    one Volume 4to. Price 18s. in Boards.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>5. A Journal of the Swediſh Ambaſſy, in the Years 1653 and 1054, from the Commonwealth of
    England, Scotland, and Ireland. Written by the Ambaſſador the Lord Commiſſioner <hi rend="sc"
    >White-locke</hi>, With an <hi rend="sc">Appendix</hi> of Original Papers. 2 Vols. 4to. 1l. 11s.
    6d. Boards.</p>
    <p>** This very curious and valuable Work is printed from the Author's own Manuſcript (which is
    depoſited in the Britiſh Muſeum for public Inſpection) and at the Requeſt of his Grandſon
    Carleton Whitelocke, of Prior's Wood, near Dublin, Eſq; of Lord Chancellor Bowes, late of the
    Kingdom of Ireland ; of Archbiſhop Secker, late Primate of all England; and of Arthur Onflow,
    Eſq; late Speaker of the Houſe of Commons.</p> </item>
   <item>
    <p>6. Dr. Goldſmith's Hiſtory of England, to the Acceſſion of his preſent Majeſty. Tlluſtrated
    with the Heads of all the Kings and Queens. 4 Vols. 8vo. 1l. 4s. bound.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>7. Atkyn's Antiquities of Gloceſterſhire, With a great Number of fine Plates. Folio. Large
    Paper. 3l. 3s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>8. The ſame Book. Small Paper, 2l. 10s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>9. Harrington's Works. New Edition. Royal Quarto, 1l. 1s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>10. Ludlow's Memoirs, New Edition. Royal Quarto. 1l. 1s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>11. The Works of Algernon Sidney. New Edition. Royal Quarto, 1l. 7s.</p> </item>
   <item>
    <p>12. Addiſon's Works. Beautifully printed by Baſkerville. 4 Vols. Royal Quarto. 4l.
    4s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>13. Pope's Works. New Edition. 6 Vols. 12mo. 18s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>14. —— Homer. New Edition. 9 Vols. 12mo. 1l. 7s.</p></item>
   <item>
    <p>15. —— Ditto. New Edition. 9 Vols. Small 8vo. 1l. 11s. 6d. </p></item>
  </list>
 </div>
 <!--  -->
 <!--   -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb n="73200003" facs="1773-026.pbm"/>
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb n="73200004" facs="1773-029.pbm"/>
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb n="73200005" facs="1773-032.pbm"/>
 <titlePage>
  <docTitle>
   <titlePart>THE POEMS OF OSSIAN.</titlePart>
   <titlePart>TRANSLATED By JAMES MACPHERSON, Eſq: </titlePart>
   <titlePart>IN TWO VOLUMES. </titlePart>
   <titlePart>VOL. II.</titlePart>
  </docTitle>
  <docEdition>A NEW EDITION, Carefully corrected, and greatly improved.</docEdition>
  <docImprint>LONDON: Printed for <hi rend="sc">W. Strahan</hi>; and <hi rend="sc">T. Becket</hi>,
   in the Strand, Bookſeller to their Royal Highneſſes the Prince of <hi rend="sc">Wales</hi> and
   Biſhop of <hi rend="sc">Osnabrugh</hi>.</docImprint>
  <docDate>MDCCLXXIII. </docDate>
 </titlePage>
 
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb n="73200006" facs="1773-035.pbm"/>
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb n="73200007" facs="1773-038.pbm"/>
 <!--   -->
 <!--  -->
 <!--   -->
 <div type="contents">
  <head>CONTENTS OF THE SECOND VOLUME.</head>
<list><item>
  <p>TEMORA, Book I — — Page 1 Book II. — — 29 Book III. — — 53 Book IV. — — 75 Book V. — — 97 Book
   VI. — — 117 Book VII. — — 139 Book VIII. — — 157</p>
  <p>CONLATH and CUTHONA, — 181</p>
  <p>BERRATHON, — — — 191</p>
  <p>A DISSERTATION concerning the ÆRA of OSSIAN, — — 211</p>
  <p>A DISSERTATION concerning the POEMS of OSSIAN, — 233</p>
  <p>A critical DISSERTATION on the POEMS of OSSIAN, — 281 </p></item></list>
 </div>
 <!--  -->
 <!-- 3 TE- -->
 <!--  -->
 <pb n="73200008" facs="1773-041.pbm"/>
 <!--  -->
 <!--  -->
</front>
