<div type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73210157" facs="../img/1773-512.pbm"/>
 <head>TEMORA: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK VIII. </head>

 <pb xml:id="P73210158" facs="../img/1773-515.pbm"/>
 <div type="argument">
  <head>ARGUMENT to Book VIII.</head>
  <p> The fourth morning, from the opening of the poem, comes on. Fingal, ſtill continuing in the
   place, to which he had retired on the preceding night, is ſeen, at intervals, thro' the miſt,
   which covered the rock of Cormul. The deſcent of the king is deſcribed. He orders Gaul, Dermid,
   and Carril the bard, to go to the valley of Cluna, and conduct, from thence, to the Caledonian
   army, Ferad-artho, the ſon of Cairbre, the only perſon remaining of the family of Conar, the
   firſt king of Ireland. The king takes the command of the army, and prepares for battle. Marching
   towards the enemy, he comes to the cave of Luber, where the body of Fillan lay. Upon ſeeing his
   dog Bran, who lay at the entrance of the cave, his grief returns. Cathmor arranges the Iriſh army
   in order of battle. The appearance of that hero. The general conflict is deſcribed. The actions
   of Fingal and Cathmor. A ſtorm. The total rout of the Firbolg. The two kings engage, in a column
   of miſt, on the banks of Lubar. Their attitude and conference after the combat. The death of
   Cathmor. Fingal reſigns <hi>the ſpear of Trenmor</hi> to Oſſian. The ceremonies obſerved on that
   occaſion. The ſpirit of Cathmor, in the mean time, appears to Sul-malla, in the valley of Lona.
   Her ſorrow. Evening comes on. A feaſt is prepared. The coming of Ferad-artho is announced by the
   ſongs of a hundred bards. The poem cloſes, with a ſpeech of Fingal. </p>
 </div>

 <pb xml:id="P73210159" facs="../img/1773-518.pbm"/>
 <!-- [159] -->
 <div type="poem">
  <head>TEMORA: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK VIII.</head>
  <p> <hi rend="sc">As</hi> when the wintry winds have ſeized the waves of the mountain-lake, have
   ſeized them, in ſtormy night, and cloathed them over with ice; white, to the hunter's early eye,
   the billows ſtill ſeem to roll. He turns his ear to the ſound of each unequal ridge. But each is
   ſilent, gleaming, ſtrewn with boughs and tufts of graſs, which ſhake and whiſtle to the wind,
   over their grey ſeats of froſt. So ſilent ſhone to the morning the ridges of Morven's hoft, as
   each warrior looked up from his helmet towards the hill of the king; the cloud-covered hill of
   Fingal, where he ſtrode, in the folds of miſt. At times is the hero ſeen, greatly dim in all his
   arms. <!-- From -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210160" facs="../img/1773-521.pbm"/>
   <!-- 160 T E M © R A: Book VIIL. --> From thought to thought rolled the war, along his mighty
   ſoul.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Now</hi> is the coming forth of the king. Firſt appeared the ſword of Luno; the
   ſpear half iſſuing from a cloud, the ſhield ſtill dim in miſt. But when the ſtride of the king
   came abroad, with all his grey, dewy locks in the wind ; then roſe the ſhouts of his hoſt over
   every moving tribe. They gathered, gleaming, round, with all their ecchoing ſhields. So riſe the
   green ſeas round a ſpirit, that comes down from the ſqually wind. The traveller hears the ſound
   afar, and lifts his head over the rock. He looks on the troubled bay, and thinks he dimly ſees
   the form. The waves ſport, unwieldy, round, with all their backs of foam.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Far-distant</hi> ſtood the ſon of Morni, Duthno's race, and Cona's bard. We ſtood
   far-diſtant ; each beneath his tree. We ſhunned the eyes of the king; we had not conquered in the
   field. A little ſtream rolled at my feet: I touched its light wave, with my ſpear. I touched it
   with my ſpear; nor there was the ſoul of Oſſian. It darkly roſe, from thought to thought, and
   ſent abroad the ſigh.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Morni,” ſaid the king, “Dermid, hunter of roes ! why are ye dark,
   like two rocks, each with its trickling waters? No wrath gathers <!-- on -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210161" facs="../img/1773-524.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 161 --> on Fingal's ſoul, againſt the chiefs of men. Ye are my
   ſtrength in battle; the kindling of my joy in peace. My early voice has been a pleaſant gale to
   your ears, when Fillan prepared the bow. The ſon of Fingal is not here, nor yet the chace of the
   bounding roes. Put why ſhould the breakers of ſhields ſtand, darkened, far away ?”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Tall</hi> they ſtrode towards the king ; they ſaw him turned to Mora's wind. His
   tears came down, for his blue-eyed ſon, who ſlept in the cave of ſtreams. But he brightened
   before them, and ſpoke to the broad-ſhielded kings.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Crommal</hi>, with woody rocks, and miſty top, the field of winds, pours forth,
   to the fight, blue Lubar's ſtreamy roar. Behind it rolls clear-winding Lavath, in the ſtill vale
   of deer. A cave is dark in a rock ; above it ſtrong-winged eagles dwell; broad-headed oaks,
   before it, ſound in Cluna's wind. Within, in his locks of youth, is Ferad-artho<note>
   <p> Ferad-artho was the ſon of Cairbar Mac-Cormac king of Ireland. He was the only one remaining
   of the race of Conar, the ſon of Trenmor, the firſt Iriſh monarch, according to Oſſian. In order
   to make this paſſage thoroughly underſtood, it may not be improper to recapitulate ſome part of
   what has been ſaid in preceding notes. Upon the death of Conar the ſon of Trenmor, his ſon Cormac
   ſucceeded on the Irifh throne. Cormac reigned long. His children were, Cairbar, who ſucceeded
   him, and Ros-crana, the firſt wife of Fingal. Cairbar, long before the death of his father
   Cormac, had taken to wife Bos-gala, the daughter of Colgar, one of the moſt powerful chiefs in
   Connaught, and had, by her, Artho, afterwards king of ſreland. Soon after Artho arrived at man's
   eſtate, his mother Bos-gala died, and Cairbar married Beltanno, the daughter of Conachar of
   Ullin, who brought him a ſon, whom he called Ferad artho, i. e. <hi>a man in the place of
   Artho</hi>. The occaſion of the name was this. Artho, when his brother was born, was abſent, on
   an expedition, in the ſouth of Ireland. A falſe report was brought to his father, that he was
   killed. <hi>Cairbar</hi>, to uſe the words of a poem on the ſubject, <hi>darkened for his
   fair-haired ſon. He turned to the young beam of light, the ſon of Baltanno of Conachar. Thou
   ſhalt be Farad-artho, he ſaid, a fire before thy race</hi>. Cairbar, ſoon after, died, nor did
   Artho long ſurvive him. Artho was ſucceeded, in the Iriſh throne, by his ſon Cormac, who, in his
   minority, was murdered by Cairbar, the ſon of Borbar-duthul. Ferad-artho, ſays tradition, was
   very young, when the expedition of Fingal, to ſettle him on the throne of Ireland, happened.
   During the ſhort reign of young Cormac, Feradartho lived at the royal reſidence of Temora. Upon
   the murder of the king, Condan, the bard, conveyed Ferad-artho, privately, to the cave of Cluna,
   behind the mountain Crommal, in Ulſter, where they both lived concealed, during the ufurpation of
   the family of Atha. A late bard has delivered the whole hiſtory, in a poem juſt now in my
   poſſeſſion. It has little merit, if we except the ſcene between Ferad-artho, and the meſſengers
   of Fingal, upon their arrival, in the valley of Cluna. After hearing of the great actions of
   Fingal, the young prince propoſes the following queſtions concerning him, to Gaul and Dermid, “Is
   the king tall as the rock of my cave? Is his ſpear a fir of Cluna ? Is he a rough-winged blaſt,
   on the mountain, which takes the green oak by the head, and tears it from its hill? Glitters
   Lubar within his ſtride, when he ſends his flately ſteps along. Nor is he tall, ſaid Gaul, as
   that rock: nor glitter ſtreams within his ſtrides, but his ſoul is a mighty flood, like the
   ſtrength of Ullin's ſeas.” </p></note>, blue-eyed king, the ſon <!-- of -->
   <!-- Vol. II. M   ceeded -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210162" facs="../img/1773-527.pbm"/>
   <!-- 162 T E M O R A: Book VIII --> of broad-ſhielded Cairbar, from Ullin of the roes. He liſtens
   to the voice of Condan, as, grey, he bends in feeble light. He liſtens, for his foes dwell in the
   ecchoing halls ef Temora. <!-- He -->
   <!-- ſpear -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210163" facs="../img/1773-530.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 163 --> He comes, at times, abroad, in the ſkirts of miſt, to
   pierce the bounding roes. When the ſun looks on the field, nor by the rock; nor ſtream, is he! He
   ſhuns the race of Bolga, who dwell in his father's hall. Tell him, that Fingal lifts the ſpear,
   and that his foes, perhaps, may fail.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Lift</hi> up, O Gaul, the ſhield before him. Stretch, Dermid, Temora's ſpear. Be
   thy voice in his ear, O Carril, with the deeds of his fathers. Lead him to green Moi-lena, to the
   duſky field of ghoſts; for there, I fall forward, in battle, in the folds of war. Before dun
   night deſcends, come to high Dunmora's top. Look, from the grey ſkirts of miſt, on Lena of the
   ſtreams. If there my ſtandard ſhall float on wind, over Lubar's gleaming ſtream, then has not
   Fingal failed in the laſt of his fields.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> were his words; nor aught replied the ſilent, ſtriding kings. They
   looked ſide-long, on Erin's hoſt, and darkened, as they went. Never before had they left the
   king, in the midſt of the ſtormy field. Behind them, touching at <!-- M 2 times -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210164" facs="../img/1773-533.pbm"/>
   <!-- 164 TE MO R A: Book VIII. --> times his harp, the grey-haired Carril moved. He foreſaw the
   fall of the people, and mournful was the ſound! It was like a breeze that comes, by fits, over
   Lego's reedy lake ; when ſleep half-deſcends on the hunter, within his moſſy cave. “<hi rend="sc"
   >Why</hi> bends the bard of Cona,” ſaid Fingal, “over his ſecret ſtream ? Is this a time for
   ſorrow, father of low-laid Oſcar? Be the warriors<note>
   <p> Malvina is ſuppoſed to ſpeak the following ſoliloquy.</p> <quote>
   <p>“Malvina is like the bow of the ſhower, in the ſecret valley of ſtreams; it is bright, but the
   drops of heaven are rolling on its blended light. They ſay, that I am fair within my locks, but,
   on my brightneſs, is the wandering of tears. Darkneſs flies over my ſoul, as the duſky wave of
   the breeze, along the graſs of Lutha. Yet have not the roes failed me, when I moved between the
   hills. Pleaſant, beneath my white hand, aroſe the ſound of harps. What then, daughter of Lutha,
   travels over thy ſoul, like the dreary path a ghoſt, along the nightly beam ? Should the young
   warrior fall, in the roar of his troubled fields! Young virgins of Lutha ariſe, call back the
   wandering thoughts of Malvina. Awake the voice of the harp, along my ecchoing vale. Then ſhall my
   ſoul come forth, like a light from the gates of the morn, when clouds are rolled around them,
   with their broken ſides.</p>
   <p>“Dweller of my thoughts, by night, whoſe form aſcends in troubled fields, why doſt thou ſtir
   up my ſoul, thou fardiſtant ſon of the king ? is that the ſhip of my love, its dark courſe
   through the ridges of ocean? How art thou ſo ſudden, Oſcar, from the heath of ſhields ?”</p> </quote>
   <p>The reſt of this poem conſiſts of a dialogue between Ullin and Malvina, wherein the diſtreſs
   of the latter is carried to the higheſt pitch. </p></note> remembered in peace; when ecchoing
   ſhields are heard no more. Bend, then, in grief, over the <!-- flood, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210165" facs="../img/1773-536.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 164 --> flood, where blows the mountain breeze. Let them paſs on
   thy ſoul, the blue-eyed dwellers of the tomb. But Erin rolls to war ; wide-tumbling, rough, and
   dark. Lift, Oſſian, lift the ſhield. I am alone, my ſon!”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> comes the ſudden voice of winds to the becalmed ſhip of Inis-huna, and
   drives it large, along the deep, dark rider of the wave; ſo the voice of Fingal ſent Oſſian,
   tall, along the heath. He lifted high his ſhining ſhield, in the duſky wing of war : like the
   broad, blank moon, in the ſkirt of a cloud, before the ſtorms ariſe.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Loud</hi>, from moſs-covered Mora, poured down, at once, the broad-winged war.
   Fingal led his people forth, king of Morven of ſtreams. On high ſpreads the eagle's wing. His
   grey hair is poured on his ſhoulders broad. In thunder are his mighty ſtrides. He often ſtood,
   and ſaw behind, the wide-gleaming rolling of armour. A rock he ſeemed, grey over with ice, whoſe
   woods are high in wind. Bright ſtreams leap from its head, and ſpread their foam on blaſts.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Now</hi> he came to Lubar's cave, where Fillan darkly ſlept. Bran ſtill lay on
   the broken ſhield : the eagle-wing is ſtrewed by the winds. Bright, from withered furze, looked
   forth the hero's ſpear. Then grief ſtirred the ſoul of the king, like whirlwinds blackening on a
   lake. He <!-- M 3 turned -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210166" facs="../img/1773-539.pbm"/>
   <!-- 166 T E M O R A: Book VIII. --> turned his ſudden ſtep, and leaned on his bending ſpear.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">White-breasted</hi> Bran came bounding with joy to the known path of Fingal. He
   came, and looked towards the cave, where the blue-eyed hunter lay, for he was wont to ſtride,
   with morning, to the dewy bed of the roe. It was then the tears of the king came dawn, and all
   his ſoul was dark. But as the riſing wind rolls away the ſtorm of rain, and leaves the white
   ſtreams to the ſun, and high hills with their heads of graſs : ſo the returning war brightened
   the mind of Fingal. He bounded<note>
   <p> The Iriſh compoſitions concerning Fingal invariably ſpeaks of him as a giant. Of theſe
   Hibernian poems there are now many in my hands. From the language, and alluſions to the times in
   which they were writ, I ſhould fix the date of their compoſition in the fifteenth and ſixteenth
   centuries. In ſome paſſages, the poetry is far from wanting merit, but the fable is unnatural,
   and the whole conduct of the pieces injudicious. I ſhall give one inſtance of the extravagant
   fictions of the Iriſh bards, in a poem which they, moſt unjuſtly, aſcribe to Oſſian. The ſtory of
   it is this: Ireland being threatened with an invaſion from ſome part of Scandinavia, Fingal ſent
   Oſſian, Oſcar, and Ca-olt, to watch the bay, in which, it was expected, the enemy was to land.
   Oſcar, unluckily, fell aſleep, before the Scandinavians appeared ; and, great as he was, ſays the
   Iriſh bard, he had one bad property, that no leſs could waken him, before his time, than cutting
   off one of his fingers, or throwing a great ſtone againſt his head ; and it was dangerous to come
   near him on thoſe occaſions, till he had recovered himſelf, and was fully awake.</p>
   <p>Ca-olt, who was employed by Oſſian to waken his ſon, made choice of throwing the ſtone againſt
   his head, as the leaſt dangerous expedient. The ſtone, rebounding from the hero's head, ſhook, as
   it rolled along, the hill for three miles round. Oſcar roſe in rage, fought bravely, and, ſingly,
   vanquiſhed a wing of the enemy's army. Thus the bard goes on, till Fingal put an end to the war,
   by the total rout of the Scandinavians. Puerile, and even deſpicable, as theſe fictions are, yet
   Keating and O'Flaherty have no better authority than the poems which contain them, for all that
   they write concerning Fion Mac-comnal, and the pretended militia of Ireland. </p></note>, on his
   <!-- ſpear, -->
   <!-- 4 Ca-olt, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210167" facs="../img/1773-542.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII, An EPIC POEM, 167 --> ſpear, over Lubar, and ſtruck his ecchoing ſhield. His
   ridgy hoſt bend forward, at once, with all their pointed ſteel.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> Erin heard, with fear, the ſound : wide they came rolling along. Dark
   Malthos, in the wing of war, looks forward from ſhaggy brows. Next roſe that beam of light
   Hidalla ; then the ſide-long-looking gloom of Maronnan. Blue-ſhielded Clonar lifts the ſpear ;
   Cormar ſhakes his buſhy locks on the wind. Slowly, from behind a rock, roſe the bright form of
   Atha. Firſt appeared his two pointed ſpears, then the half of his burniſhed ſhield ; like the
   rifing of a nightly meteor, over the vale of ghoſts. But when he ſhone all abroad : the hoſts
   plunged, at once, into ſtrife. The gleaming waves of ſteel are poured on either ſide.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> meet two troubled ſeas, with the rolling of all their waves, when they
   feel the wings of <!-- M 4 tending -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210168" facs="../img/1773-545.pbm"/>
   <!-- 168 TE MOR A: Book VIII. --> contending winds, in the rock-ſided firth of Lumon; along the
   ecchoing hills is the dim courſe of ghoſts : from the blaſt fall the torn groves on the deep,
   amidſt the foamy path of whales. So mixed the hoſts! Now Fingal; now Cathmor came abroad. The
   dark tumbling of death is before them : the gleam of broken ſteel is rolled on their ſteps, as,
   loud, the high-bounding kings hewed down the ridge of ſhields.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Maronnan</hi> fell, by Fingal, laid large acroſs a ſtream. The waters gathered by
   his ſide, and leapt grey over his boſſy ſhield. Clonar is pierced by Cathmor: nor yet lay the
   chief on earth. An oak ſeized his hair in his fall. His helmet rolled on the ground. By its
   thong, hung his broad ſhield; over it wandered his ſtreaming blood. Tla-min<note>
   <p> Tla-min, <hi>mildly-ſoft</hi>. The loves of Clonar and Tlamin were rendered famous in the
   north, by a fragment of a lyric poem. It is a dialogue between Clonar and Tlamin. She begins with
   a ſoliloquy, which he overhears. </p><sp>
   <speaker> TLAMIN.</speaker>
   <p> “Clonar, ſon of Conglas of I-mor, young hunter of dun-ſided roes! where art thou laid, amidſt
    ruſhes, beneath the paſſing wing of the breeze? I behold thee, my love, in the plain of thy own
    dark ſtreams! The clung thorn is rolled by the wind, and ruſtles along his ſhield. Bright in his
    locks he lies : the thoughts of his dreams fly, darkening, over his face. Thou thinkeſt of the
    battles of Ofſian, young ſon of the ecchoing iſle !</p>
   <p> “Half hid, in the grove, I ſit down. Fly back, ye miſts of the hill. Why ſhould ye hide her
    love from the blue eyes of Tlamin of harps? </p>
   </sp><sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Clonar</hi>.</speaker>
   <p> “As the ſpirit, ſeen in a dream, flies off from our opening eyes, we think, we behold his
    bright path between the cloſing hills ; ſo fled the daughter of Clun-gal, from the ſight of
    Clonar of ſhields. Ariſe, from the gathering of trees; blue-eyed Tlamin ariſe. </p>
   </sp><sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Tlamin</hi>.</speaker>
   <p> “I turn me away from his ſteps. Why ſhould he know of my love! My white breaſt is heaving
    over ſighs, as foam on the dark courſe of ſtreams. But he paſſes away, in his arms ! Son of
    Conglas, my ſoul is ſad. </p>
   </sp><sp>
   <speaker><hi rend="sc">Clonar</hi>,</speaker>
   <p> “It was the ſhield of Fingal! the voice of kings from Selma of harps! My path is towards
    green Erin. Ariſe, fair light, from thy ſhades. Come to the field of my ſoul, there is the
    ſpreading of hoſts. Ariſe, on Clonar's troubled ſoul, young daughter of blue ſhielded Clungal.”
   </p>
   </sp>
   <p>Clungal was the chief of I-mor, one of the Hebrides. </p></note> ſhall weep, in the hall, and
   ſtrike her heaving breaſt. <!-- Nor -->
   <!-- Thou -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210169" facs="../img/1773-548.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII, An EPIC POEM. 169 --> <hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> did Ofſian forget the ſpear, in the
   wing of his war. He ſtrewed the field with dead. Young Hidalla came. “Soft voice of ſtreamy
   Clonra ! Why doſt thou lift the ſteel? O that we met, in the ſtrife of ſong, in thy own ruſhy
   vale !” Malthos beheld him low, and darkened as he ruſhed along. On either ſide of a ſtream, we
   bend in the ecchoing ſtrife. Heaven comes rolling down : around burſt the voices of ſqually
   winds. Hills are clothed, at times, in fire. <!-- 6 Thunder -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210170" facs="../img/1773-551.pbm"/>
   <!-- 170 T E M O R A: Book VIII. --> Thunder rolls in wreaths of miſt. In darkneſs ſhrunk the foe
   : Morven's warriors ſtood aghaſt. Still I bent over the ſtream, amidſt my whiſtling locks.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Then</hi> roſe the voice of Fingal, and the ſound of the flying foe. I ſaw the
   king, at times, in lightning, darkly-ſtriding in his might. I ſtruck my ecchoing ſhield, and hung
   forward on the ſteps of Alnecma : the foe is rolled before me, like a wreath of ſmoak.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſun looked forth from his cloud. The hundred ſtreams of Moi-lena ſhone.
   Slow roſe the blue columns of miſt, againſt the glittering hill. “Where are the mighty kings
   ?<note>
   <p> Fingal and Cathmor. The conduct here is perhaps proper. The numerous deſcriptions of ſingle
   combats have already exhauſted the ſubject. Nothing new, nor adequate to our high idea of the
   kings, can be ſaid. <hi>A column of miſt</hi> is thrown over the whole, and the combat is left to
   the imagination of the reader. Poets have almoſt univerſally failed in their deſcriptions of this
   ſort. Not all the ſtrength of Homer could ſuſtain, with dignity, the <hi>minutiæ</hi> of a fingle
   combat. The throwing of a ſpear, and the braying of a ſhield, as ſome of our own poets moſt
   elegantly expreſs it, convey no magnificent, though they are ſtriking ideas. Our imagination
   ſtretches beyond, and conſequently, deſpiſes, the deſcription. It were, therefore, well, for ſome
   poets, in my opinion, (tho' it is, perhaps, ſomewhat ſingular) to have, ſometimes, thrown
   <hi>miſt</hi> over their ſingle combats. </p> </note> Nor by that ſtream, nor wood, are they ! I
   hear the clang of arms! Their ſtrife is in the boſom of <!-- that -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210171" facs="../img/1773-554.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VII, An EPIC POEM. 171 --> that miſt. Such is the contending of ſpirits in a nightly
   cloud, when they ſtrive for the wintry wings of winds, and the rolling of the foam-covered
   waves.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">I rushed</hi> along. The grey miſt roſe. Tall, gleaming, they ſtood at Lubar.
   Cathmor leaned againſt a rock. His half-fallen ſhield received the ſtream, that leapt from the
   moſs above. Towards him is the ſtride of Fingal : he ſaw the hero's blood. His ſword fell ſlowly
   to his ſide. He ſpoke, midſt his darkening joy.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Yields</hi> the race of Borbar-duthul ? Or ſtill does he lift the ſpear? Not
   unheard is thy name, at Atha, in the green dwelling of ſtrangers. It has come, like the breeze of
   his deſart, to the ear of Fingal. Come to my hill of feaſts: the mighty fail, at times. No fire
   am I to low-laid foes ; I rejoice not over the fall of the brave. To cloſe<note>
   <p> Fingal is very much celebrated, in tradition, for his knowlege in the virtues of herbs. The
   Iriſh poems, concerning him, often repreſent him, curing the wounds which his chiefs received in
   battle. They fable concerning him, that he was in poſſeſſion of a cup, containing the eſſence of
   herbs, which inſtantaneouſly healed wounds. The knowlege of curing the wounded, was, till of
   late, univerſal among the Highlanders. We hear of no other diſorder, which required the ſkill of
   phyſic. The wholſomeneſs of the climate, and an active life, ſpent in hunting, excluded diſeaſes.
   </p> </note> the wound is mine: I have known <!-- the -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210172" facs="../img/1773-557.pbm"/>
   <!-- 172 T E M O R A: Book VIII. --> the herbs of the hills. I ſeized their fair heads, on high,
   as they waved by their ſecret ſtreams. Thou art dark and ſilent, king of Atha of ſtrangers.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">By</hi> Atha of the ſtream,” he ſaid, “there riſes a moſſy rock. On its head is
   the wandering of boughs, within the courſe of winds. Dark, in its face, is a cave, with its own
   loud rill. There have I heard the tread of ſtrangers<note>
   <p> Cathmor reflects, with pleaſure, even in his laſt moments, on the relief he had afforded to
   ftrangers. The very tread of their feet was pleafant in his ear. His hoſpitality was not paſſed
   unnoticed by the bards; for, with them, it became a proverb, when they deſcribed the hoſpitable
   diſpoſition of a hero, <hi>that he was like Cathmor of Atha, the friend of ſtrangers</hi>. It
   will ſeem ſtrange, that, in all the Iriſh poems, there is no mention made of Cathmor. This muſt
   be attributed to the revolutions and domeſtic confuſions which happened in that iſland, and
   utterly cut off all the real traditions concerning ſo ancient a period. All that we have related
   of the ſtate of lreland before the fifth century is of late invention, aud the work of ill
   informed ſenachies and injudicious bards. </p> </note>, when they paſſed to my hall of ſhells.
   Joy roſe, like a flame, on my ſoul: I bleſt the ecchoing rock. Here be my dwelling, in darkneſs;
   in my graſſy vale. From this I ſhall mount the breeze, that purſues my thiſtle's beard; or look
   down, on blue-winding Atha, from its wandering miſt.” <!-- War --> </p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73210173" facs="../img/1773-560.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 173 --> “<hi rend="sc">Why</hi> ſpeaks the king of the tomb ?
   Oſſian! the warrior has failed ! Joy meet thy ſoul, like a ſtream, Cathmor, friend of ſtrangers!
   My ſon, I hear the call of years; they take my ſpear as they paſs along. Why does not Fingal,
   they ſeem to ſay, reſt within his hall? Doſt thou always delight in blood? In the tears of the
   ſad? No: ye dark-rolling years, Fingal delights not in blood. Tears are wintry ſtreams that waſte
   away my ſoul. But, when I lie down to reſt, then comes the mighty voice of war. It awakes me, in
   my hall, and calls forth all my ſteel. It ſhall call it forth no more; Oſſian, take thou thy
   father's ſpear. Lift it, in battle, when the proud ariſe.</p>
  <p>My fathers, Oſſian, trace my ſteps; my deeds are pleaſant to their eyes. Wherever I come forth
   to battle, on my field, are their columns of miſt. But mine arm reſcued the feeble; the haughty
   found my rage was fire. Never over the fallen did mine eye rejoice. For this<note>
   <p> The Celtic nations had ſome idea of rewards, and perhaps of puniſhments, after death. Thoſe
   who behaved, in life, with bravery and virtue, were received, with joy, to the airy halls of
   their fathers; but <hi>the dark in ſoul</hi>, to uſe the expreſſion of the poet, were ſpurned
   away <hi>from the habitation of heroes, to wander on all the winds</hi>. Another opinion, which
   prevailed in thoſe times, tended not a little to make individuals emulous to excel one another in
   martial atchievements. It was thought, that, in the <hi>hall of clouds</hi>, every one had a
   ſeat, raiſed above others, in proportion as he excelled them, in valour, when he lived. </p>
   </note>, my fathers ſhall meet me, at the gates <!-- of -->
   <!-- prevailed -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210174" facs="../img/1773-563.pbm"/>
   <!-- 174 T E M O R A: Book VIII. --> of their airy halls, tall, with robes of light, with
   mildly-kindled eyes. But, to the proud in arms, they are darkened moons in heaven, which ſend the
   fire of night, red-wandering over their face.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Father</hi> of heroes, Trenmor, dweller of eddying winds! I give thy ſpear to
   Oſſian, let thine eye rejoice. Thee have I ſeen, at times, bright from between thy clouds; ſo
   appear to my ſon, when he is to lift the ſpear: then ſhall he remember thy mighty deeds, though
   thou art now but a blaſt.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> gave the ſpear to my hand, and raiſed; at once, a ſtone on high, to ſpeak
   to future times, with its grey head of moſs. Beneath he placed a ſword<note>
   <p> There are ſome ſtones ſtill to be ſeen in the north, whick were erected as memorials of ſome
   remarkable tranſactions between the ancient chiefs. There are generally found, beneath them, ſome
   piece of arms, and a bit of half-burnt wood. The cauſe of placing the laſt there is not mentioned
   in tradition. </p> </note> in earth, and one bright boſs from his ſhield. Dark in thought,
   a-while, he bends : his words, at length, came forth. <!-- WHEN --> </p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73210175" facs="../img/1773-566.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 175 --> “<hi rend="sc">When</hi> thou, O ſtone, ſhall moulder down,
   and loſe thee, in the moſs of years, then ſhall the traveller come, and whiſtling paſs away. Thou
   know'ft not, feeble man, that fame once ſhone on Moi-lena. Here Fingal reſigned his ſpear, after
   the laſt of his fields. Paſs away, thou empty ſhade; in thy voice there is no renown. Thou
   dwelleſt by ſome peaceful ſtream ; yet a few years, and thou art gone. No one remembers thee,
   thou dweller of thick miſt ! But Fingal ſhall be clothed with fame, a beam of light to other
   times; for he went forth, in ecchoing ſteel, to ſave the weak in arms.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Brightening</hi> in his fame, the king ſtrode to Lubar's ſounding oak, where it
   bent, from its rock, over the bright-tumbling ſtream. Beneath it is a narrow plain, and the ſound
   of the fount of the rock. Here the ſtandard<note>
   <p> The erecting of his ſtandard on the bank of Lubar, was the ſignal which Fingal, in the
   beginning of the book, promiſed to give to the chiefs, who went to conduct Ferad-artho to the
   army, ſhould he himſelf prevail in battle. This ſtandard here is called, the <hi>ſun-beam</hi>.
   The reaſon of this appellation, I gave in my notes on the poem intitled Fingal. </p></note> of
   Morven poured its wreaths on the wind, to mark the way of Ferad-artho, from his ſecret vale.
   Bright, from his parted weſt, the ſun of heaven looked abroad. The hero ſaw his people, and heard
   <!-- their -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210176" facs="../img/1773-569.pbm"/>
   <!-- 176 T E M O R A: Book VIII. --> their ſhouts of joy. In broken ridges round, they glittered
   to the beam. The king rejoiced, as a hunter in his own green vale, when, after the ſtorm is
   rolled away, he ſees the gleaming ſides of the rocks. The green thorn ſhakes its head in their
   face; from their top look forward the roes.<note>
   <p> The ſcene is changed to the valley of Lona, whither Sulmalla had been ſent, by Cathmor,
   before the battle. Clonmal, an aged bard, or rather druid, as he ſeems here to be endued with a
   preſcience of events, had long dwelt there, in a cave. This ſcene is calculated to throw a
   melancholy gloom over the mind. </p></note> <hi rend="sc">Grey</hi>, at his moſſy cave, is bent
   the aged form of Clonmal. The eyes of the bard had failed. He leaned forward, on his ſtaff.
   Bright, in her locks, before him, Sul-malla liſtened to the tale; the tale of the kings of Atha,
   in the days of old. The noiſe of battle had ceaſed in his ear: he ftopt, and raiſed the ſecret
   ſigh. The ſpirits of the dead, they ſaid, often lightened along his ſoul. He ſaw the king of Atha
   low, beneath his bending tree.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Why</hi> art thou dark,” ſaid the maid? “The ſtrife of arms is paſt. Soon<note>
   <p> Cathmor had promiſed, in the ſeventh book, to come to the cave of Clonmal, after the battle
   was over. </p></note> ſhall he come to thy cave, over thy winding ſtreams. The ſun looks from the
   rocks of the weſt. The <!-- , miſts -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210177" facs="../img/1773-572.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 177 --> miſts of the lake ariſe. Grey, they ſpread on that hill,
   the ruſhy dwelling of roes. From the miſt ſhall my king appear ! Behold, he comes in his arms.
   Come to the cave of Clonmal, O my beſt beloved !” </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">It</hi> was the ſpirit of Cathmor, ſtalking, large, a gleaming form. He ſunk by
   the hollow ſtream, that roared between the hills. “It was but the hunter,” ſhe ſaid,“who ſearches
   for the bed of the roe. His ſteps are not forth to war; his ſpouſe expects him with night. He
   ſhall, whiſtling, return, with the ſpoils of the dark-brown hinds.” Her eyes were turned to the
   hill; again the ſtately form came down. She roſe, in the midſt of joy. He retired again in miſt.
   Gradual vaniſh his limbs of ſmoak, and mix with the mountain-wind. Then ſhe knew that he fell!
   “King of Erin art thou low!” Let Oſſian forget her grief; it waſtes the ſoul of age<note>
   <p> Tradition relates, that Oſſian, the next day after the deciſive battle between Fingal and
   Cathmor, went to find out Sul-malla, in the valley of Lona, His addreſs to her follows :</p>
   <quote>
   <p>“Awake thou daughter of Conmor, from the fern-ſkirted cavern of Lona. Awake, thou ſun-beam in
   deſarts ; warriors one day muſt fail. They move forth, like terrible lights ; but, often, their
   cloud is near. Go to the valley of ſtreams, to the wandering of herds, on Lumon; there dwells, in
   his lazy miſt, the man of many days. But he is unknown, Sulmalla, like the thiſtle of the rocks
   of roes; it ſhakes its grey beard, in the wind, and falls, unſeen of our eyes. Not ſuch are the
   kings of men, their departure is a meteor of fire, which pours its red courſe, from the deſart,
   over the boſom of night.</p>
   <p>“He is mixed with the warriors of old, thoſe fires that have hid their heads. At times ſhall
   they come forth in ſong. Not forgot has the warrior failed. He has not ſeen, Sul-malla, the fall
   of a beam of his own: no fair-haired ſon, in his blood, young troubler of the field. I am lonely,
   young branch of Lumon, I may hear the voice of the feeble, when my ſtrength ſhall have failed in
   years, for young Oſcar has ceaſed, on his field,” — * *</p> </quote>
   <p>Sul-malla returned to her own country, She makes a conſiderable figure in another poem ; her
   behaviour in that piece accounts for that partial regard with which the poet ought to ſpeak of
   her throughout Temora, </p></note>. <!-- EVENING -->
   <!-- Vol. II. N lazy -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210178" facs="../img/1773-575.pbm"/>
   <!-- 178 T E M O R A: Book VIII. --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Evening</hi> came down on Moi-lena, Grey rolled the ſtreams of the land. Loud
   came forth the voice of Fingal : the beam of oaks aroſe. The people gathered round with gladneſs
   ; with gladneſs blended with ſhades. They ſidelong looked to the king, and beheld his unfiniſhed
   joy. Pleaſant, from the way of the deſart, the voice of muſic came. It ſeemed, at firſt, the
   noiſe of a ſtream, far-diſtant on its rocks. Slow it rolled along the hill, like the ruffled wing
   of a breeze, when it takes the tufted beard of the rocks, in the ſtill ſeaſon of night. It was
   the voice of Condan, mixed with Carril's trembling harp. They came, with blue-eyed Ferad-artho,
   to Mora of the ſtreams. <!-- 9 SUDDEN --> </p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73210179" facs="../img/1773-578.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book VIII. An EPIC POEM. 179 --> <hi rend="sc">Sudden</hi> burſts the ſong from our bards,
   on Lena : the hoſt ſtruck their ſhields midſt the ſound. Gladneſs roſe brightening on the king,
   like the beam of a cloudy day, when it riſes, on the green hill, before the roar of winds. He
   ſtruck the boſſy ſhield of kings; at once they ceaſe around. The people lean forward, from their
   ſpears, towards the voice of their land<note>
   <p> Before I finiſh my notes, it may not be altogether improper to obviate an objection, which
   may be made to the credibility of the ſtory of Temora. It may be aſked, whether it is probable,
   that Fingal could perform ſuch actions as are aſcribed to him in this book, at an age when his
   grandſon, Oſcar, had acquired ſo much reputation in arms. To this it may be anſwered, that Fingal
   was but very young [book 4th] when he took to wife Ros-crana, who ſoon after became the mother of
   Oſſian. Oſſian was alſo extremely young when he married Ever-allin, the mother of Oſcar.
   Tradition relates, that Fingal was but eighteen years old at the birth of his ſon Oſſian ; and
   that Oſſian was much about the ſame age, when Oſcar, his ſon, was born. Oſcar, perhaps, might be
   about twenty, when he was killed, in the battle of Gabhra, [book 1ſt] ſo the age of Fingal, when
   the deciſive battle was fought between him and Cathmor, was juſt fifty-ſix years. In thoſe times
   of activity and health, the natural ſtrength and vigour of a man was little abated, at ſuch an
   age ; ſo that there is nothing improbable in the actions of Fingal, as related in this book. </p>
   </note>.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Sons</hi> of Morven, ſpread the feaſt ; ſend the night away in ſong. Ye have
   ſhone around me; and the dark ſtorm is paſt. My people are the windy rocks, from which I ſpread
   my eagle <!-- N 2 wings, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210180" facs="../img/1773-581.pbm"/>
   <!-- 130 T E M O R A. Book VII. --> wings, when I ruſh forth to renown, and ſeize it on its
   field. Oſſian, thou haſt the ſpear of Fingal : it is not the ſtaff of a boy with which he ſtrews
   the thiſtle round, young wanderer of the field. No: it is the lance of the mighty, with which
   they ſtretched forth their hands to death. Look to thy fathers, my ſon; they are awful beams.
   With morning lead Ferad-artho forth to the ecchoing halls of Temora. Remind him of the kings of
   Erin; the ſtately forms of old. Let not the fallen be forgot, they were mighty in the field. Let
   Carril pour his ſong, that the kings may rejoice in their miſt. To-morrow I ſpread my ſails to
   Selma's ſhaded walls; where ſtreamy Duthula winds through the ſeats of roes.” </p>
 </div>
</div>
