<div type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73210030" facs="../img/1773-131.pbm"/>
 <head source="NYPL">TEMORA: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK II.</head>
 <div type="argument">
  <head>ARGUMENT to Book II.</head>
  <p> This book opens, we may ſuppoſe, about midnight, with a ſoliloquy of Oſſian, who had retired,
   from the reſt of the army, to mourn for his ſon Oſcar. Upon hearing the noiſe of Cathmor's army
   approaching, he went to find out his brother Fillan, who kept the watch, on the hill of Mora, in
   the front of Fingal's army. In the converſation of the brothers, the epiſode of Conar, the ſon of
   Trenmor, who was the firſt king of Ireland, is introduced, which lays open the origin of the
   conteſts between the Cael and Firbolg, the two nations who firſt poſſeſſed themſelves of that
   iſland. Oſſian kindles a fire on Mora ; upon which Cathmor deſiſted from the deſign he had formed
   of ſurpriſing the army of the Caledonians. He calls a council of his chiefs; reprimands Foldath
   for adviſing a night-attack, as the Iriſh army were ſo much ſuperior in number to the enemy. The
   bard Fonar introduces the ſtory of Crothar, the anceſtor of the king, which throws further light
   on the hiſtory of Ireland, and the original pretenſions of the family of Atha, to the throne of
   that kingdom. The Iriſh chiefs lie down to reſt, and Cathmor himſelf undertakes the watch. In his
   circuit, round the army, he is met by Oſſian. The interview of the two heroes is deſcribed.
   Cathmor obtains a promiſe from Oſſian, to order a funeral elegy to be ſung over the grave of
   Cairbar; it being the opinion of the times, that the ſouls of the dead could not be happy, till
   their elegies were ſung by a bard. Morning comes. Cathmor and Oſſian part; and the latter,
   caſually meeting with Carril the ſon of Kinſena, ſends that bard, with a funeral ſong, to the
   tomb of Cairbar. </p>
 </div>
 
 
 <pb xml:id="P73210031" facs="../img/1773-134.pbm"/>
 <!-- [31] -->
 <div type="translation">
  <head>T E M O R A: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK II.</head>
  <p><note>
   <p> Though this book has little action, it is not the leaſt important part of Temora. The poet,
    in ſeveral epiſodes, runs up the cauſe of the war to the very ſource. The firſt population of
    Ireland, the wars between the two nations who originally poſſeſſed that iſland, its firſt race
    of kings, and the revolutions of its government, are important facts, and are delivered by the
    poet, with ſo little mixture of the fabulous, that one cannot help preferring his accounts to
    the improbable fictions of the Scotch and Iriſh hiſtorians. The Mileſian fables bear about them
    the marks of a late invention. To trace their legends to their ſource would be no difficult taſk
    ; but a diſquiſition of this ſort would extend this note too far. </p>
   </note><hi rend="sc">Father</hi> of heroes! O Trenmor ! High dweller of eddying winds! where the
   dark-red thunder marks the troubled clouds ! Open thou thy ſtormy halls. Let the bards of old be
   near. Let them draw near, with ſongs and their half-viewleſs harps. No dweller of miſty valley
   comes ! No hunter unknown at his ſtreams ! It is the carborne Oſcar, from the fields of
   war.<!--Sudden-->
   <pb xml:id="P73210032" facs="../img/1773-137.pbm"/>
   <!-- 32 T E M O R A: Book II. --> Sudden is thy change, my ſon, from what thou wert on dark
   Moilena! The blaſt folds thee in its ſkirt, and ruffles through the ſky ! Doſt thou not behold
   thy father, at the ſtream of night? The chiefs of Morven ſleep far-diſtant. They have loſt no ſon
   : But ye have loſt a hero, chiefs of reſounding Morven! Who could equal his ſtrength, when battle
   rolled againſt his ſide, like the darkneſs of crowded waters? Why this cloud on Oſſian's ſoul ?
   It ought to burn in danger. Erin is near with her hoſt. The king of Selma is alone. Alone thou
   ſhalt not be, my father, while I can lift the ſpear !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">I rose</hi>, in all my arms. I roſe and liſtened to the wind. The ſhield of Fillan<note>
   <p> We underſtand, from the preceding book, that Cathmor was near with an army. When Cairbar was
    killed, the tribes who attended him fell back to Cathmor; who, as it afterwards appears, had
    taken a reſolution to ſurprize Fingal by night. Fillan was diſpatched to the hill of Mora, which
    was in the front of the Caledonians, to obſerve the motions of Cathmor. In this ſituation were
    affairs when Oſſian, upon hearing the noiſe of the approaching enemy, went to find out his
    brother. Their converſation naturally introduces the epiſode, concerning Conar the ſon of
    Trenmor, the firſt Iriſh monarch, which is ſo neceſſary to the underſtanding the foundation of
    the rebellion and uſurpation of Cairbar and Cathmor. Fillan was the youngeſt of the ſons of
    Fingal, then living. He and Boſmina, mentioned in the <hi>battle of Lora</hi>, were the only
    children of the king, by Clatho the daughter of Cathulla king of Inis-tore, whom he had taken to
    wife, after the death of Ros-crana, the daughter of Cormac Mac-Conar king of Ireland. </p>
   </note> is 
   <!-- not -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210033" facs="../img/1773-140.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 33 --> not heard. I tremble for the ſon of Fingal. “Why ſhould the
   foe come by night? Why ſhould the dark-haired warrior fail ?” Diſtant, ſullen murmurs riſe : like
   the noiſe of the lake of Lego, when its waters ſhrink, in the days of froſt, and all its burſting
   ice reſounds. The people of Lara look to heaven, and foreſee the ſtorm! My ſteps are forward on
   the heath. The ſpear of Oſcar in my hand! Red ſtars looked from high. I gleamed, along the
   night.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">I saw</hi> Fillan ſilent before me, bending forward from Mora's rock. He heard
   the ſhout of the foe. The joy of his ſoul aroſe. He heard my ſounding tread, and turned his
   lifted ſpear. “Comeſt thou, ſon of night, in peace ? Or doſt thou meet my wrath? The foes of
   Fingal are mine. Speak, or fear my ſteel. I ſtand not, in vain, the ſhield of Morven's race.”
   “Never mayſt thou ſtand in vain, ſon of blue eyed Clatho! Fingal begins to be alone. Darkneſs
   gathers on the laſt of his days. Yet he has two<note>
   <p> That is, two ſons in Ireland. Fergus, the ſecond ſon of Fingal, was, at that time, on an
    expedition, which is mentioned in one of the leſſer poems. He, according to ſome traditions, was
    the anceſtor of Fergus, the ſon of Erc or Arcath, commonly called <hi>Fergus the ſecond</hi> in
    the Scotch hiſtories. The beginning of the reign of Fergus over the Scots, is placed, by the
    moſt approved annals of Scotland, in the fourth year of the fifth age : a full century after the
    death of Oſſian. The genealogy of his family is recorded thus by the Highland Senachies;
    <hi>Fergus Mac Arcath Mac Chongael, Mac-Fergus, Mac-Fien-gäal na buai'</hi>; i. e. Fergus the
    ſon of Arcath, the ſon of Congal, the ſon of Fergus, the ſon of Fingal <hi>the victorious</hi>.
    This ſubject is treated more at large, in the diſſertation annexed to the poem. </p>
   </note> ſons who ought to ſhine in war. Who 
   <!-- ought -->
   <!-- Vol. II. D fifth -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210034" facs="../img/1773-143.pbm"/>
   <!-- 34 T E M O R A: Book II. --> ought to be two beams of light, near the ſteps of his
   departure.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Fingal,” replied the youth, “it is not long ſince I raiſed the
   ſpear. Few are the marks of my ſword in war. But Fillan's ſoul is fire! The chiefs of Bolga<note>
   <p> The ſouthern parts of Ireland went, for ſome time, under the name of Bolga, from the Fir-bolg
    or Belgæ of Britain, who ſettled a colony there. <hi>Bolg</hi> ſignifies <hi>a quiver</hi>, from
    which proceeds <hi>Fir-bolga</hi> i. e. <hi>bow-men</hi> ; ſo called from their uſing bows, more
    than any of the neighbouring nations. </p>
   </note> crowd around the ſhield of generous Cathmor. Their gathering is on that heath. Shall my
   ſteps approach their hoſt? I yielded to Oſcar alone, in the ſtrife of the race, on Cona !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Fillan</hi>, thou ſhalt not approach their hoſt; nor fall before thy fame is
   known. My name is heard in ſong : when needful I advance. From the ſkirts of night I ſhall view
   them over all their gleaming tribes. Why, Fillan, didſt thou ſpeak of Oſcar! Why awake my ſigh? I
   muſt forget<note>
   <p> After this paſſage, Oſcar is not mentioned in all Temora. The ſituations of the characters
    who act in the poem are ſo intereſting, that others, foreign to the ſubject, could not be
    introduced with any luſtre. Though the epiſode, which follows, may ſeem to flow naturally enough
    from the converſation of the brothers, yet I have ſhewn, in a preceding note, and, more at
    large, in the diſſertation annexed to this collection, that the poet had a farther deſign in
    view. </p>
   </note> the warrior, till the ſtorm is rolled 
   <!-- away. -->
   <!-- tereşting, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210035" facs="../img/1773-146.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II, An EPIC POEM. 35 --> away. Sadneſs ought not to dwell in danger, nor the tear in
   the eye of war. Our fathers forgot their fallen ſons, till the noiſe of arms was paſt. Then
   ſorrow returned to the tomb, and the ſong of bards aroſe.” The memory of thoſe, who fell, quickly
   followed the departure of war: When the tumult of battle is paſt, the ſoul, in ſilence, melts
   away, for the dead.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Conar</hi><note>
   <p> Conar, the firſt king of Ireland, was the ſon of Trenmor, the great-grand-father of Fingal.
    It was on account of this family-connection, that Fingal was engaged in ſo many wars in the
    cauſe of the race of Conar. Tho' few of the actions of Trenmor are mentioned, he was the moſt
    renowned name of antiquity. The moſt probable opinion concerning him is, that he was the firſt,
    who united the tribes of the Caledonians, and commanded them, in chief, againſt the incurſions
    of the Romans. The genealogiſts of the North have traced his family far back, and given a liſt
    of his anceſtors to <hi>Cuan-mór nan lan</hi>, or Conmor of the ſwords, who, according to them,
    was the firſt who croſſed the <hi>great ſea</hi>, to Caledonia, from which circumſtance his name
    proceeded, which ſignifies <hi>Great ocean</hi>. Genealogies of ſo ancient a date, however, are
    little to be depended upon. </p>
   </note> was the brother of Trathal, firſt of mortal men. His battles were on every coaſt. A
   thouſand ſtreams rolled down the blood of his foes. His fame filled green Erin, like a pleaſant
   gale. 
   <!-- D 2 The -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210036" facs="../img/1773-149.pbm"/>
   <!-- 26 T E M O R A: Book II. --> The nations gathered in Ullin, and they bleſſed the king; the
   king of the race of their fathers, from the land of Selma.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> chiefs<note>
   <p> The chiefs of the Fir-bolg who poſſeſſed themſelves of the ſouth of Ireland, prior, perhaps,
    to the ſettlement of the <hi>Caël</hi> of Caledonia, and the Hebrides, in Ulſter. From the
    ſequel, it appears that the Fir-bolg were, by much, the moſt powerful nation; and it is probable
    that the Caël muſt have ſubmitted to them, had they not received ſuccours from their
    mother-country, under the command of Conar. </p>
   </note> of the ſouth were gathered, in the darkneſs of their pride. In the horrid cave of Muma,
   they mixed their ſecret words. Thither often, they ſaid, the ſpirits of their fathers came;
   ſhewing their pale forms from the chinky rocks : reminding them of the honor of Bolga. “Why
   ſhould Conar reign,” they ſaid, “the ſon of reſounding Morven ?”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">They</hi> came forth, like the ſtreams of the deſart, with the roar of their
   hundred tribes. Conar was a rock before them : broken they rolled on every ſide. But often they
   returned, and the ſons of Selma fell. The king ſtood, among the tombs of his warriors. He darkly
   bent his mournful face. His ſoul was rolled into itſelf ; and he had marked the place, where he
   was to fall ; when Trathal came, in his ſtrength, his brother from cloudy Morven. Nor did he come
   <!-- alone. -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210037" facs="../img/1773-152.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. Av EPIC POEM. 37 --> alone, Colgar<note>
   <p> Colg-er, <hi>fiercely-looking warrior</hi>. Sulin-corma, <hi>blue eyes</hi>. Colgar was the
    eldeſt of the ſons of Trathal: Comhal, who was the father of Fingal, was very young when the
    preſent expedition to Ireland happened, It is remarkable, that, of all the anceſtors of Fingal,
    tradition makes the leaſt mention of Comhal ; which, probably, proceeded from the unfortunate
    life and untimely death of that hero. From ſome paſſages, concerning him, we learn, indeed, that
    he was brave, but he wanted conduct. </p>
   </note> was at his ſide; Colgar the ſon of the King and of white-boſomed Solin-corma.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> Trenmor, cloathed with meteors, deſcends from the halls of thunder,
   pouring the dark ſtorm before him over the troubled ſea ; ſo Colgar deſcended to battle, and
   waſted the ecchoing field. His father rejoiced over the hero : but an arrow came! His tomb was
   raiſed, without a tear. The King was to revenge his ſon. He lightened forward in battle, till
   Bolga yielded at her ſtreams !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">When</hi> peace returned to the land : When his blue waves bore the king to
   Morven : then he remembered his ſon, and poured the ſilent tear. Thrice did the bards, at the
   cave of Furmono, call the ſoul of Colgar. They called him to the hills of his land. He heard them
   in his miſt, Trathal placed his ſword in the cave, that the ſpirit of his ſon might rejoice.
   <!-- D 3 © COLGAR, --> </p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73210038" facs="../img/1773-155.pbm"/>
   <!-- 38 TE M O R A: Book II. --> “<hi rend="sc">Colgar</hi><note>
   <p> The poem begins here to mark ſtrongly the character of Fillan, who is to make ſo great a
    figure in the ſequel. He has the impatience, the ambition and fire which are peculiar to a young
    hero. Kindled with the fame of Colgar, he forgets his untimely fall. From Fillan's expreſſions
    in this paſſage, it would ſeem, that he was neglected by Fingal, on account of his youth. </p>
   </note>, ſon of Trathal!” ſaid Fillan, “thou wert renowned in youth! But the king hath not marked
   my ſword, bright-ſtreaming on the field. I go forth with the crowd. I return, without my fame.
   But the foe approaches, Oſſian ! I hear their murmur on the heath. The ſound of their ſteps is
   like thunder, in the boſom of the ground, when the rocking hills ſhake their groves, and not a
   blaſt pours from the darkened ſky !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Ossian</hi> turned ſudden on his ſpear. He raiſed the flame of an oak on high. I
   ſpread it large, on Mora's wind. Cathmor ſtopt in his courſe. Gleaming he ſtood, like a rock, on
   whoſe ſides are the wandering of blaſts; which ſeize its ecchoing ſtreams and clothe them over
   with ice. So ſtood the friend<note>
   <p> Cathmor is diſtinguiſhed, by this honourable title, on account of his generoſity to
    ſtrangers, which was ſo great as to be remarkable even in thoſe days of hoſpitality. </p>
   </note> of ſtrangers ! The winds lift his heavy locks. Thou art the talleſt of the race of Erin,
   king of ſtreamy Atha ! 
   <!-- “FIRST --> </p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73210039" facs="../img/1773-158.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 39 --> “<hi rend="sc">First</hi> of bards,” ſaid Cathmor, “Fonar<note>
   <p> <hi>Fónar, the man of ſong</hi>. Before the introduction of Chriſtianity a name was not
    impoſed upon any perſon, till he had diſtinguiſhed himſelf by ſome remarkable action, from which
    his name ſhould be derived. </p>
   </note>, call the chiefs of Erin. Call red-hair'd Cormar : dark-browed Malthos: the
   ſide-long-looking gloom of Maronan. Let the pride of Foldath appear. The red-rolling eye of
   Turlotho. Nor let Hidalla be forgot ; his voice, in danger, is the ſound of a ſhower, when it
   falls in the blaſted vale, near Atha's falling ſtream.” Pleaſant is its ſound, on the plain,
   whilſt broken thunder travels over the ſky !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">They</hi> came, in their clanging arms. They bent forward to his voice, as if a
   fpirit of their fathers ſpoke from a cloud of night. Dreadful ſhone they to the light; like the
   fall of the ſtream of Brumo<note>
   <p> Brumo was a place of worſhip (Fing. b. 6.) in Craca, which is ſuppoſed to be one of the iſles
    of Shetland. It was thought, that the ſpirits of the deceaſed haunted it, by night, which adds
    more terror to the deſcription introduced here. <hi>The horrid circle of Brumo, where often,
    they ſaid, the ghoſts of the dead howled round the ſtone of fear</hi>. </p>
   </note>, when the meteor lights it, before the nightly ſtranger. Shuddering, he ſtops in his
   journey, and looks up for the beam of the morn ! </p>
  <!-- D4 “Why -->
  <pb xml:id="P73210040" facs="../img/1773-161.pbm"/>
  <!-- 40 T EE M O R A: Book Il, -->
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Why</hi><note xml:id="N_12">
   <p> From this paſſage, it appears, that it was Foldath who had adviſed the night-attack. The
    gloomy character of Foldath is properly contraſted to the generous, the open Cathmor. </p>
   </note> delights Foldath,” ſaid the king, “to pour the blood of foes, by night ? Fails his arm in
   battle, in the beams of day ? Few are the foes before us, why ſhould we clothe us in ſhades? The
   valiant delight to ſhine, in the battles of their land! Thy counſel was in vain, chief of Morna !
   The eyes of Morven do not ſleep. They are watchful, as eagles, on their moſſy rocks. Let each
   collect, beneath his cloud, the ſtrength of his roaring tribe. To-morrow I move, in light, to
   meet the foes of Bolga? Mighty<note xml:id="N_13">
   <p> By this exclamation Cathmor intimates that he intends to revenge the death of his brother
    Cairbar. </p>
   </note>was he, that is low, the race of Borbar-Duthul !” </p>
  <p> “<hi rend="sc">Not</hi> unmarked !” ſaid Foldath, “were my ſteps before thy race. In light, I
   met the foes of Cairbar. The warrior praiſed my deeds. But his ſtone was raiſed without a tear?
   No bard ſung<note xml:id="N_14">
   <p> To have no funeral elegy ſung over his tomb, was, among the Celtæ, reckoned the greateſt
    misfortune that could befal a man ; as his ſoul could not otherwiſe be admitted to the <hi>airy
    hall of his fathers</hi>. </p>
   </note> over Erin's king. Shall his foes rejoice along their moſſy hills? No: they muſt not
   rejoice ! He was the friend of Foldath ! Our words were mixed, in ſecret, in Morna's ſilent cave;
   whilſt 
   <!-- thou, -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210041" facs="../img/1773-164.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 41 --> thou, a boy in the field, purſuedſt the thiſtle's beard. With
   Morna's ſons I ſhall ruſh abroad, and find the foe, on his duſky hills. Fingal ſhall lie, without
   his ſong, the grey-haired king of Selma.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Dost</hi> thou think, thou feeble man,” replied Cathmor, half-enraged : “Doſt
   thou think Fingal can fall, without his fame, in Erin? Could the bards be ſilent, at the tomb of
   Selma's king ? The ſong would burſt in ſecret ! the ſpirit of the king would rejoice! It is when
   thou ſhalt fall, that the bard ſhall forget the ſong. Thou art dark, chief of Morna, though thine
   arm is a tempeſt in war. Do I forget the king of Erin, in his narrow houſe? My ſoul is not loſt
   to Cairbar, the brother of my love! I marked the bright beams of joy, which travelled over his
   cloudy mind, when I returned, with fame, to Atha of the ſtreams.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Tall</hi> they removed, beneath the words of the king. Each to his own dark tribe
   ; where, humming, they rolled on the heath, faint-glittering to the ſtars: like waves, in a rocky
   bay, before the nightly wind. Beneath an oak, lay the chief of Atha. His ſhield, a duſky round,
   hung high. Near him, againſt a rock, leaned 
   <!-- 9 the -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210042" facs="../img/1773-167.pbm"/>
   <!-- 42 T E M O R A: Book II. --> the fair ſtranger<note>
   <p> By <hi>the ſtranger of Inis huna</hi>, is meant Sulmalla, the daughter of Conmor king of
    Inis-huna, the ancient name of that part of South-Britain, which is next to the Iriſh coaſt. She
    had followed Cathmor in diſguiſe. Her ſtory is related at large in the fourth book. </p>
   </note> of Inis-huna: that beam of light, with wandering locks, from Lumon of the roes. At
   diſtance roſe the voice of Fonar, with the deeds of the days of old. The ſong fails, at times, in
   Lubar's growing roar !</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Crothar</hi><note>
   <p> Crothar was the anceſtor of Cathmor, and the firſt of his family, who had ſettled in Atha, It
    was, in his time, that the firſt wars were kindled between the Fir-bolg and Cal. The propriety
    of the epiſode is evident; as the conteſt which originally roſe between Crothar and Conar,
    ſubſiſted afterwards between their poſterity, and was the foundation of the ſtory of the poem.
   </p>
   </note>,” begun the bard,“firſt dwelt at Atha's moſſy ſtream! A thouſand<note>
   <p> From this circumſtance we may learn that the art of building with ſtone was not known in
    Ireland ſo early as the days of Crothar. When the colony were long ſettled in the country, the
    arts of civil life began to increaſe among them, for we find mention made of the <hi>towers of
    Atha</hi> in the time of Cathmor, which could not well be applied to wooden buildings. In
    Caledonia they begun very early to build with ſtone. None of the houſes of Fingal, excepting
    Ti-foirmal, were of wood. Ti-foirmal was the great hall where the bards met to repeat their
    compoſitions annually, before they ſubmitted them to the judgment of the king in Selma. By ſome
    accident or other, this wooden houſe happened to be burnt, and an ancient bard, in the character
    of Oſſian, has left us a curious catalogue of the furniture which it contained. The poem is not
    juſt now in my hands, otherwiſe I would lay here a tranſlation of it before the reader. It has
    little poetical merit, and evidently bears the marks of a later period. </p>
   </note> oaks, from the mountains, formed his ecchoing hall. The gathering of the people was
   there, around the feaſt of the blue-eyed king. But who, among his chiefs, was like the ſtately
   Crothar ? Warriors kindled in his preſence. The young 
   <!-- şigh -->
   <!-- we -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210043" facs="../img/1773-170.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II, An EPIC POEM, 43 --> ſigh of the virgins roſe. In Alnecma<note>
   <p> Alnecma, or Alnecmacht, was the ancient name of Connaught. Ullin is ſtill the Iriſh name of
    the province of Ulſter. To avoid the multiplying of notes, I ſhall here give the ſignification
    of the names in this epiſode. Drumardo, <hi>high ridge</hi>, Cathmin, <hi>calm in battle</hi>
    Cón-lamha, <hi>ſoft hand</hi>, Turloch, <hi>man of the quiver</hi>. Cormul, <hi>blue eye</hi>.
   </p>
   </note> was the warrior honoured: the firſt of the race of Bolga.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">He</hi> purſued the chace in Ullin : on the moſs covered top of Drumardo. From
   the wood looked the daughter of Cathmin, the blue-rolling eye of Con-lama. Her ſigh roſe in
   ſecret. She bent her head, midſt her wandering locks. The moon looked in, at night, and ſaw the
   white-toſſing of her arms ; for ſhe thought of the mighty Crothar, in the ſeaſon of dreams.”</p>
  <p>
   <!-- “THREE -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210044" facs="../img/1773-173.pbm"/>
   <!-- 44 T E M O R A: Book II, --> “<hi rend="sc">Three</hi> days feaſted Crothar with Cathmin. On
   the fourth they awaked the hinds. Con-lama moved to the chace, with all her lovely ſteps. She met
   Crothar in the narrow path. The bow fell, at once, from her hand. She turned her face away, and
   half-hid it with her locks. The love of Crothar roſe. He brought the white-boſomed maid to Atha.
   Bards raiſed the ſong in her preſence. Joy dwelt round the daughter of Cathmin.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> pride of Turloch roſe, a youth who loved the white-handed Con-láma. He
   came, with battle, to Alnecma; to Atha of the roes. Cormul went forth to the ſtrife, the brother
   of car-borne Crothar. He went forth, but he fell. The ſigh of his people roſe. Silent and tall,
   acroſs the ſtream, came the darkening ſtrength of Crothar : he rolled the foe from Alnecoma. He
   returned, mid the joy of Con-lama.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Battle</hi> on battle comes. Blood is poured on blood. The tombs of the valiant
   riſe. Erin's clouds are hung round with ghoſts. The chiefs of the ſouth gathered round the
   ecchoing ſhield of Crothar. He came, with death, to the paths of the foe. The virgins wept, by
   the ſtreams of Ullin. They looked to the miſt of the hill ; No hunter deſcended from its folds.
   Silence 
   <!-- darkened -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210045" facs="../img/1773-176.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book I. An EPIC POEM. 45 --> darkened in the land. Blaſts ſighed lonely on graſſy
   tombs.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Descending</hi> like the eagle of heaven, with all his ruſtling wings, when he
   forſakes the blaſt, with joy, the ſon of Trenmor came; Conar, arm of death, from Morven of the
   groves. He poured his might along green Erin. Death dimly ſtrode behind his ſword. The ſons of
   Bolga fled, from his courſe, as from a ſtream, that burſting from the ſtormy deſart, rolls the
   fields together, with all their ecchoing woods. Crothar<note>
   <p> The delicacy here, with regard to Crothar, is proper. As he was the anceſtor of Cathmor, to
    whom the epiſode is addreſſed, the bard ſoftens his defeat, by only mentioning that his people
    fled. Cathmor took the ſong of Fonar in an unfavourable light. The bards, being of the order of
    the Druids, who pretended to a foreknowlege of events, were ſuppoſed to have ſome ſupernatural
    preſcience of futurity. The king thought, that the choice of Fonar's ſong proceeded, from his
    foreſeeing the unfortunate iſſue of the war ; and that his own fate was ſhadowed out, in that of
    his anceſtor Crothar. The attitude of the bard, after the reprimand of his patron, is
    pictureſque and affecting, We admire the ſpeech of Cathmor, but lament the effect it has on the
    feeling ſoul of the good old poet. </p>
   </note> met him in battle: but Alnecma's warriors fled. The king of Atha ſlowly retired, in the
   grief of his ſoul. He, afterwards, ſhone in the ſouth; but dim as the ſun of Autumn, when he
   viſits, in his robes of miſt, Lara of 
   <!-- dark -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210046" facs="../img/1773-179.pbm"/>
   <!-- 46 T E M O R A: Book II. --> dark ſtreams. The withered graſs is covered with dew : the
   field, tho' bright, is ſad !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Why</hi> wakes the bard before me,” ſaid Cathmor, “the memory of thoſe who fled?
   Has ſome ghoſt, from his duſky cloud, bent forward to thine ear; to frighten Cathmor from the
   field, with the tales of old ? Dwellers of the ſkirts of night, your voice is but a blaſt to me;
   which takes the grey thiſtle's head, and ſtrews its beard on ſtreams. Within my boſom is a voice.
   Others hear it not. His ſoul forbids the king of Erin to ſhrink back from war.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Abashed</hi> the bard ſinks back in night : retired he bends above a ſtream. His
   thoughts are on the days of Atha, when Cathmor heard his ſong with joy. His tears come rolling
   down. The winds are in his beard. <hi rend="sc">Erin</hi> ſleeps around. No ſleep comes down on
   Cathmor's eyes. Dark, in his ſoul, he ſaw the ſpirit of low-laid Cairbar. He ſaw him, without his
   ſong, rolled in a blaſt of night. He roſe. His ſteps were round the hoſt. He ſtruck, at times,
   his ecchoing ſhield. The ſound reached Oſſian's ear, on Mora's moſſy brow.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Fillan</hi>,” I ſaid, “the foes advance. I hear the ſhield of war. Stand thou in
   the narrow path, Oſſian ſhall mark their courſe, If 
   <!-- 2 over -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210047" facs="../img/1773-182.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II, An EPIC POEM. 47 --> over my fall the hoſt ſhould pour ; then be thy buckler heard.
   Awake the king on his heath, leſt his fame ſhould fly away.” I ſtrode in all my rattling arms;
   wide-bounding over a ſtream that darkly-winded, in the field, before the king of Atha. Green
   Atha's king, with lifted ſpear, came forward on my courſe. Now would we have mixed in horrid
   fray, like two contending ghoſts, that bending forward, from two clouds, ſend forth the roaring
   winds; did not Oſſian behold, on high, the helmet of Erin's kings. The Eagle's wing ſpread above
   it, ruſtling in the breeze. A red ſtar looked thro' the plumes. I ſtopt the lifted ſpear.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">The</hi> helmet of kings is before me! Who art thou ſon of night? Shall Oſſian's
   ſpear be renowned, when thou art lowly-laid ?” At once he dropt the gleaming lance. Growing
   before me ſeemed the form. He ſtretched his hand in night. He ſpoke the words of kings.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Friend</hi> of the ſpirits of heroes, do I meet thee thus in ſhades? I have
   wiſhed for thy ſtately ſteps in Atha, in the days of joy. Why ſhould my ſpear now ariſe ? The ſun
   muſt behold us, Oſſian; when we bend, gleaming, in the ſtrife. Future warriors ſhall mark the
   place : and, ſhuddering, think of other years, They 
   <!-- şhall -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210048" facs="../img/1773-185.pbm"/>
   <!-- 48 TE M O R A: Book II. --> ſhall mark it, like the haunt of ghoſts, pleaſant and dreadful
   to the ſoul.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Shall</hi> it then be forgot,” I ſaid, “where we meet in peace? Is the
   remembrance of battles always pleaſant to the ſoul? Do not we behold, with joy, the place where
   our fathers feaſted ? But our eyes are full of tears, on the fields of their war. This ſtone
   ſhall riſe, with all its moſs, and ſpeak to other years. “Here Cathmor and Oſſian met! the
   warriors met in peace !” When thou, O ſtone, ſhalt fail. When Lubar's ſtream ſhall roll away !
   then ſhall the traveller come, and bend here, perhaps, in reſt. When the darkened moon is rolled
   over his head, our ſhadowy forms may come, and, mixing with his dreams, remind him of this place.
   But why turneſt thou ſo dark away, ſon of Borbar-duthul<note>
   <p> Borbar-duthul, <hi>the ſurly warrior of the dark brown eyes</hi>. That his name ſuited well
    with his character, we may eaſily conceive, from the ſtory delivered concerning him, by Malthos,
    toward the end of the ſixth book. He was the brother of that Colculla, who is mentioned in the
    epiſode which begins the fourth book. </p>
   </note> ?”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Not</hi> forgot, ſon of Fingal, ſhall we aſcend theſe winds. Our deeds are
   ſtreams of light, before the eyes of bards. But darkneſs is rolled on Atha : the king is low,
   without his 
   <!-- şong : -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210049" facs="../img/1773-188.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. AN EPIC POEM. 49 --> ſong: ſtill there was a beam towards Cathmor from his ſtormy
   ſoul; like the moon, in a cloud, amidſt the dark-red courſe of thunder.”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Erin,” I replied, “my wrath dwells not, in his earth<note>
   <p> This reply abounds with the ſentiments of a noble mind. Tho', of all men living, he was the
    moſt injured by Cairbar, yet he lays aſide his rage as the <hi>foe was low</hi>. How different
    is this from the behaviour of the heroes of other ancient poems ? <foreign xml:lang="la"
    ><hi>Cynthius aurem vellit</hi></foreign>. </p>
   </note>. My hatred flies, on eagle-wing, from the foe that is low. He ſhall hear the ſong of
   bards. Cairbar ſhall rejoice on his winds,”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Cathmor's</hi> ſwelling ſoul aroſe. He took the dagger from his ſide; and placed
   it gleaming in my hand. He placed it, in my hand, with ſighs, and, ſilent, ſtrode away, Mine eyes
   followed his departure. He dimly gleamed, like the form of a ghoſt, which meets a traveller, by
   night, on the dark-ſkirted heath. His words are dark like ſongs of old : with morning ſtrides the
   unfiniſhed ſhade away !<note>
   <p> The morning of the ſecond day, from the opening of the poem comes on. After the death of
    Cuthullin, Carril, the ſon of Kinfena, his bard, retired to the cave of Tura, which was in the
    neighbourhood of Moi-lena, the fcene of the poem of Temora. His caſual appearance here enables
    Oſſian to fulfil immediately the promiſe he had made to Cathmor, of cauſing the <hi>funeral
    ſong</hi> to be pronounced over the tomb of Cairbar. This book takes up only the ſpace of a few
    hours. </p>
   </note></p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Who</hi> comes from Lubar's vale? From the ſkirts of the morning miſt ? The drops
   of <!-- Ven -->
   <!-- - Vol, II, 8 fulfil -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210050" facs="../img/1773-191.pbm"/>
   <!-- 50 T E M O R A: Book Il. --> heaven are on his head. His ſteps are in the paths of
   the ſad. It is Carril of other times. He comes from Tura's ſilent cave. I behold it dark in the
   rock, thro' the thin folds of miſt. There, perhaps, Cuthullin ſits, on the blaſt which bends its
   trees. Pleaſant is the ſong of the morning from the bard of Erin!</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">The</hi> waves crowd away,” ſaid Carril. “They crowd away for fear. They hear
   the ſound of thy coming forth, O ſun! Terrible is thy beauty, ſon of heaven, when death is
   deſcending on thy locks: when thou rolleſt thy vapors before thee, over the blaſted hoſt. But
   pleaſant is thy beam to the hunter, ſitting by the rock in a ſtorm, when thou ſheweſt thyſelf
   from the parted cloud, and brighteneſt his dewy locks: he looks down on the ſtreamy vale, and
   beholds the deſcent of roes! How long ſhalt thou riſe on war, and roll, a bloody ſhield, thro'
   heaven ? I ſee the deaths of heroes, dark-wandering over thy face!”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Why</hi> wander the words of Carril?” I ſaid. “Does the ſon of heaven mourn ? He
   is unſtained in his courſe, ever rejoicing in his fire. 
   <!-- 8 Roll -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210051" facs="../img/1773-194.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book II. An EPIC POEM. 51 --> Roll on, thou careleſs light. Thou too, perhaps, muſt fall.
   Thy darkening hour may ſeize thee, ſtruggling, as thou rolleſt through thy ſky. But pleaſant is
   the voice of the bard: pleaſant to Oſſian's ſoul! It is like the ſhower of the morning, when it
   comes through the ruſtling vale, on which the ſun looks thro miſt, juſt riſing from his rocks.
   But this is no time, O bard, to ſit down, at the ſtrife of ſong. Fingal is in arms on the vale.
   Thou ſeeft the flaming ſhield of the king. His face darkens between his locks. He beholds the
   wide rolling of Erin. Does not Carril behold that tomb, beſide the roaring ſtream ? Three ſtones
   lift their grey heads, beneath a bending oak. A king is lowly laid ! Give thou his ſoul to the
   wind. He is the brother of Cathmor ! Open his airy hall! Let thy ſong be a ſtream of joy to
   Cairbar's darkened ghoſt.” 
   <!-- E 2 -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210052" facs="../img/1773-197.pbm"/> </p>
 </div>
</div>
