<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><front/><body>
<pb n="73210117" facs="1773-392.pbm"/>
 <div><head>T E M O R A: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK VI</head><p> </p></div> <!--  -->
<!-- I 3 -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210118" facs="1773-395.pbm"/>
 <div><head>ARGUMENT to Book VI.</head><p> <hi rend="sc">This</hi> book opens with a ſpeech of Fingal, who ſees Cathmor deſcending to the aſſiſtance of his flying army. The king diſpatches Oſſian to the relief of Fillan. He himſelf retires behind the rock of Cormul, to avoid the ſight of the engagement between his ſon and Cathmor. Oſſian advances. The deſcent of Cathmor deſcribed. He rallies the army, renews the battle, and, before Oſſian could arrive, engages Fillan himſelf. Upon the approach of Oſſian, the combat between the two heroes ceaſes. Oſſian and Cathmor prepare to fight, but night coming on prevents them. Oſſian returns to the place where Cathmor and Fillan fought. He finds Fillan mortally wounded, and leaning againſt a rock. Their diſcourſe. Fillan dies: his body is laid, by Oſſian, in a neighbouring cave. The Caledonian army return to Fingal. He queſtions them about his ſon, and, underſtanding that he was killed, retires, in ſilence, to the rock of Cormul. Upon the retreat of the army of Fingal, the Fir-bolg advance. Cathmor finds Bran, one of the dogs of Fingal, lying on the ſhield of Fillan, before the entrance of the cave, where the body of that hero lay. His reflections thereupon. He returns, in a melancholy mood, to his army. Malthos endeavours to comfort him, by the example of his father Borbar-duthal. Cathmor retires to reſt. The ſong of Sul-malla concludes the book, which ends about the middle of the third night, from the opening of the poem. </p></div> <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210119" facs="1773-398.pbm"/>
<!-- [ 119 ] -->
 <div><head>T E M O R A: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK: VI.</head><p><note><p> Fingal ſpeaks. </p></note>“<hi rend="sc">Cathmor</hi> riſes on his hill! Shall Fingal take the ſword of Luno? But what ſhould become of thy fame, ſon of white-boſomed Clatho? Turn not thine eyes from Fingal, fair daughter of Iniſtore. I ſhall not quench thy early beam. It ſhines along my ſoul. Riſe, wood-ſkirted Mora, riſe between the war and me! Why ſhould Fingal behold the ſtrife, leſt his dark-haired warrior ſhould fall ! Amidſt the ſong, O Carril, pour the ſound of the trembling harp! Here are the voices of rocks! and there the bright tumbling of waters. Father of Oſcar lift the ſpear ! Defend the young in arms. Conceal thy ſteps from Fillan. He <!--  -->
<!-- I 4 muſt -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210120" facs="1773-401.pbm"/>
<!-- 120 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 muſt not know that I doubt his ſteel. No cloud of mine ſhall riſe, my ſon, upon thy ſoul of fire !”</p><p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> ſunk behind his rock, amid the ſound of Carril's ſong. Brightening, in my growing ſoul, 1 took the ſpear of Temora<note><p>The <hi>ſpear of Temora</hi> was that which Oſcar had received, in a preſent, from Cormac, the ſon of Artho, king of Ireland. It was of it that Cairbar made the pretext for quarrelling with Oſcar, at the feaſt, in the firſt book. </p></note>. I ſaw, along Moi-lena, the wild tumbling of battle; the ſtrife of death, in gleaming rows, disjoined and broken round. Fillan is a beam of fire. From wing to wing is his waſteful courſe. The ridges of war melt before him. They are rolled, in ſmoak, from the fields !</p><p><hi rend="sc">Now</hi> is the coming forth of Cathmor, in the armour of kings! Dark-waves the eagle's wing, above his helmet of fire. Unconcerned are his ſteps, as if they were to the chace of Erin. He raiſes, at times, his terrible voice. Erin, abaſhed, gathers round. Their ſouls return back, like a ſtream. They wonder at the ſteps of their fear. He roſe, like the beam of the morning, on a haunted heath : the traveller looks back, with bending eye, on the field of dreadful forms ! Sudden, from the rock of Moilena, are Sul malla's trembling ſteps. An oak <!--  -->
<!-- 2 takes -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210121" facs="1773-404.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 121 -->
 takes the ſpear from her hand. Half-bent ſhe looſes the lance. But then are her eyes on the king, from amid her wandering locks! No friendly ſtrife is before thee ! No light contending of bows, as when the youth of Inis-huna<note><p> Clu-ba, <hi>winding bay</hi> ; an arm of the ſea in Inis-huna, or the weſtern coaſt of South-Britain. It was in this bay that Cathmor was wind-bound when Sul-malla came, in the diſguiſe of a young warrior, to accompany him in his voyage to Ireland. Conmor, the father of Sul-malla, as is inſinuated at the cloſe of the fourth book, was dead before the departure of his daughter. </p></note> come forth beneath the eye of Conmor !</p><p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> the rock of Runo, which takes the paſſing clouds as they fly, ſeems growing, in gathered darkneſs, over the ſtreamy heath ; ſo ſeems the chief of Atha taller, as gather his people around. As different blaſts fly over the ſea, each behind its dark-blue wave, ſo Cathmor's words, on every ſide, pour his warriors forth. Nor ſilent on his hill is Fillan. He mixes his words with his ecchoing ſhield. An eagle he ſeemed, with ſounding wings, caliing the wind to his rock, when he ſees the coming forth of the roes, on Lutha's<note><p> Lutha was the name of a valley in Morven. There dwelt Toſcar the ſon of Conloch, the father of Malvina, who, upon that account, is often called <hi>the maid of Lutha</hi>, Lutha ſignifies <hi>ſwift ſtream</hi>. </p></note> ruthy field ! <!--  -->
<!-- Now -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210122" facs="1773-407.pbm"/>
<!-- 122 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 Now they bend forward in battle. Death's hundred voices ariſe. The kings, on either ſide, were like fires on the ſouls of the hoſts. Oſſian bounded along. High rocks and trees ruſh tall between the war and me. But I hear the noiſe of ſteel, between my clanging arms. Rifing, gleaming, on the hill, I behold the backward ſteps of hoſts : their backward ſteps, on either ſide, and wildly-looking eyes. The chiefs were met in dreadful fight! The two blue-ſhielded kings! Tall and dark, through gleams of ſteel, are ſeen the ſtriving heroes! I ruſh. My fears for Fillan fly, burning acroſs my ſoul.</p><p><hi rend="sc">I come</hi>. Nor Cathmor flies; nor yet comes on; he ſidelong ſtalks along. An icy rock, cold, tall he ſeems. I call forth all my ſteel. Silent awhile we ſtride, on either ſide of a ruſhing ſtream : then, ſudden turning, all at once, we raiſe our pointed ſpears! We raiſe our ſpears, but night comes down. It is dark and ſilent round ; but where the diſtant ſteps of hoſts are ſounding over the heath!</p><p><hi rend="sc">I come</hi> to the place where Fillan fought. Nor voice, nor ſound is there. A broken helmet lies on earth, a buckler cleft in twain. Where, Fillan, where art thou, young chief of ecchoing Morven ? He hears me leaning on a rock, <!--  -->
<!-- which -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210123" facs="1773-410.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 123 -->
 which bends its grey head over the ſtream. He hears ; but ſullen, dark he ſtands. Ar length I ſaw the hero !</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Why</hi> ſtandeſt thou, robed in darkneſs, ſon of woody Selma ? Bright is thy path, my brother, in this dark-brown field ! Long has been thy ſtrife in battle! Now the horn of Fingal is heard. Aſcend to the cloud of thy father, to his hill of feaſts. In the evening miſt he ſits, and hears the ſound of Carril's harp. Carry joy to the aged, young breakers of the ſhields !”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Can</hi> the vanquiſhed carry joy ? Oſſian, no ſhield is mine ! It lies broken on the field. The eagle-wing of my helmet is torn. It is when foes fly before them, that fathers delight in their ſons. But their ſighs burſt forth, in ſecret, when their young warriors yield. No : Fillan ſhall not behold the king! Why ſhould the hero mourn ?”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of blue-eyed Clatho! O Fillan, awake not my ſoul ! Wert thou not a burning fire before him ? Shall he not rejoice? Such fame belongs not to Oſſian ; yet is the king ſtill a ſun to. me. He looks on my ſteps, with joy. Shadows never riſe on his face. Aſcend, O Fillan, to Mora ! His feaſt is ſpread in the folds of miſt.”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Ossian</hi>! give me that broken ſhield : theſe feathers that are rolled in the wind. Place them <!--  -->
<!-- near -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210124" facs="1773-413.pbm"/>
<!-- 124 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 near to Fillan, that leſs of his fame may fall. Oſſian, I begin to fail. Lay me in that hollow rock. Raiſe no ſtone above, left one ſhould aſk about my fame. I am fallen in the firſt of my fields; fallen without renown. Let thy voice <hi rend="sc">alone</hi> ſend joy to my flying ſoul. Why ſhould the bard know where dwells the loſt beam of Clatho<note><p> A dialogue between Clatho the mother and Boſmina, the ſiſter of Fillan. </p><sp><speaker><hi rend="sc">Clatho</hi>.</speaker><p> “Daughter of Fingal, ariſe : thou light between thy locks. Lift thy fair head from reſt, foſt-gliding ſun-beam of Selma! I beheld thy arms, on thy breaſt, white-toſſed amidſt thy wandering locks: when the ruſtling breeze of the morning came from the deſart of ſtreams. Haſt thou ſeen thy fathers, Bos-mina, deſcending in thy dreams? Ariſe, daughter of Clatho; dwells there aught of grief in thy ſoul ? </p></sp><sp><speaker><hi rend="sc">Bos-mina</hi>.</speaker><p> A thin form paſſed before me, fading as it flew: like the darkening wave of a breeze, along a field of graſs. Deſcend, from thy wall, O harp, and call back the ſoul of Bos-mina. It has rolled away, like a ſtream, I hear thy pleaſant ſound. I hear thee, O harp, and my voice ſhall riſe.</p><p>How often ſhall ye ruſh to war, ye dwellers of my ſoul ? Your paths are diſtant, kings of men, in Erin of blue ſtreams. Lift thy wing, thou ſouthern breeze, from Clono's darkening heath : ſpread the ſails of Fingal towards the bays of his land.</p><p>But who is that, in his ſtrength, darkening in the preſence of war? His arm ſtretches to the foe, like the beam of the fickly ſun ; when his ſide is cruſted with darkneſs; and he rolls his diſmal courſe through the ſky. Who is it, but the father of Eos-mina ? Shall he return till danger is paſt!</p><p>Fillan, thou art a beam by his ſide ; beautiful, but terrible, is thy light. Thy ſword is before thee, a blue fire of night. When ſhalt thou return to thy roes; to the ſtreams of thy ruſhy fields? When ſhall I behold thee from Mora, while winds ſtrew my long locks on their blaſts! But ſhall a young eagle return from the field where the heroes fall! </p></sp><sp><speaker><hi rend="sc">Clatho</hi>.</speaker><p> Soft, as the ſong of Loda, is the voice of Selma's maid. Pleaſant to the ear of Clatho is the name of the breaker of ſhield. Behold, the king comes from ocean : the ſhield of Morven is borne by bards. The foe has fled before him, like the departure of miſt. I hear not the ſounding wings of my eagle; the ruſhing forth of the ſon of Clatho. Thou art dark, O Fingal ; ſhall the warrior never return?  * * * </p></sp> </note> !” <!--  -->
<!-- “Is -->
<!--  -->
<!-- Fillan, -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210125" facs="1773-416.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 126 -->
 “<hi rend="sc">Is</hi> thy ſpirit on the eddying winds, O Fillan, young breaker of ſhield ! Joy purſue my hero, through his folded clouds. The forms of thy fathers, O Fillan, bend to receive their ſon. I behold the ſpreading of their fire on Mora : the blue-rolling of their miſty wreaths. Joy meet thee my brother! But we are dark and ſad! I Behold the foe round the aged. I behold the waſting away of his fame. Thou art left alone in the field, O grey-haired king of Selma !”</p><p><hi rend="sc">I laid</hi> him in the hollow rock, at the roar of the nightly ſtream. One red ſtar looked in on the hero. Winds lift, at times, his locks. I liſten. No ſound is heard. The warrior flept ! As lightening on a cloud, a thought came ruſhing along my ſoul. My eyes roll in fire: my <!--  -->
<!-- ſtride -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210126" facs="1773-419.pbm"/>
<!-- 126 T E M O R A: Book VI, -->
 ſtride was in the clang of ſteel. “I will find thee, king of Erin! in the gathering of thy thouſands find thee. Why ſhould that cloud eſcape, that quenched our early beam? Kindle your meteors on your hills, my fathers. Light my daring ſteps. I will conſume in wrath<note><p> Here the ſentence is deſignedly left unfiniſhed. The ſenſe is, that he was reſolved, like a deſtroying fire, to conſume Cathmor, who had killed his brother. In the midſt of this reſolution, the ſituation of Fingal ſuggeſts itſelf to him, in a very ſtrong light. He reſolves to return to aſſiſt the king in proſecuting the war. But then his ſhame for not defending his brother, recurs to him. He is determined again to go and find out Cathmor. We may conſider him, as in the act of advancing towards the enemy, when the horn of Fingal ſounded on Mora, and called back his people to his preſence. This ſoliloquy is natural : the reſolutions which ſo ſuddenly follow one another, are expreſſive of a mind extremely agitated with ſorrow and conſcious ſhame ; yet the behaviour of Oſſian, in his execution of the commands of Fingal, is ſo irreprehenſible, that it is not eaſy to determine where he failed in his duty. The truth is, that when men fail in deſigns which they ardently wiſh to accompliſh, they naturally blame themſelves, as the chief cauſe of their diſappointment. </p></note>. But ſhould not I return ! The king is without a ſon, grey-haired among his foes! His arm is not as in the days of old. His fame grows dim in Erin. Let me not behold him, laid low in his latter field. But can I return to the king ? Will he not aſk about his ſon ? “Thou oughteſt to defend young Fillan.” Oſſian will meet the foe! Green Erin, thy ſounding tread is pleaſant <!--  -->
<!-- co -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210127" facs="1773-422.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI, An EPIC POEM. 127 -->
 to my ear. I ruſh on thy ridgy hoſt, to ſhun the eyes of Fingal. I hear the voice of the king, on Mora's miſty top ! He calls his two ſons! I come, my father, in my grief. I come like an eagle, which the flame of night met in the defart, and ſpoiled of half his wings !”</p><p><hi rend="sc">Distant</hi><note><p> “This ſcene, ſays an ingenious writer, and a good judge, is ſolemn, The poet always places his chief character amidſt objects which favour the ſublime. The face of the country, the night, the broken remains of a defeated army, and, above all, the attitude and ſilence of Fingal himſelf, arc circumſtances calculated to impreſs an awful idea on the mind. Oſſian is moſt ſucceſsful in his night-deſcriptions. Dark images ſuited the melancholy temper of his mind. His poems were all compoſed after the active part of his life was over, when he was blind, and had ſurvived all the companions of his youth : we therefore find a veil of melancholy thrown over the whole.” </p></note>, round the king, on Mora, the broken ridges of Morven are rolled. They turned their eyes : each darkly bends, on his own aſhen ſpear. Silent ſtood the king in the midſt. Thought on thought rolled over his ſoul. As waves on a ſecret mountain-lake, each with its back of foam. He looked ; no ſon appeared, with his long-beaming ſpear. The ſighs roſe, crowding, from his ſoul ; but he concealed his grief. At length I ſtood beneath an oak. No voice of mine was heard. What could I ſay to Fingal in his hour of woe? His <!--  -->
<!-- 4 words -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210128" facs="1773-425.pbm"/>
<!-- 128 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 words roſe, at length, in the midſt : the people ſhrunk backward as he ſpoke<note><p>I owe the firſt paragraph of the following note to the ſame pen.</p><p>The abaſhed behaviour of the army of Fingal proceeds rather from ſhame than fear. The king was not of a tyrannical diſpoſition : <hi>He</hi>, as he profeſſes himſelf in the fifth book, <hi>never was a dreadful form, in their preſence, darkened into wrath. His voice was no thunder to their ears : his eye ſent forth no death</hi>. The firſt ages of ſociety are not the times of arbitrary power. As the wants of mankind are few, they retain their independence. It is an advanced ſtate of civilization that moulds the mind to that ſubmiſſion to government, of which ambitious magiſtrates take advantage, and raiſe themſelves into abſolute power.</p><p>It is a vulgar error, that the common Highlanders lived, in abject ſlavery, under their chiefs. Their high ideas of, and attachment to, the heads of their families, probably, led the unintelligent into this miſtake. When the honour of the tribe was concerned, the commands of the chief were obeyed, without reſtriction : but, if individuals were oppreſſed, they threw themſelves into the arms of a neighbouring clan, aſſumed a new name, and were encouraged and protected. The fear of this deſertion, no doubt, made the chiefs cautious in their government. As their conſequence, in the eyes of others, was in proportion to the number of their people, they took care to avoid every thing that tended to diminiſh it.</p><p>It was but very lately that the authority of the laws extended to the Highlands. Before that time the clans were governed, in Civil affairs, not by the verbal commands of the chief, but by what they called <hi>Clechda</hi>, or the traditional precedents of their anceſtors. When differences happened between individuals, ſome of the oldeſt men in the tribe were choſen umpires between the parties, to decide according to the <hi>Clechda</hi>. The chief interpoſed his authority, and, invariably, enforced the deciſion. In their wars, which were frequent,</p><p>on account of family-feuds, the chief was leſs reſerved in the execution of his authority ; and even then he ſeldom extended it to the taking the life of any of his tribe. No crime was capital, except murder ; and that was very unfrequent in the Highlands. No corporal puniſhment, of any kind, was inflicted. The memory of an affront of this ſort would remain, for ages, in a family, and they would ſeize every opportunity to be revenged, unleſs it came immediately from the hands of the chief himſelf; in that caſe it was taken, rather as a fatherly correction, than a legal puniſhment for offences. </p></note>. <!--  -->
<!-- WHERE -->
<!--  -->
<!-- on -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210129" facs="1773-428.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 129 -->
</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Where</hi> is the ſon of Selma, he who led in war? I behold not his ſteps, among my people, returning from the field. Fell the young bounding roe, who was ſo ſtately on my hills? He fell; for ye are ſilent. The ſhield of war is cleft in twain, Let his armour be near to Fingal ; and the ſword of dark-brown Luno. I am waked on my hills; with morning I deſcend to war.”</p><p><hi rend="sc">High</hi><note><p> This rock of Cormul is often mentioned in the preceding part of the poem, It was on it Fingal and Oſſian ſtood to view the battle. The cuſtom of retiring from the army, on the night prior to their engaging in battle, was univerſal among the kings of the Caledonians. Trenmor, the moſt renowned of the anceſtors of Fingal, is mentioned as the firſt who inſtitated this cuſtom. Succeeding bards attributed it to a hero of a latter period. In an old poem, which begins with <hi>MacArcath na ceud ſról</hi>, this cuſtom of retiring from the army, before an engagement, is numbered, among the wiſe inſtitutions of Fergus, the ſon of Arc or Arcath, the firft king of Scots. I</p><p>ſhall here tranſlate the paſſage; in ſome other note I may probably, give all that remains of the poem. <hi>Fergus of the hundred ſtreams, ſon of Arcath who fought of old : thou didſt firſt retire at night: when the foe rolled before thee, in ecchoing fields. Nor bending in reſt is the king : he gathers battles in his ſoul. Fly, ſon of the ſtranger ; with morn he ſhall ruſh abroad</hi>. When, or by whom, this poem was written, is uncertain. </p></note> on Cormul's rock, an oak is flaming to the wind. The grey ſkirts of miſt are rolled around ; thither ſtrode the King in his wrath. <!--  -->
<!-- Diſtant -->
<!--  -->
<!-- Vol II, K . ſhall -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210130" facs="1773-431.pbm"/>
<!-- 130 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 Diſtant from the hoſt he always lay, when battle burnt within his ſoul. On two ſpears hung his ſhield on high ; the gleaming ſign of death ; that ſhield, which he was wont to ſtrike, by night, before he ruſhed to war. It was then his warriors knew, when the king was to lead in ſtrife; for never was this buckler heard, till the wrath of Fingal aroſe. Unequal were his ſteps on high, as he ſhone in the beam of the oak ; he was dreadful as the form of the ſpirit of night, when he cloaths, on hills, his wild geſtures with miſt, and, iſſuing forth, on the troubled ocean, mounts the car of winds.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> ſettled, from the ſtorm, is Erin's ſea of war! they glitter, beneath the moon, and, low-humming, ſtill roll on the field. Alone are the ſteps of Cathmor, before them on the heath ; he hangs forward, with all his arms, on Morven's flying hoſt. Now had he come to the moſſy cave, where Fillan lay in night. One tree was bent above the ſtream, which glittered over the rock. There ſhone to the moon the broken <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<!-- ſhield -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210131" facs="1773-434.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI. An EPIC POEM. 131 -->
 ſhield of Clatho's ſon; and near it, on graſs, lay hairy-footed Bran<note><p> I remember to have met with an old poem, wherein a ſtory of this ſort is very happily introduced. In one of the invaſions of the Danes, Ullin-clundu, a conſiderable chief, on the weſtern coaſt of Scotland, was killed in a rencounter with a flying party of the enemy, who had landed, at no great diſtance, from the place of his reſidence. The few followers who attended him were alſo ſlain. The young wife of Ullin-clundu, who had not heard of his fall. fearing the worſt, on account of his long delay, alarmed the reſt of his tribe, who went in ſearch of him along the ſhore. They did not find him; and the beautiful widow became diſconſolate. At length he was diſcovered, by means of his dog, who ſat on a rock beſide the body, for ſome days. The ſtanza concerning the dog, whoſe name was Du-chos, or <hi>Blackfoot</hi>, is deſcriptive.</p><p>“Dark-ſided Du-chos! feet of wind! cold is thy ſeat on rocks. He (the dog) ſees the roe: his ears are high ; and half he bounds away, He looks around ; but Ullin ſleeps; he droops again his head. The winds come paſt ; dark Duchos thinks, that Ullin's voice is there. But ſtill he beholds him ſilent, laid amidſt the waving heath. Dark ſided Duchos, his voice no more ſhall ſend thee over the heath !” </p></note>. He had miſſed the chief on Mora, and ſearched him along the wind. He thought that the blue-eyed hunter ſlept ; he lay upon his ſhield. No blaſt came over the heath, unknown to bounding Bran.</p><p><hi rend="sc">Cathmor</hi> ſaw the white-breaſted dog; he ſaw the broken ſhield. Darkneſs is blown back on his ſoul; he remembers the falling away of the people. They come, a ſtream ; are rolled away ; another race ſucceeds, “But ſome mark the fields, as they paſs, with their own mighty <!--  -->
<!-- K 2 Names. -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210132" facs="1773-437.pbm"/>
<!-- 132 T E M O R A: Book VI; -->
 names. The heath, through dark-brown years, is theirs; ſome blue ſtream winds to their fame. Of theſe be the chief of Atha, when he lays him down on earth. Often may the voice of future times meet Cathmor in the air : when he ſtrides from wind to wind, or folds himſelf in the wing of a ſtorm.”</p><p><hi rend="sc">Green</hi> Erin gathered round the king, to hear the voice of his power. Their joyful faces bend, unequal, forward, in the light of the oak. They who were terrible were removed : Lubar<note><p> In order to illuſtrate this paſſage, it is proper to lay beſore the reader the ſcene of the two preceding battles. Beween the hills of Mora and Lona lay the plain of Moi-lena, through which ran the river Lubar. The firſt battle, wherein Gaul, the ſon of Mozni, commanded on the Caledonian ſide, was fought on the banks of Lubar. As there was little advantage obtained, on either ſide, the armies, after the battle, retained their former poſitions.</p><p>In the ſecond battle, wherein Fillan commanded, the Iriſh aſter the fall of Foldath, were driven up the hill of Lona; but, upon the coming of Cathmor to their aid, they regained their former ſituation, and drove back the Caledonians, in their turn; ſo that <hi>Lubar winded again in their hoſt</hi>. </p></note> winds again in their hoſt. Cathmor was that beam from heaven which ſhone when his people were dark. He was honoured in the midſt. Their ſouls roſe with ardour around. The king alone no gladneſs ſhewed ; no ſtranger he to war !</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Why</hi> is the king ſo fad,” ſaid Malthos eagle-eyed? “Remains there a foe at Lubar? Lives <!--  -->
<!-- there -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210133" facs="1773-440.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI An EPIC POEM. 132 -->
 there among them, who can lift the ſpear ? Not ſo peaceful was thy father, Borbar-duthul<note><p> Borbar-duthul, the father of Catkmor, was the brother of that Colc-ulla, who is ſaid, in the beginning of the fourth book, to have rebelled againſt Cormac king of Ireland. Borbar-duthul ſeems to have retained all the prejudice of his family againſt the ſucceſſion of the poſterity of Conar, on the Iriſh throne. From this ſhort epiſode we learn ſome facts which tend to throw light on the hiſtory of the times. It appears, that, when Swaran invaded Ireland, he was only oppoſed by the Cael, who poſſeſſed Ulſter, and the north of that iſland. Calmar, the ſon of Matha, whoſe gallant behaviour and death are related in the third book of Fingal, was the only chief of the race of the Fir-bolg, that joined the Cael, or Iriſh Caledonians, during the invaſion of Swaran. The indecent joy, which Borbar-duthul expreſſed, upon the death of Calmar, is well ſuited with that ſpirit of revenge, which ſubſiſted, univerſally, in every country where the feudal ſyſtem was eſtabliſhed. Tt would appear that ſome perſon had carried to Borbar-duthul that weapon, with which, it was pretended, Calmar had been killed. </p></note>, king of ſpears. His rage was a fire that always burned : his joy over fallen foes was great. Three days feaſted the grey-haired hero, when he heard that Calmar fell : Calmar, who aided the race of Ullin, from Lara of the ſtreams. Often did he feel, with his hands, the ſteel which, they ſaid, had pierced his foe. He felt it, with his hands, for Borbar-duthul's eyes had failed. Yet was the king a ſun to his friends; a gale to lift their branches round. Joy was around him in his halls: he loved the ſons of <!--  -->
<!-- K 3 Bolga. -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210134" facs="1773-443.pbm"/>
<!-- 134 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 Bolga. His name remains in Atha, like the awful memory of ghoſts, whoſe preſence was terrible, but they blew the ſtorm away. Now let the voices<note><p> <hi>The voices of Erin</hi>, a poetical expreſſion for the bards of Ireland. </p></note> of Erin raiſe the ſoul of the king; he that ſhone when war was dark, and laid the mighty low. Fonar, from that grey browed rock, pour the tale of other times : pour it on wide-ſkirted Erin, as it ſettles round.”</p><p>« To me,” ſaid Cathmor, “no ſong ſhall riſe ; nor Fonar ſit on the rock of Lubar. The mighty there are laid low. Difturb not their ruſhing ghoſts. Far, Malthos, far remove the ſound of Erin's ſong. I rejoice not over the foe, when he ceaſes to lift the ſpear. With morning we pour our ſtrength abroad. Fingal is wakened on his ecchoing hill.”</p><p><hi rend="sc">Like</hi> waves, blown back by ſudden winds, Erin retired, at the voice of the king. Deeprolled into the field of night, they ſpread their humming tribes. Beneath his own tree, at intervals, each<note><p> Not only the kings, but every petty chief, had anciently their bards attending them, in the field ; and thoſe bards, in proportion to the power of the chiefs, who retained them, had a number of inferior bards in their train. Upon ſolemn occaſions, all the bards, in the army, would join in one chorus; either when they celebrated their viftories, or lamented the</p><p>death of a perſon, worthy and renowned, ſlain in the war. The words were of the compoſition of the arch-bard, retained by the king himſelf, who generally attained to that high office on account of his ſuperior genius for poetry. As the perſons of the bards were ſacred, and the emoluments of their office conſiderable, the order, in ſucceeding times, became very numerous and inſolent. It would appear, that, after the introduction of Chriſtianity, ſome ſerved in the double capacity of bards and clergymen. It was, from this circumſtance, that they had the name of <hi>Chlére</hi>, which is, probably, derived from the Latin Clericus. The <hi>Chlére</hi>, be their name derived from what it will, became, at laſt, a public nuiſance; for, taking advantage of their ſacred character, they went about, in great bodies, and lived, at diſcretion, in the houſes of the chiefs ; till another party, of the ſame order, drove them away by mere dint of ſatire. Some of the indelicate diſputes of theſe worthy poetical combatants are handed down, by tradition, and ſhew how much the bards, at laſt, abuſed the privileges, which the admiration of their countrymen had conferred on the order. It was this inſolent behaviour that induced the chiefs to retrench their number, and to take away thoſe privileges which they were no longer worthy to enjoy. Their indolence, and diſpoſition to lampoon, extinguiſhed all the poetical fervour, which diſtinguiſhed their predeceſſors, and makes us the leſs regret the extinction of the order. </p></note> bard ſat down with his harp. <!--  -->
<!-- They -->
<!--  -->
<!-- death -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210135" facs="1773-446.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI, An EPIC POEM. 135 -->
 They raiſed the ſong, and touched the ſtring : each to the chief he loved. Before a burning oak Sul-malla touched, at times, the harp. She touched the harp, and heard, between, the breezes in her hair. In darkneſs near, lay the king of Atha, beneath an aged tree. The beam of the oak was turned from him ; he ſaw the maid, but was not ſeen. His ſoul poured forth, <!--  -->
<!-- K. 4 18. -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210136" facs="1773-449.pbm"/>
<!-- 136 T E M O R A: Book VI. -->
 in ſecret, when he beheld her fearful eye, “But battle is before thee, ſon of Borbar-duthul.”</p><p><hi rend="sc">Amidst</hi> the harp, at intervals, ſhe liftened whether the warrior ſlept. Her ſoul was up; ſhe longed, in ſecret, to pour her own ſad ſong. The field is ſilent. On their wings, the blaſts of night retire. The bards had ceaſed; and meteors came, red-winding with their ghoſts. The ſky grew dark ; the forms of the dead were blended with the clouds. But heedleſs bends the daughter of Conmor, over the decaying flame. Thou wert alone in her ſoul, car-borne chief of Atha. She raiſed the voice of the ſong, and touched the harp between.</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Clun-galo</hi><note><p> Clun galo, the wife of Conmor, king of Inis-huna, and the mother of Sul-maila. She is here repreſented, as miſſing her daughter, after ſhe had fled with Cathmor. </p></note> came; ſhe miſſed the maid. Where art thou, beam of light ? Hunters, from the moſſy rock, ſaw ye the blue-eyed fair? Are her ſteps on graſſy Lumon ; near the bed of roes? Ah me! I behold her bow in the hall. Where art thou, beam of light ?”</p><p>“<hi rend="sc">Cease</hi><note><p> Sul-malla replies to the ſuppoſed queſtions of her mother. Towards the middle of this paragraph ſhe calls Cathmor <hi>the ſun of her ſoul</hi>, and continues the metaphor throughout. This book ends, we may ſuppoſe, about the middle of the third night, from the opening of the poem. </p></note>, love of Conmor, ceaſe; I hear thee <!--  -->
<!-- not -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210137" facs="1773-452.pbm"/>
<!-- Book VI. Aw EPIC POEM 137 -->
 not on the ridgy heath, My eye is turned to the king, whoſe path is terrible in war. He for whom my ſoul is up, in the ſeaſon of my reſt. Deep-boſomed in war he ſtands, he beholds me not from his cloud. Why, ſun of Sulmalla, doſt thou not look forth ? I dwell in darkneſs here; wide over me flies the thadowy miſt. Filled with dew are my locks : look thou from thy cloud, O ſun of Sul-malla's ſoul.”  * * * <!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210138" facs="1773-455.pbm"/>
</p><p><!--  -->
<!--  -->
<pb n="73210139" facs="1773-458.pbm"/>
</p><p><!--  -->
<!--  -->
</p></div>
</body></text>