<div type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <pb xml:id="P73210097" facs="../img/1773-332.pbm"/>
 <head source="NYPL">TEMORA: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK V.</head>

 <pb xml:id="P73210098" facs="../img/1773-335.pbm"/>

 <div type="argument">
  <head>ARGUMENT to Book V.</head>
  <p> The poet, after a ſhort addreſs to the harp of Cona, deſcribes the arrangement of both armies
   on either ſide of the river Lubar. Fingal gives the command to Fillan ; but, at the ſame time,
   orders Gaul, the ſon of Morni, who had been wounded in the hand in the preceding battle, to
   aſſiſt him with his counſel. The army of the Fir-bolg is commanded by Foldath. The general onſet
   is deſcribed. The great actions of Fillan. He kills Rothmar and Culmin. But when Fillan conquers,
   in one wing, Foldath preſſes hard on the other. He wounds Dermid, the ſon of Duthno, and puts the
   whole wing to flight. Dermid deliberates with himſelf, and, at laſt, reſolves to put a ſtop to
   the progreſs of Foldath, by engaging him in ſingle combat. When the two chiefs were approaching
   towards one another, Fillan came ſuddenly to the relief of Dermid ; engaged Foldath, and killed
   him. The behaviour of Malthos towards the fallen Foldath. Fillan puts the whole army of the
   Fir-bolg to flight. The book cloſes with an addreſs to Clatho, the mother of that hero. </p>
 </div>


 <div type="poem">
  <pb xml:id="P73210099" facs="../img/1773-338.pbm"/>
  <!-- [ 99 ] -->
  <head>TEMORA: AN EPIC POEM. BOOK V.</head>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Thou</hi> dweller between the ſhields, that hang, on high, in Oſſian's hall!
   Deſcend from thy place, O harp, and let me hear thy voice! Son of Alpin, ſtrike the ſtring. Thou
   muſt awake the ſoul of the bard. The murmur of Lora's<note>
   <p> Lora is often mentioned; it was a ſmall and rapid ſtream in the neighbourhood of Selma. There
    is no veſtige of this name now remaining ; though it appears from a very old ſong, which the
    tranſlator has ſeen, that one of the ſmall rivers on the north-weſt coaſt was called Lora ſome
    centuries ago. </p>
   </note> ſtream has rolled the tale away. I ſtand in the cloud of years. Few are its openings
   toward the paſt; and when the viſion comes, it is but dim and dark. I hear thee, harp of Selma !
   my ſoul returns, like a breeze, which the ſun brings back to the vale, where dwelt the lazy miſt
   ! <!-- H 2  <sc>Lubar</sc> -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210100" facs="../img/1773-341.pbm"/>
   <!-- 100 T E M O R A: Book V. --> <hi rend="sc">Lubar</hi><note>
   <p> From ſeveral paſſages in the poem we may form a diſtinct idea of the ſcene of the action of
    Temora. At a ſmall diſtance from one another roſe the hills of Mora and Lora; the firſt
    poſſeſſed by Fingal, the ſecond by the army of Cathmor. Through the intermediate plain ran the
    ſmall river Lubar, on the banks of which all the battles were fought, excepting that between
    Cairbar and Oſcar, related in the firſt book. This laſt mentioned engagement happened to the
    north of the hill of Mora, of which Fingal took poſſeſſion, after the army of Cairbar fell back
    to that of Cathmor. At ſome diſtance, but within ſight of Mora, towards the weſt, Lubar iſſued
    from the mountain of Crommal, and, after a ſhort courſe through the plain of Moi lena,
    diſcharged itſelf into the ſea near the field of battle. Behind the mountain of Crommal ran the
    ſmall ſtream of Lavath, on the banks of which Ferad-artho, the ſon of Cairbre, the only perſon
    remaining of the race of Conar, lived concealed in a cave, during the uſurpation of Cairbar, the
    ſon of Borbar-duthul. </p>
   </note> is bright before me in the windings of its vale. On either ſide, on their hills, riſe the
   tall forms of the kings. Their people are poured around them, bending forward to their words: as
   if their fathers ſpoke, deſcending from the winds. But they themſelves are like two rocks in the
   midſt; each with its dark head of pines, when they are ſeen in the deſart, above low-failing
   miſt. High on their face are ſtreams, which ſpread their foam on blaſts of wind!</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Beneath</hi> the voice of Cathmor pours Erin, like the ſound of flame. Wide they
   come down to Lubar. Before them is the ſtride of Foldath. But Cathmor retires to his hill,
   beneath his <!-- bending -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210101" facs="../img/1773-344.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. 101 --> bending oak. The tumbling of a ſtream is near the king. He
   lifts, at times, his gleaming ſpear. It is a flame to his people, in the midſt of war. Near him
   ſtands the daughter of Con-mor, leaning on a rock. She did not rejoice at the ſtrife. Her ſoul
   delighted not in blood. A valley<note>
   <p> It was to this valley Sul-malla retired, during the laſt and deciſive battle between Fingal
    and Cathmor. It is deſcribed in the ſeventh book, where it is called the vale of Lona, and the
    reſidence of a Druid. </p>
   </note> ſpreads green behind the hill, with its three blue ſtreams. The ſun is there in ſilence.
   The dun mountain-roes come down. On theſe are turned the eyes of Sul-malla in her thoughtful
   mood.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Fingal</hi> beholds Cathmor, on high, the ſon of Borbar-duthul ! he beholds the
   deep-rolling of Erin, on the darkened plain. He ſtrikes that warning boſs, which bids the people
   to obey ; when he ſends his chiefs before them, to the field of renown. Wide riſe their ſpears to
   the ſun. Their ecchoing ſhields reply around. Fear, like a vapour, winds not among the hoſt: for
   <hi rend="sc">he, the king</hi>, is near, the ſtrength of ſtreamy Selma. Gladneſs brightens the
   hero. We hear his words with joy.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Like</hi> the coming forth of winds, is the ſound of Selma's ſons! They are
   mountain waters, determined in their courſe. Hence is <!-- H 3 Fingal -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210102" facs="../img/1773-347.pbm"/>
   <!-- 102 T E M O R A: Book V. --> Fingal renowned. Hence is his name in other lands. He was not a
   lonely beam in danger ; for your ſteps were always near! But never was Fingal a dreadful form, in
   your preſence, darkened into wrath. My voice was no thunder to your ears. Mine eyes ſent forth no
   death. When the haughty appeared, I beheld them not. They were forgot at my feaſts. Like miſt
   they melted away. A young beam is before you! Few are his paths to war ! They are few, but he is
   valiant. Defend my dark-haired ſon. Bring Fillan back with joy. Hereafter he may ſtand alone, His
   form is like his fathers. His ſoul is a flame of their fire. Son of car-borne Morni, move behind
   the youth. Let thy voice reach his ear, from the ſkirts of war. Not unobſerved rolls battle,
   before thee, breaker of the ſhields!”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">The</hi> king ſtrode, at once, away to Cormul's lofty rock. Intermitting, darts
   the light, from his ſhield, as, ſlow the king of heroes moves. Sidelong rolls his eye o'er the
   heath, as forming advance the lines. Graceful, fly his halfgrey locks, round his kingly features,
   now lightened with dreadful joy. Wholly mighty is the chief! Behind him dark and flow I moved.
   Straight came forward the ſtrength of Gaul. His ſhield hung looſe on its thong. He ſpoke, in
   haſte, <!-- 5 to -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210103" facs="../img/1773-350.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V, Av EPIC POEM. 103 --> to Oſſian. “Bind<note>
   <p> It is neceſſary to remember, that Gaul was wounded; which occaſions his requiring here the
    aſſiſtance of Oſſian to bind his ſhield on his ſide, </p>
   </note>, ſon of Fingal, this ſhield ! Bind it high to the ſide of Gaul. The foe may behold it,
   and think I lift the ſpear. If I ſhould fall, let my tomb be hid in the field ; for fall I muſt
   without fame. Mine arm cannot lift the ſteel. Let not Evir-choma hear it, to bluſh between her
   locks. Fillan, the mighty behold us ! Let us not forget the ſtrife. Why ſhould <hi rend="sc"
   >they</hi> come, from their hills, to aid our flying field ?”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> ſtrode onward, with the ſound of his ſhield. My voice purſued him, as he
   went, “Can the ſon of Morni fall, without his fame in Erin? But the deeds of the mighty are
   forgot by themſelves. They ruſh careleſs over the fields of renown. Their words are never heard
   !” I rejoiced over the ſteps of the chief. I ſtrode to the rock of the king, where he ſat, in his
   wandering locks, amid the mountain-wind !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">In</hi> two dark ridges bend the hoſts, toward each other, at Lubar. Here Foldath
   riſes a pillar of darkneſs : there brightens the youth of Fillan. Each, with his ſpear in the
   ſtream, ſent forth the voice of war. Gaul ſtruck the ſhield of Selma. At once they plunge in
   battle! Steel pours its gleam on ſteel : like the fall of ſtreams <!-- H 4 şhone -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210104" facs="../img/1773-353.pbm"/>
   <!-- 104 T E M O R A: Book V, --> ſhone the field, when they mix their foam together, from two
   dark-browed rocks ! Behold he comes the ſon of fame He lays the people low ! Deaths ſit on blaſts
   around him ! Warriors ſtrew thy paths, O Fillan !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Rothmar</hi><note>
   <p> Roth-mar, <hi>the ſound of the ſea before a ſtorm</hi>. Druman-ard, <hi>high-ridge</hi>.
    Cul-min, <hi>ſoft-haired</hi>. Cull-allin, <hi>beautiful locks</hi>. Strutha, <hi>ſtreamy
    river</hi>. </p>
   </note>, the ſhield of warriors, ſtood between two chinky rocks. Two oaks, which winds had bent
   from high, ſpread their branches on either ſide. He rolls his darkening eyes on Fillan, and,
   ſilent, ſhades his friends. Fingal ſaw the approaching fight. The hero's ſoul aroſe. But as the
   ſtone of Loda<note>
   <p> By the ſtone of Loda is meant a place of worſhip among the Scandinavians. The Caledonians in
    their many expeditions to Orkney and Scandinavia, became acquainted with ſome of the rites of
    the religion, which prevailed in thoſe countries, and the ancient poetry frequently alludes to
    them. There are ſome ruins, and circular pales of ſtone, remaining ſtill in Orkney, and the
    iſlands of Shetland, which retain, to this day, the name of <hi>Loda</hi> or <hi>Loden</hi>.
    They ſeem to have differed materially, in their conſtruction, from thoſe Druidical monuments
    which remain in Britain, and the weſtern iſles. The places of worſhip among the Scandinavians
    were originally rude and unadorned. In after ages, when they opened a communication with other
    nations, they adopted their manners, and built temples. That at Upſal, in Sweden, was amazingly
    rich and magnificent. Harquin, of Norway, built one, near Drontheim, little inferior to the
    former; and it went always under the name of Loden. <hi>Mallet, introduction a l'hiſtoire de
    Dannemarc</hi>. </p>
   </note> falls, ſhook, <!-- at -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210105" facs="../img/1773-356.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. 105 --> at once, from rocking Druman-ard, when ſpirits heave the earth
   in their wrath ; ſo fell blue-ſhielded Rothmar.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Near</hi> are the ſteps of Culmin. The youth came, burſting into tears. Wrathful
   he cut the wind, ere yet he mixed his ſtrokes with Fillan. He had firſt bent the bow with
   Rothmar, at the rock of his own blue ſtreams. There they had marked the place of the roe, as the
   ſun-beam flew over the fern. Why, ſon of Cul-allin! Why, Culmin, doſt thou ruſh on that beam<note>
   <p> The poet, metaphorically, calls Fillan a beam of light. Culmin, mentioned here, was the ſon
    of Clonmar, chief of Strutha, by the beautiful Cul-allin. She was ſo remarkable for the beauty
    of her perſon, that ſhe is introduced, frequently, in the ſimilies and alluſions of ancient
    poetry. <hi><foreign xml:lang="gd">Mar Chulaluin Strutha nan ſian</foreign> ; Lovely as
    Cul-allin of Strutha of the ſtorms</hi>. </p>
   </note> of light? It is a fire that conſumes. Son of Cul-allin retire. Your fathers were not
   equal, in the glittering ſtrife of the field. The mother of Culmin remains in the hall. She looks
   forth on blue-rolling Strutha. A whirlwind riſes, on the ſtream, dark-eddying round the ghoſt of
   her ſon. His dogs<note>
   <p> Dogs were thought to be ſenſible of the death of their maſter, let it happen at ever ſo great
    a diſtance. It was alſo the opinion of the times, that the arms which warriors left at home
    became bloody, when they themſelves fell in battle. It was from thoſe ſigns that Cul-allin is
    ſuppoſed to underſtand that her ſon is killed ; in which ſhe is confirmed by the appearance of
    his ghoſt. Her ſudden and ſhort exclamation is more judicious in the poet, than if ſhe had
    extended her complaints to a greater length. The attitude of the fallen youth, and Fillan's
    reflexions over him, come forcibly back on the mind, when we conſider, that the ſuppoſed
    ſituation of the father of Culmin, was ſo ſimilar to that of Fingal, after the death of Fillan
    himſelf. </p>
   </note> are howling <!-- in -->
   <!-- by -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210106" facs="../img/1773-359.pbm"/>
   <!-- 106 T E M O R A: Book V. --> in their place. His ſhield is bloody in the hall. “Art thou
   fallen, my fair-haired ſon, in Erin's diſmal war ?”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> a roe, pierced in ſecret, lies panting, by her wonted ſtreams ; the
   hunter ſurveys her feet of wind : He remembers her ſtately bounding before. So lay the ſon of
   Cul-allin, beneath the eye of Fillan. His hair is rolled in a little ſtream. His blood wanders on
   his ſhield. Still his hand holds the ſword, that failed him in the midſt of danger. “Thou art
   fallen,” ſaid Fillan, “ere yet thy fame was heard. Thy father ſent thee to war. He expects to
   hear of thy deeds. He is grey, perhaps, at his ſtreams, His eyes are toward Moi-lena. But thou
   ſhalt not return, with the ſpoil of the fallen foe !”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Fillan</hi> pours the flight of Erin before him, over the reſounding heath. But,
   man on man, fell Morven before the dark-red rage of Foldath : for, far on the field, he poured
   the roar of half his tribes. Dermid ſtands before him in wrath. The ſons of Selma gathered
   around. <!-- But -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210107" facs="../img/1773-362.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. 107 --> But his ſhield is cleft by Foldath. His people fly over the
   heath.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Then</hi> ſaid the foe, in his pride, “They have fled. My fame begins! Go,
   Malthos, go bid Cathmor guard the dark-rolling of ocean ; that Fingal may not eſcape from my
   ſword. <hi rend="sc">He</hi> muſt lie on earth. Beſide ſome fen ſhall his tomb be ſeen. It ſhall
   riſe without a ſong. His ghoſt ſhall hover, in miſt, over the reedy pool.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Malthos</hi> heard, with darkening doubt. He rolled his ſilent eyes. He knew the
   pride of Foldath. He looked up to Fingal on his hills: then darkly turning, in doubtful mood, he
   plunged his ſword in war.</p>
  <p>In Clono's<note>
   <p> This valley had its name from Clono, ſon of Lethmal of Lora, one of the anceſtors of Dermid,
    the ſon of Duthno. His hiſtory is thus related in an old poem. In the days of Conar, the ſon of
    Trenmor, the firſt king of Ireland, Clono paſſed over into that kingdom, from Caledonia, to aid
    Conar againſt the Fir-bolg. Being remarkable for the beauty of his perſon, he ſoon drew the
    attention of Sulmin, the young wife of an Iriſh chief. She diſcloſed her paſſion, which was not
    properly returned by the Caledonian. The lady ſickened, thro' diſappointment, and her love for
    Clono came to the ears of her huſband. Fired with jealouſy, he vowed revenge. Clono, to avoid
    his rage, departed from Temora, in order to paſs over into Scotland ; and, being benighted in
    the valley mentioned, here, he laid him down to ſleep. <hi>There Lethmal deſcended in the dreams
    of Clono, and told him that danger was near</hi>.</p>
   <sp>
    <speaker>Ghoſt of <hi rend="sc">Lethmal</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> “Ariſe from thy bed of moſs; ſon of low-laid Lethmal, ariſe. The ſound of the coming of
     foes, deſcends along the wind. </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Clono</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> Whoſe voice is that, like many ſtreams, in the ſeaſon of my reſt ? </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker>Ghoſt of <hi rend="sc">Lethmal</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> Ariſe, thou dweller of the ſouls of the lovely ; ſon of Lethmal, ariſe, </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Clono</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> How dreary is the night! The moon is darkened in the ſky; red are the paths of ghoſts, along
     its ſullen face! Green-ſkirted meteors ſet around. Dull is the roaring of ſtreams, from the
     valley of dim forms. I hear thee, ſpirit of my father, on the eddying courſe of the wind. I
     hear thee ; but thou bendeſt not, forward, thy tall form, from the ſkirts of night.” </p>
   </sp>
   <p>As Clono prepared to depart, the huſband of Sulmin came up, with his numerous attendants.
    Clono defended himſelf, but, after a gallant reſiſtance, he was overpowered and ſlain. He was
    buried in the place where he was killed, and the valley was called after his name. Dermid, in
    his requeſt to Gaul the ſon of Morni, which immediately follows this paragraph, alludes to the
    tomb of Clono, and his own connection with that unfortunate chief. </p>
   </note> narrow vale, where bend two trees above the ſtream, dark, in his grief, ſtood
   <!-- Duthno's -->
   <!-- into -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210108" facs="../img/1773-365.pbm"/>
   <!-- 108 T E M O R A: Book V. --> Duthno's ſilent ſon. The blood pours from the ſide of Dermid.
   His ſhield is broken near. His ſpear leans againſt a ſtone. Why, Dermid, why ſo ſad? “I hear the
   roar of battle. My <!-- people -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210109" facs="../img/1773-368.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. 109 --> people are alone. My ſteps are ſlow on the heath; and no
   ſhield is mine. Shall he then prevail ? It is then after Dermid is ſlow! I will call thee forth,
   O Foldath, and meet thee yet in fight.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> took his ſpear, with dreadful joy. The ſon of Morni came. “Stay, ſon of
   Duthno, ſtay thy ſpeed. Thy ſteps are marked with blood. No boſſy ſhield is thine. Why ſhouldſt
   thou fall unarmed?” “Son of Morni! give thou thy ſhield. It has often rolled back the war. I
   ſhall ſtop the chief, in his courſe. Son of Morni! behold that ſtone! It lifts its grey head
   thro' graſs. There dwells a chief of the race of Dermid. Place me there in night.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">He</hi> ſlowly roſe againſt the hill. He ſaw the troubled field: The gleaming
   ridges of battle, disjoined and broken round. As diſtant fires, on heath by night, now ſeem as
   loſt in ſmoak; now rearing their red ſtreams on the hill, as blow or ceaſe the winds : ſo met the
   intermitting war the eye of broad-ſhielded Dermid. Thro' the hoſt are the ſtrides of Foldath,
   like ſome dark ſhip on wintry waves, when ſhe iſſues from between two iſles, to ſport on
   reſounding ocean !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Dermid</hi>, with rage, beholds his courſe. He ſtrives to ruſh along. But he
   fails amid his <!-- şteps -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210110" facs="../img/1773-371.pbm"/>
   <!-- 110 T E M O R A: Book V. --> ſteps; and the big tear comes down. He ſounds his father's
   horn. He thrice ſtrikes his boſſy ſhield. He calls thrice the name of Foldath, from his roaring
   tribes. Foldath, with joy, beholds the chief. He lifts aloft his bloody ſpear. As a rock is
   marked with ſtreams, that fell troubled down its ſide in a ſtorm; ſo, ſtreaked with wandering
   blood, is the dark chief of Morna ! The hoſt, on either ſide, withdraw from the contending of
   kings. They raiſe, at once, their gleaming points. Ruſhing comes Fillan of Selma. Three paces
   back Foldath withdraws, dazzled with that beam of light, which came, as iſſuing from a cloud, to
   ſave the wounded chief. Growing in his pride he ſtands. He calls forth all his ſteel.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">As</hi> meet two broad-winged eagles, in their ſounding ſtrife, in winds : ſo
   ruſh the two chiefs, on Moi-lena, into gloomy fight. By turns are the ſteps of the kings<note>
   <p> Fingal and Cathmor. </p>
   </note> forward on their rocks above; for now the duſky war ſeems to deſcend on their ſwords.
   Cathmor feels the joy of warriors, on his moſſy hill: their joy in ſecret, when dangers rife to
   match their ſouls. His eye is not turned on Lubar, but on Selma's dreadful king. He beholds him,
   on Mora, riſing in his arms. <!-- <sc>Foldath</sc> -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210111" facs="../img/1773-374.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. II --> </p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Foldath</hi><note>
   <p> The fall of Foldath, if we may believe tradition, was predicted to him, before he had left
    his own country to join Cairbar, in his deſigns on the Iriſh throne. He went to the cave of
    Morna, to enquire of the ſpirits of his fathers, concerning the ſucceſs of the enterpriſe of
    Cairbar. The reſponſes of oracles are always attended with obſcurity, and liable to a double
    meaning: Foldath, therefore, put a favourable interpretation on the prediction, and purſued his
    adopted plan of aggrandizing himſelf with the family of Atha. </p>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi rend="sc">Foldath</hi>, <hi>addreſſing the ſpirits of his fathers</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> Dark, I ſtand in your preſence; fathers of Foldath, hear. Shall my ſteps paſs over Atha, to
     Ullin of the roes ? </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
    <speaker><hi>The Anſwer</hi>.</speaker>
    <p> Thy ſteps ſhall paſs over Atha, to the green dwelling of kings. There ſhall thy ſtature
     ariſe, over the fallen, like a pillar of thunder-clouds. There, terrible in darkneſs, ſhalt
     thou ſtand, till the <hi>reflected beam</hi>, or <hi>Clon-cath</hi> of Moruth, come; Moruth of
     many ſtreams, that roars in diſtant lands.” </p>
   </sp>
   <p>Cloncath, or <hi>reflected beam</hi>, ſay my traditional authors, was the name of the ſword of
    Fillan; ſo that it was, in the latent ſignification of the word <hi>Clonath</hi>, that the
    deception lay. My principal reaſon for introducing this note, is, that this tradition ſerves to
    ſhew, that the religion of the Fir-bolg differed from that of the Caledonians, as we never find
    the latter enquiring of the ſpirits of their deceafed anceſtors. </p>
   </note> falls on his ſhield. The ſpear of Fillan pierced the king. Nor looks the youth on the
   fallen, but onward rolls the war. The hundred voices of death ariſe. “Stay, ſon of Fingal, ſtay
   thy ſpeed. Beholdeſt thou not that gleaming form, - a dreadful ſign of death ? <!-- Awaken -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210112" facs="../img/1773-377.pbm"/>
   <!-- 112 T E M O R A: Book V. --> Awaken not the king of Erin. Return, ſon of blue-eyed
   Clatho.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Malthos</hi><note>
   <p> The characters of Foldath and Malthos are ſuſtained. They were both dark and ſurly, but each
    in a different way. Foldath was impetuous and cruel., Malthos ſtubborn and incredulous. Their
    attachment to the family of Atha was equal; their bravery in battle the ſame. Foldath was vain
    and oſtentatious: Malthos unindulgent but generous. His behaviour here, towards his enemy
    Foldath, ſhews, that a good heart often lies concealed under a gloomy and ſullen character. </p>
   </note> beholds Foldath low. He darkly ſtands above the chief. Hatred is rolled from his ſoul. He
   ſeems a rock in a deſart, on whoſe dark ſide are the trickling of waters ; when the ſlow-ſailing
   miſt has left it, and all its trees are blaſted with winds. He ſpoke to the dying hero, about the
   narrow houſe. “Whether ſhall thy grey ſtone rife in Ullin, or in Morna's<note>
   <p> Morna was the name of a country in the ſouth of Connaught, once famous for being the
    reſidence of an Arch-Druid. The cave of Morna was thought to be inhabited by the ſpirits of the
    chiefs of the Fir-bolg, and their poſterity ſent to enquire there, as to an oracle, concerning
    the iſſue of their wars. </p>
   </note> woody land ? where the ſun looks, in ſecret, on the blue ſtreams of Dalrutho<note>
   <p> Dal ruäth, <hi>parched or ſandy field</hi>. The etymology of Dardulena is uncertain. The
    daughter of Foldath was, probably, ſo called, from a place in Ulſter, where her father had
    defeated part of the adherents of Artho, king of Ireland, Dor-du lena; <hi>the dark wood of
    Moi-lena</hi>. As Foldath was proud and oſtentatious, it would appear, that he transferred the
    name of a place, where he himſelf had been victorious, to his daughter. </p>
   </note> ? <!-- There -->
   <!-- lena ; -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210113" facs="../img/1773-380.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. 113 --> There are the ſteps of thy daughter, blue-eyed Dardu-lena
   !”</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Rememberest</hi> thou her,” ſaid Foldath, “becauſe no ſon is mine: no youth to
   roll the battle before him, in revenge of me ? Malthos, I am revenged. I was not peaceful in the
   field. Raiſe the tombs of thoſe I have ſlain, around my narrow houſe. Often ſhall I forſake the
   blaſt, to rejoice above their graves; when I behold them ſpread around, with their long-whiſtling
   graſs.”</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">His</hi> ſoul ruſhed to the vale of Morna, to Dardu-lena's dreams, where ſhe
   ſlept, by Dalrutho's ſtream, returning from the chace of the hinds. Her bow is near the maid,
   unſtrung. The breezes fold her long hair on her breaſts. Cloathed in the beauty of youth, the
   love of heroes lay. Dark-bending, from the ſkirts of the wood, her wounded father ſeemed to come.
   He appeared, at times, then hid himſelf in miſt. Burfting into tears ſhe roſe. She knew that the
   chief was low. To her came a beam from his ſoul, when folded in its ſtorms.
   <!-- Vol. II. I Thou -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210114" facs="../img/1773-383.pbm"/>
   <!-- 114 T E M O R A: Book V. --> Thou wert the laſt of his race, O blue-eyed Dardu-lena !</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Wide-spreading</hi> over ecchoing Lubar, the flight of Bolga is rolled along.
   Fillan hangs forward on their ſteps. He ſtrews, with dead, the heath. Fingal rejoices over his
   ſon. Blue-ſhielded Cathmor roſe<note>
   <p> “The ſuſpence, in which the mind of the reader is left here, conveys the idea of Fillan's
    danger more forcibly home, than any deſcription that could be introduced. There is a ſort of
    eloquence, in ſilence with propriety. A minute detail of the circumſtances of an important ſcene
    is generally cold and inſipid. The human mind, free and fond of thinking for itſelf, is
    diſguſted to find every thing done by the poet. It is, therefore, his buſineſs only to mark the
    moſt ſtriking out-lines, and to allow the imaginations of his readers to finiſh the figure for
    themſelves.”</p>
   <p>The book ends in the afternoon of the third day, from the opening of the poem. </p>
   </note>.</p>
  <p><hi rend="sc">Son</hi> of Alpin, bring the harp. Give Fillan's praiſe to the wind. Raiſe high
   his praiſe, in mine ear, while yet he ſhines in war.</p>
  <p>“<hi rend="sc">Leave</hi>, blue-eyed Clatho, leave thy hall ! Behold that early beam of thine!
   The hoſt is withered in its courſe. No further look, it is dark. Light-trembling from the harp,
   ſtrike, virgins, ſtrike the ſound. No hunter he deſcends, from the dewy haunt of the bounding
   roe. He bends not his bow on the wind ; nor ſends his grey arrow abroad. <!-- Deep --> </p>
  <p>
   <pb xml:id="P73210115" facs="../img/1773-386.pbm"/>
   <!-- Book V. An EPIC POEM. 115 --> <hi rend="sc">Deep-folded</hi> in red war! See battle roll
   againſt his ſide. Striding amid the ridgy ſtrife, he pours the deaths of thouſands forth. Fillan
   is like a ſpirit of heaven, that deſcends from the ſkirt of winds. The troubled ocean feels his
   ſteps, as he ſtrides from wave to wave. His path kindles behind him. Iſlands ſhake their heads on
   the heaving ſeas! Leave, blue-eyed Clatho, leave thy hall! <!-- 12 -->
   <pb xml:id="P73210116" facs="../img/1773-389.pbm"/> </p>
 </div>
</div>
